Author’s Note

Chance is one of my novels that shortly after having been begun were laid aside for a few months. Starting impetuously like a sanguine oarsman setting forth in the early morning I came very soon to a fork in the stream and found it necessary to pause and reflect seriously upon the direction I would take. Either presented to me equal fascinations, at least on the surface, and for that very reason my hesitation extended over many days. I floated in the calm water of pleasant speculation, between the diverging currents or conflicting impulses, with an agreeable but perfectly irrational conviction that neither of those currents would take me to destruction. My sympathies being equally divided and the two forces being equal it is perfectly obvious that nothing but mere chance influenced my decision in the end. It is a mighty force that of mere chance; absolutely irresistible yet manifesting itself often in delicate forms such for instance as the charm, true or illusory, of a human being. It is very difficult to put one’s finger on the imponderable, but I may venture to say that it is Flora de Barral who is really responsible for this novel which relates, in fact, the story of her life.

At the crucial moment of my indecision Flora de Barral passed before me, but so swiftly that I failed at first to get hold of her. Though loth to give her up I didn’t see the way of pursuit clearly and was on the point of becoming discouraged when my natural liking for Captain Anthony came to my assistance. I said to myself that if that man was so determined to embrace a “wisp of mist” the best thing for me was to join him in that eminently practical and praiseworthy adventure. I simply followed Captain Anthony. Each of us was bent on capturing his own dream. The reader will be able to judge of our success.

Captain Anthony’s determination led him a long and roundabout course and that is why this book is a long book. That the course was of my own choosing I will not deny. A critic had remarked that if I had selected another method of composition and taken a little more trouble the tale could have been told in about two hundred pages. I confess I do not perceive exactly the bearings of such criticism or even the use of such a remark. No doubt that by selecting a certain method and taking great pains the whole story might have been written out on a cigarette paper. For that matter, the whole history of mankind could be written thus if only approached with sufficient detachment. The history of men on this earth since the beginning of ages may be resumed in one phrase of infinite poignancy: They were born, they suffered, they died. … Yet it is a great tale! But in the infinitely minute stories about men and women it is my lot on earth to narrate I am not capable of such detachment.

What makes this book memorable to me apart from the natural sentiment one has for one’s creation is the response it provoked. The general public responded largely, more largely perhaps than to any other book of mine, in the only way the general public can respond, that is by buying a certain number of copies. This gave me a considerable amount of pleasure, because what I always feared most was drifting unconsciously into the position of a writer for a limited coterie; a position which would have been odious to me as throwing a doubt on the soundness of my belief in the solidarity of all mankind in simple ideas and in sincere emotions. Regarded as a manifestation of criticism (for it would be outrageous to deny to the general public the possession of a critical mind) the reception was very satisfactory. I saw that I had managed to please a certain number of minds busy attending to their own very real affairs. It is agreeable to think one is able to please. From the minds whose business it is precisely to criticize such attempts to please, this book received an amount of discussion and of a rather searching analysis which not only satisfied that personal vanity I share with the rest of mankind but reached my deeper feelings and aroused my gratified interest. The undoubted sympathy informing the varied appreciations of that book was, I love to think, a recognition of my good faith in the pursuit of my art—the art of the novelist which a distinguished French writer at the end of a successful career complained of as being: Trop difficile! It is indeed too arduous in the sense that the effort must be invariably so much greater than the possible achievement. In that sort of foredoomed task which is in its nature very lonely also, sympathy is a precious thing. It can make the most severe criticism welcome. To be told that better things have been expected of one may be soothing in view of how much better things one had expected from oneself in this art which, in these days, is no longer justified by the assumption, somewhere and somehow, of a didactic purpose.

I do not mean to hint that anybody had ever done me the injury (I don’t mean insult, I mean injury) of charging a single one of my pages with didactic purpose. But every subject in the region of intellect and emotion must have a morality of its own if it is treated at all sincerely; and even the most artful of writers will give himself (and his morality) away in about every third sentence. The varied shades of moral significance which have been discovered in my writings are very numerous. None of them, however, have provoked a hostile manifestation. It may have happened to me to sin against taste now and then, but apparently I have never sinned against the basic feelings and elementary convictions which make life possible to the mass of mankind and, by establishing a standard of judgment, set their idealism free to look for plainer ways, for higher feelings, for deeper purposes.

I cannot say that any particular moral complexion has been put on this novel but I do not think that anybody had detected in it an evil intention. And it is only for their intentions that men can be held responsible. The ultimate effects of whatever they do are far beyond their control. In doing this book my intention was to interest people in my vision of things which is indissolubly allied to the style in which it is expressed. In other words I wanted to write a certain amount of pages in prose, which, strictly speaking, is my proper business. I have attended to it conscientiously with the hope of being entertaining or at least not insufferably boring to my readers. I can not sufficiently insist upon the truth that when I sit down to write my intentions are always blameless however deplorable the ultimate effect of the act may turn out to be.

J. C.

1920

II

The Fynes and the Girl-Friend

We were on our feet in the room by then, and Marlow, brown and deliberate, approached the window where Mr.¬ÝPowell and I had retired. ‚ÄúWhat was the name of your chance again?‚Äù he asked. Mr.¬ÝPowell stared for a moment.

‚ÄúOh! The Ferndale. A Liverpool ship. Composite built.‚Äù

‚ÄúFerndale,‚Äù repeated Marlow thoughtfully. ‚ÄúFerndale.‚Äù

‚ÄúKnow her?‚Äù

‚ÄúOur friend,‚Äù I said, ‚Äúknows something of every ship. He seems to have gone about the seas prying into things considerably.‚Äù

Marlow smiled.

‚ÄúI‚Äôve seen her, at least once.‚Äù

‚ÄúThe finest sea-boat ever launched,‚Äù declared Mr.¬ÝPowell sturdily. ‚ÄúWithout exception.‚Äù

‚ÄúShe looked a stout, comfortable ship,‚Äù assented Marlow. ‚ÄúUncommonly comfortable. Not very fast tho‚Äô.‚Äù

‚ÄúShe was fast enough for any reasonable man‚ÅÝ‚Äîwhen I was in her,‚Äù growled Mr.¬ÝPowell with his back to us.

‚ÄúAny ship is that‚ÅÝ‚Äîfor a reasonable man,‚Äù generalized Marlow in a conciliatory tone. ‚ÄúA sailor isn‚Äôt a globe-trotter.‚Äù

‚ÄúNo,‚Äù muttered Mr.¬ÝPowell.

‚ÄúTime‚Äôs nothing to him,‚Äù advanced Marlow.

‚ÄúI don‚Äôt suppose it‚Äôs much,‚Äù said Mr.¬ÝPowell. ‚ÄúAll the same a quick passage is a feather in a man‚Äôs cap.‚Äù

‚ÄúTrue. But that ornament is for the use of the master only. And by the by what was his name?‚Äù

‚ÄúThe master of the Ferndale? Anthony. Captain Anthony.‚Äù

‚ÄúJust so. Quite right,‚Äù approved Marlow thoughtfully. Our new acquaintance looked over his shoulder.

‚ÄúWhat do you mean? Why is it more right than if it had been Brown?‚Äù

‚ÄúHe has known him probably,‚Äù I explained. ‚ÄúMarlow here appears to know something of every soul that ever went afloat in a sailor‚Äôs body.‚Äù

Mr.¬ÝPowell seemed wonderfully amenable to verbal suggestions for looking again out of the window, he muttered:

‚ÄúHe was a good soul.‚Äù

This clearly referred to Captain Anthony of the Ferndale. Marlow addressed his protest to me.

‚ÄúI did not know him. I really didn‚Äôt. He was a good soul. That‚Äôs nothing very much out of the way‚ÅÝ‚Äîis it? And I didn‚Äôt even know that much of him. All I knew of him was an accident called Fyne.

At this Mr.¬ÝPowell who evidently could be rebellious too turned his back squarely on the window.

‚ÄúWhat on earth do you mean?‚Äù he asked. ‚ÄúAn‚ÅÝ‚Äîaccident‚ÅÝ‚Äîcalled Fyne,‚Äù he repeated separating the words with emphasis.

Marlow was not disconcerted.

‚ÄúI don‚Äôt mean accident in the sense of a mishap. Not in the least. Fyne was a good little man in the Civil Service. By accident I mean that which happens blindly and without intelligent design. That‚Äôs generally the way a brother-in-law happens into a man‚Äôs life.‚Äù

Marlow‚Äôs tone being apologetic and our new acquaintance having again turned to the window I took it upon myself to say:

‚ÄúYou are justified. There is very little intelligent design in the majority of marriages; but they are none the worse for that. Intelligence leads people astray as far as passion sometimes. I know you are not a cynic.‚Äù

Marlow smiled his retrospective smile which was kind as though he bore no grudge against people he used to know.

‚ÄúLittle Fyne‚Äôs marriage was quite successful. There was no design at all in it. Fyne, you must know, was an enthusiastic pedestrian. He spent his holidays tramping all over our native land. His tastes were simple. He put infinite conviction and perseverance into his holidays. At the proper season you would meet in the fields, Fyne, a serious-faced, broad-chested, little man, with a shabby knap-sack on his back, making for some church steeple. He had a horror of roads. He wrote once a little book called the ‚ÄòTramp‚Äôs Itinerary,‚Äô and was recognised as an authority on the footpaths of England. So one year, in his favourite over-the-fields, back-way fashion he entered a pretty Surrey village where he met Miss Anthony. Pure accident, you see. They came to an understanding, across some stile, most likely. Little Fyne held very solemn views as to the destiny of women on this earth, the nature of our sublunary love, the obligations of this transient life and so on. He probably disclosed them to his future wife. Miss Anthony‚Äôs views of life were very decided too but in a different way. I don‚Äôt know the story of their wooing. I imagine it was carried on clandestinely and, I am certain, with portentous gravity, at the back of copses, behind hedges‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶

‚ÄúWhy was it carried on clandestinely?‚Äù I inquired.

‚ÄúBecause of the lady‚Äôs father. He was a savage sentimentalist who had his own decided views of his paternal prerogatives. He was a terror; but the only evidence of imaginative faculty about Fyne was his pride in his wife‚Äôs parentage. It stimulated his ingenuity too. Difficult‚ÅÝ‚Äîis it not?‚ÅÝ‚Äîto introduce one‚Äôs wife‚Äôs maiden name into general conversation. But my simple Fyne made use of Captain Anthony for that purpose, or else I would never even have heard of the man. ‚ÄúMy wife‚Äôs sailor-brother‚Äù was the phrase. He trotted out the sailor-brother in a pretty wide range of subjects: Indian and colonial affairs, matters of trade, talk of travels, of seaside holidays and so on. Once I remember ‚ÄúMy wife‚Äôs sailor-brother Captain Anthony‚Äù being produced in connection with nothing less recondite than a sunset. And little Fyne never failed to add ‚ÄúThe son of Carleon Anthony, the poet‚ÅÝ‚Äîyou know.‚Äù He used to lower his voice for that statement, and people were impressed or pretended to be.‚Äù

The late Carleon Anthony, the poet, sang in his time of the domestic and social amenities of our age with a most felicitous versification, his object being, in his own words, ‚Äúto glorify the result of six thousand years‚Äô evolution towards the refinement of thought, manners and feelings.‚Äù Why he fixed the term at six thousand years I don‚Äôt know. His poems read like sentimental novels told in verse of a really superior quality. You felt as if you were being taken out for a delightful country drive by a charming lady in a pony carriage. But in his domestic life that same Carleon Anthony showed traces of the primitive cave-dweller‚Äôs temperament. He was a massive, implacable man with a handsome face, arbitrary and exacting with his dependants, but marvellously suave in his manner to admiring strangers. These contrasted displays must have been particularly exasperating to his long-suffering family. After his second wife‚Äôs death his boy, whom he persisted by a mere whim in educating at home, ran away in conventional style and, as if disgusted with the amenities of civilization, threw himself, figuratively speaking, into the sea. The daughter (the elder of the two children) either from compassion or because women are naturally more enduring, remained in bondage to the poet for several years, till she too seized a chance of escape by throwing herself into the arms, the muscular arms, of the pedestrian Fyne. This was either great luck or great sagacity. A civil servant is, I should imagine, the last human being in the world to preserve those traits of the cave-dweller from which she was fleeing. Her father would never consent to see her after the marriage. Such unforgiving selfishness is difficult to understand unless as a perverse sort of refinement. There were also doubts as to Carleon Anthony‚Äôs complete sanity for some considerable time before he died.

Most of the above I elicited from Marlow, for all I knew of Carleon Anthony was his unexciting but fascinating verse. Marlow assured me that the Fyne marriage was perfectly successful and even happy, in an earnest, unplayful fashion, being blessed besides by three healthy, active, self-reliant children, all girls. They were all pedestrians too. Even the youngest would wander away for miles if not restrained. Mrs.¬ÝFyne had a ruddy out-of-doors complexion and wore blouses with a starched front like a man‚Äôs shirt, a stand-up collar and a long necktie. Marlow had made their acquaintance one summer in the country, where they were accustomed to take a cottage for the holidays‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶

At this point we were interrupted by Mr.¬ÝPowell who declared that he must leave us. The tide was on the turn, he announced coming away from the window abruptly. He wanted to be on board his cutter before she swung and of course he would sleep on board. Never slept away from the cutter while on a cruise. He was gone in a moment, unceremoniously, but giving us no offence and leaving behind an impression as though we had known him for a long time. The ingenuous way he had told us of his start in life had something to do with putting him on that footing with us. I gave no thought to seeing him again.

Marlow expressed a confident hope of coming across him before long.

‚ÄúHe cruises about the mouth of the river all the summer. He will be easy to find any week-end,‚Äù he remarked ringing the bell so that we might settle up with the waiter.

* * * * *

Later on I asked Marlow why he wished to cultivate this chance acquaintance. He confessed apologetically that it was the commonest sort of curiosity. I flatter myself that I understand all sorts of curiosity. Curiosity about daily facts, about daily things, about daily men. It is the most respectable faculty of the human mind‚ÅÝ‚Äîin fact I cannot conceive the uses of an incurious mind. It would be like a chamber perpetually locked up. But in this particular case Mr.¬ÝPowell seemed to have given us already a complete insight into his personality such as it was; a personality capable of perception and with a feeling for the vagaries of fate, but essentially simple in itself.

Marlow agreed with me so far. He explained however that his curiosity was not excited by Mr.¬ÝPowell exclusively. It originated a good way further back in the fact of his accidental acquaintance with the Fynes, in the country. This chance meeting with a man who had sailed with Captain Anthony had revived it. It had revived it to some purpose, to such purpose that to me too was given the knowledge of its origin and of its nature. It was given to me in several stages, at intervals which are not indicated here. On this first occasion I remarked to Marlow with some surprise:

‚ÄúBut, if I remember rightly you said you didn‚Äôt know Captain Anthony.‚Äù

‚ÄúNo. I never saw the man. It‚Äôs years ago now, but I seem to hear solemn little Fyne‚Äôs deep voice announcing the approaching visit of his wife‚Äôs brother ‚Äúthe son of the poet, you know.‚Äù He had just arrived in London from a long voyage, and, directly his occupations permitted, was coming down to stay with his relatives for a few weeks. No doubt we two should find many things to talk about by ourselves in reference to our common calling, added little Fyne portentously in his grave undertones, as if the Mercantile Marine were a secret society.

You must understand that I cultivated the Fynes only in the country, in their holiday time. This was the third year. Of their existence in town I knew no more than may be inferred from analogy. I played chess with Fyne in the late afternoon, and sometimes came over to the cottage early enough to have tea with the whole family at a big round table. They sat about it, an unsmiling, sunburnt company of very few words indeed. Even the children were silent and as if contemptuous of each other and of their elders. Fyne muttered sometimes deep down in his chest some insignificant remark. Mrs.¬ÝFyne smiled mechanically (she had splendid teeth) while distributing tea and bread and butter. A something which was not coldness, nor yet indifference, but a sort of peculiar self-possession gave her the appearance of a very trustworthy, very capable and excellent governess; as if Fyne were a widower and the children not her own but only entrusted to her calm, efficient, unemotional care. One expected her to address Fyne as Mr.¬ÝWhen she called him John it surprised one like a shocking familiarity. The atmosphere of that holiday was‚ÅÝ‚Äîif I may put it so‚ÅÝ‚Äîbrightly dull. Healthy faces, fair complexions, clear eyes, and never a frank smile in the whole lot, unless perhaps from a girl-friend.

The girl-friend problem exercised me greatly. How and where the Fynes got all these pretty creatures to come and stay with them I can‚Äôt imagine. I had at first the wild suspicion that they were obtained to amuse Fyne. But I soon discovered that he could hardly tell one from the other, though obviously their presence met with his solemn approval. These girls in fact came for Mrs.¬ÝFyne. They treated her with admiring deference. She answered to some need of theirs. They sat at her feet. They were like disciples. It was very curious. Of Fyne they took but scanty notice. As to myself I was made to feel that I did not exist.

After tea we would sit down to chess and then Fyne‚Äôs everlasting gravity became faintly tinged by an attenuated gleam of something inward which resembled sly satisfaction. Of the divine frivolity of laughter he was only capable over a chess-board. Certain positions of the game struck him as humorous, which nothing else on earth could do‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶

‚ÄúHe used to beat you,‚Äù I asserted with confidence.

‚ÄúYes. He used to beat me,‚Äù Marlow owned up hastily.

So he and Fyne played two games after tea. The children romped together outside, gravely, unplayfully, as one would expect from Fyne‚Äôs children, and Mrs.¬ÝFyne would be gone to the bottom of the garden with the girl-friend of the week. She always walked off directly after tea with her arm round the girl-friend‚Äôs waist. Marlow said that there was only one girl-friend with whom he had conversed at all. It had happened quite unexpectedly, long after he had given up all hope of getting into touch with these reserved girl-friends.

One day he saw a woman walking about on the edge of a high quarry, which rose a sheer hundred feet, at least, from the road winding up the hill out of which it had been excavated. He shouted warningly to her from below where he happened to be passing. She was really in considerable danger. At the sound of his voice she started back and retreated out of his sight amongst some young Scotch firs growing near the very brink of the precipice.

‚ÄúI sat down on a bank of grass,‚Äù Marlow went on. ‚ÄúShe had given me a turn. The hem of her skirt seemed to float over that awful sheer drop, she was so close to the edge. An absurd thing to do. A perfectly mad trick‚ÅÝ‚Äîfor no conceivable object! I was reflecting on the foolhardiness of the average girl and remembering some other instances of the kind, when she came into view walking down the steep curve of the road. She had Mrs.¬ÝFyne‚Äôs walking-stick and was escorted by the Fyne dog. Her dead white face struck me with astonishment, so that I forgot to raise my hat. I just sat and stared. The dog, a vivacious and amiable animal which for some inscrutable reason had bestowed his friendship on my unworthy self, rushed up the bank demonstratively and insinuated himself under my arm.

The girl-friend (it was one of them) went past some way as though she had not seen me, then stopped and called the dog to her several times; but he only nestled closer to my side, and when I tried to push him away developed that remarkable power of internal resistance by which a dog makes himself practically immovable by anything short of a kick. She looked over her shoulder and her arched eyebrows frowned above her blanched face. It was almost a scowl. Then the expression changed. She looked unhappy. ‚ÄúCome here!‚Äù she cried once more in an angry and distressed tone. I took off my hat at last, but the dog hanging out his tongue with that cheerfully imbecile expression some dogs know so well how to put on when it suits their purpose, pretended to be deaf.

She cried from the distance desperately.

‚ÄúPerhaps you will take him to the cottage then. I can‚Äôt wait.‚Äù

‚ÄúI won‚Äôt be responsible for that dog,‚Äù I protested getting down the bank and advancing towards her. She looked very hurt, apparently by the desertion of the dog. ‚ÄúBut if you let me walk with you he will follow us all right,‚Äù I suggested.

She moved on without answering me. The dog launched himself suddenly full speed down the road receding from us in a small cloud of dust. It vanished in the distance, and presently we came up with him lying on the grass. He panted in the shade of the hedge with shining eyes but pretended not to see us. We had not exchanged a word so far. The girl by my side gave him a scornful glance in passing.

‚ÄúHe offered to come with me,‚Äù she remarked bitterly.

‚ÄúAnd then abandoned you!‚Äù I sympathized. ‚ÄúIt looks very unchivalrous. But that‚Äôs merely his want of tact. I believe he meant to protest against your reckless proceedings. What made you come so near the edge of that quarry? The earth might have given way. Haven‚Äôt you noticed a smashed fir tree at the bottom? Tumbled over only the other morning after a night‚Äôs rain.‚Äù

‚ÄúI don‚Äôt see why I shouldn‚Äôt be as reckless as I please.‚Äù

I was nettled by her brusque manner of asserting her folly, and I told her that neither did I as far as that went, in a tone which almost suggested that she was welcome to break her neck for all I cared. This was considerably more than I meant, but I don‚Äôt like rude girls. I had been introduced to her only the day before‚ÅÝ‚Äîat the round tea-table‚ÅÝ‚Äîand she had barely acknowledged the introduction. I had not caught her name but I had noticed her fine, arched eyebrows which, so the physiognomists say, are a sign of courage.

I examined her appearance quietly. Her hair was nearly black, her eyes blue, deeply shaded by long dark eyelashes. She had a little colour now. She looked straight before her; the corner of her lip on my side drooped a little; her chin was fine, somewhat pointed. I went on to say that some regard for others should stand in the way of one‚Äôs playing with danger. I urged playfully the distress of the poor Fynes in case of accident, if nothing else. I told her that she did not know the bucolic mind. Had she given occasion for a coroner‚Äôs inquest the verdict would have been suicide, with the implication of unhappy love. They would never be able to understand that she had taken the trouble to climb over two post-and-rail fences only for the fun of being reckless. Indeed even as I talked chaffingly I was greatly struck myself by the fact.

She retorted that once one was dead what horrid people thought of one did not matter. It was said with infinite contempt; but something like a suppressed quaver in the voice made me look at her again. I perceived then that her thick eyelashes were wet. This surprising discovery silenced me as you may guess. She looked unhappy. And‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI don‚Äôt know how to say it‚ÅÝ‚Äîwell‚ÅÝ‚Äîit suited her. The clouded brow, the pained mouth, the vague fixed glance! A victim. And this characteristic aspect made her attractive; an individual touch‚ÅÝ‚Äîyou know.

The dog had run on ahead and now gazed at us by the side of the Fyne‚Äôs garden-gate in a tense attitude and wagging his stumpy tail very, very slowly, with an air of concentrated attention. The girl-friend of the Fynes bolted violently through the aforesaid gate and into the cottage leaving me on the road‚ÅÝ‚Äîastounded.

A couple of hours afterwards I returned to the cottage for chess as usual. I saw neither the girl nor Mrs.¬ÝFyne then. We had our two games and on parting I warned Fyne that I was called to town on business and might be away for some time. He regretted it very much. His brother-in-law was expected next day but he didn‚Äôt know whether he was a chess-player. Captain Anthony (‚Äúthe son of the poet‚ÅÝ‚Äîyou know‚Äù) was of a retiring disposition, shy with strangers, unused to society and very much devoted to his calling, Fyne explained. All the time they had been married he could be induced only once before to come and stay with them for a few days. He had had a rather unhappy boyhood; and it made him a silent man. But no doubt, concluded Fyne, as if dealing portentously with a mystery, we two sailors should find much to say to one another.

This point was never settled. I was detained in town from week to week till it seemed hardly worth while to go back. But as I had kept on my rooms in the farmhouse I concluded to go down again for a few days.

It was late, deep dusk, when I got out at our little country station. My eyes fell on the unmistakable broad back and the muscular legs in cycling stockings of little Fyne. He passed along the carriages rapidly towards the rear of the train, which presently pulled out and left him solitary at the end of the rustic platform. When he came back to where I waited I perceived that he was much perturbed, so perturbed as to forget the convention of the usual greetings. He only exclaimed Oh! on recognizing me, and stopped irresolute. When I asked him if he had been expecting somebody by that train he didn‚Äôt seem to know. He stammered disconnectedly. I looked hard at him. To all appearances he was perfectly sober; moreover to suspect Fyne of a lapse from the proprieties high or low, great or small, was absurd. He was also a too serious and deliberate person to go mad suddenly. But as he seemed to have forgotten that he had a tongue in his head I concluded I would leave him to his mystery. To my surprise he followed me out of the station and kept by my side, though I did not encourage him. I did not however repulse his attempts at conversation. He was no longer expecting me, he said. He had given me up. The weather had been uniformly fine‚ÅÝ‚Äîand so on. I gathered also that the son of the poet had curtailed his stay somewhat and gone back to his ship the day before.

That information touched me but little. Believing in heredity in moderation I knew well how sea-life fashions a man outwardly and stamps his soul with the mark of a certain prosaic fitness‚ÅÝ‚Äîbecause a sailor is not an adventurer. I expressed no regret at missing Captain Anthony and we proceeded in silence till, on approaching the holiday cottage, Fyne suddenly and unexpectedly broke it by the hurried declaration that he would go on with me a little farther.

‚ÄúGo with you to your door,‚Äù he mumbled and started forward to the little gate where the shadowy figure of Mrs.¬ÝFyne hovered, clearly on the lookout for him. She was alone. The children must have been already in bed and I saw no attending girl-friend shadow near her vague but unmistakable form, half-lost in the obscurity of the little garden.

I heard Fyne exclaim ‚ÄúNothing‚Äù and then Mrs.¬ÝFyne‚Äôs well-trained, responsible voice uttered the words, ‚ÄúIt‚Äôs what I have said,‚Äù with incisive equanimity. By that time I had passed on, raising my hat. Almost at once Fyne caught me up and slowed down to my strolling gait which must have been infinitely irksome to his high pedestrian faculties. I am sure that all his muscular person must have suffered from awful physical boredom; but he did not attempt to charm it away by conversation. He preserved a portentous and dreary silence. And I was bored too. Suddenly I perceived the menace of even worse boredom. Yes! He was so silent because he had something to tell me.

I became extremely frightened. But man, reckless animal, is so made that in him curiosity, the paltriest curiosity, will overcome all terrors, every disgust, and even despair itself. To my laconic invitation to come in for a drink he answered by a deep, gravely accented: ‚ÄúThanks, I will‚Äù as though it were a response in church. His face as seen in the lamplight gave me no clue to the character of the impending communication; as indeed from the nature of things it couldn‚Äôt do, its normal expression being already that of the utmost possible seriousness. It was perfect and immovable; and for a certainty if he had something excruciatingly funny to tell me it would be all the same.

He gazed at me earnestly and delivered himself of some weighty remarks on Mrs.¬ÝFyne‚Äôs desire to befriend, counsel, and guide young girls of all sorts on the path of life. It was a voluntary mission. He approved his wife‚Äôs action and also her views and principles in general.

All this with a solemn countenance and in deep measured tones. Yet somehow I got an irresistible conviction that he was exasperated by something in particular. In the unworthy hope of being amused by the misfortunes of a fellow-creature I asked him point-blank what was wrong now.

What was wrong was that a girl-friend was missing. She had been missing precisely since six o‚Äôclock that morning. The woman who did the work of the cottage saw her going out at that hour, for a walk. The pedestrian Fyne‚Äôs ideas of a walk were extensive, but the girl did not turn up for lunch, nor yet for tea, nor yet for dinner. She had not turned up by footpath, road or rail. He had been reluctant to make inquiries. It would have set all the village talking. The Fynes had expected her to reappear every moment, till the shades of the night and the silence of slumber had stolen gradually over the wide and peaceful rural landscape commanded by the cottage.

After telling me that much Fyne sat helpless in unconclusive agony. Going to bed was out of the question‚ÅÝ‚Äîneither could any steps be taken just then. What to do with himself he did not know!

I asked him if this was the same young lady I saw a day or two before I went to town? He really could not remember. Was she a girl with dark hair and blue eyes? I asked further. He really couldn‚Äôt tell what colour her eyes were. He was very unobservant except as to the peculiarities of footpaths, on which he was an authority.

I thought with amazement and some admiration that Mrs.¬ÝFyne‚Äôs young disciples were to her husband‚Äôs gravity no more than evanescent shadows. However, with but little hesitation Fyne ventured to affirm that‚ÅÝ‚Äîyes, her hair was of some dark shade.

‚ÄúWe had a good deal to do with that girl first and last,‚Äù he explained solemnly; then getting up as if moved by a spring he snatched his cap off the table. ‚ÄúShe may be back in the cottage,‚Äù he cried in his bass voice. I followed him out on the road.

It was one of those dewy, clear, starry nights, oppressing our spirit, crushing our pride, by the brilliant evidence of the awful loneliness, of the hopeless obscure insignificance of our globe lost in the splendid revelation of a glittering, soulless universe. I hate such skies. Daylight is friendly to man toiling under a sun which warms his heart; and cloudy soft nights are more kindly to our littleness. I nearly ran back again to my lighted parlour; Fyne fussing in a knicker-bocker suit before the hosts of heaven, on a shadowy earth, about a transient, phantom-like girl, seemed too ridiculous to associate with. On the other hand there was something fascinating in the very absurdity. He cut along in his best pedestrian style and I found myself let in for a spell of severe exercise at eleven o‚Äôclock at night.

In the distance over the fields and trees smudging and blotching the vast obscurity, one lighted window of the cottage with the blind up was like a bright beacon kept alight to guide the lost wanderer. Inside, at the table bearing the lamp, we saw Mrs.¬ÝFyne sitting with folded arms and not a hair of her head out of place. She looked exactly like a governess who had put the children to bed; and her manner to me was just the neutral manner of a governess. To her husband, too, for that matter.

Fyne told her that I was fully informed. Not a muscle of her ruddy smooth handsome face moved. She had schooled herself into that sort of thing. Having seen two successive wives of the delicate poet chivied and worried into their graves, she had adopted that cool, detached manner to meet her gifted father‚Äôs outbreaks of selfish temper. It had now become a second nature. I suppose she was always like that; even in the very hour of elopement with Fyne. That transaction when one remembered it in her presence acquired a quaintly marvellous aspect to one‚Äôs imagination. But somehow her self-possession matched very well little Fyne‚Äôs invariable solemnity.

I was rather sorry for him. Wasn‚Äôt he worried! The agony of solemnity. At the same time I was amused. I didn‚Äôt take a gloomy view of that ‚Äúvanishing girl‚Äù trick. Somehow I couldn‚Äôt. But I said nothing. None of us said anything. We sat about that big round table as if assembled for a conference and looked at each other in a sort of fatuous consternation. I would have ended by laughing outright if I had not been saved from that impropriety by poor Fyne becoming preposterous.

He began with grave anguish to talk of going to the police in the morning, of printing descriptive bills, of setting people to drag the ponds for miles around. It was extremely gruesome. I murmured something about communicating with the young lady‚Äôs relatives. It seemed to me a very natural suggestion; but Fyne and his wife exchanged such a significant glance that I felt as though I had made a tactless remark.

But I really wanted to help poor Fyne; and as I could see that, manlike, he suffered from the present inability to act, the passive waiting, I said: ‚ÄúNothing of this can be done till to-morrow. But as you have given me an insight into the nature of your thoughts I can tell you what may be done at once. We may go and look at the bottom of the old quarry which is on the level of the road, about a mile from here.‚Äù

The couple made big eyes at this, and then I told them of my meeting with the girl. You may be surprised but I assure you I had not perceived this aspect of it till that very moment. It was like a startling revelation; the past throwing a sinister light on the future. Fyne opened his mouth gravely and as gravely shut it. Nothing more. Mrs.¬ÝFyne said, ‚ÄúYou had better go,‚Äù with an air as if her self-possession had been pricked with a pin in some secret place.

And I‚ÅÝ‚Äîyou know how stupid I can be at times‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI perceived with dismay for the first time that by pandering to Fyne‚Äôs morbid fancies I had let myself in for some more severe exercise. And wasn‚Äôt I sorry I spoke! You know how I hate walking‚ÅÝ‚Äîat least on solid, rural earth; for I can walk a ship‚Äôs deck a whole foggy night through, if necessary, and think little of it. There is some satisfaction too in playing the vagabond in the streets of a big town till the sky pales above the ridges of the roofs. I have done that repeatedly for pleasure‚ÅÝ‚Äîof a sort. But to tramp the slumbering country-side in the dark is for me a wearisome nightmare of exertion.

With perfect detachment Mrs.¬ÝFyne watched me go out after her husband. That woman was flint.

* * * * *

The fresh night had a smell of soil, of turned-up sods like a grave‚ÅÝ‚Äîan association particularly odious to a sailor by its idea of confinement and narrowness; yes, even when he has given up the hope of being buried at sea; about the last hope a sailor gives up consciously after he has been, as it does happen, decoyed by some chance into the toils of the land. A strong grave-like sniff. The ditch by the side of the road must have been freshly dug in front of the cottage.

Once clear of the garden Fyne gathered way like a racing cutter. What was a mile to him‚ÅÝ‚Äîor twenty miles? You think he might have gone shrinkingly on such an errand. But not a bit of it. The force of pedestrian genius I suppose. I raced by his side in a mood of profound self-derision, and infinitely vexed with that minx. Because dead or alive I thought of her as a minx‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶‚Äù

I smiled incredulously at Marlow‚Äôs ferocity; but Marlow pausing with a whimsically retrospective air, never flinched.

‚ÄúYes, yes. Even dead. And now you are shocked. You see, you are such a chivalrous masculine beggar. But there is enough of the woman in my nature to free my judgment of women from glamorous reticency. And then, why should I upset myself? A woman is not necessarily either a doll or an angel to me. She is a human being, very much like myself. And I have come across too many dead souls lying so to speak at the foot of high unscaleable places for a merely possible dead body at the bottom of a quarry to strike my sincerity dumb.

The cliff-like face of the quarry looked forbiddingly impressive. I will admit that Fyne and I hung back for a moment before we made a plunge off the road into the bushes growing in a broad space at the foot of the towering limestone wall. These bushes were heavy with dew. There were also concealed mudholes in there. We crept and tumbled and felt about with our hands along the ground. We got wet, scratched, and plastered with mire all over our nether garments. Fyne fell suddenly into a strange cavity‚ÅÝ‚Äîprobably a disused lime-kiln. His voice uplifted in grave distress sounded more than usually rich, solemn and profound. This was the comic relief of an absurdly dramatic situation. While hauling him out I permitted myself to laugh aloud at last. Fyne, of course, didn‚Äôt.

I need not tell you that we found nothing after a most conscientious search. Fyne even pushed his way into a decaying shed half-buried in dew-soaked vegetation. He struck matches, several of them too, as if to make absolutely sure that the vanished girl-friend of his wife was not hiding there. The short flares illuminated his grave, immovable countenance while I let myself go completely and laughed in peals.

I asked him if he really and truly supposed that any sane girl would go and hide in that shed; and if so why?

Disdainful of my mirth he merely muttered his basso-profundo thankfulness that we had not found her anywhere about there. Having grown extremely sensitive (an effect of irritation) to the tonalities, I may say, of this affair, I felt that it was only an imperfect, reserved, thankfulness, with one eye still on the possibilities of the several ponds in the neighbourhood. And I remember I snorted, I positively snorted, at that poor Fyne.

What really jarred upon me was the rate of his walking. Differences in politics, in ethics and even in aesthetics need not arouse angry antagonism. One‚Äôs opinion may change; one‚Äôs tastes may alter‚ÅÝ‚Äîin fact they do. One‚Äôs very conception of virtue is at the mercy of some felicitous temptation which may be sprung on one any day. All these things are perpetually on the swing. But a temperamental difference, temperament being immutable, is the parent of hate. That‚Äôs why religious quarrels are the fiercest of all. My temperament, in matters pertaining to solid land, is the temperament of leisurely movement, of deliberate gait. And there was that little Fyne pounding along the road in a most offensive manner; a man wedded to thick-soled, laced boots; whereas my temperament demands thin shoes of the lightest kind. Of course there could never have been question of friendship between us; but under the provocation of having to keep up with his pace I began to dislike him actively. I begged sarcastically to know whether he could tell me if we were engaged in a farce or in a tragedy. I wanted to regulate my feelings which, I told him, were in an unbecoming state of confusion.

But Fyne was as impervious to sarcasm as a turtle. He tramped on, and all he did was to ejaculate twice out of his deep chest, vaguely, doubtfully.

‚ÄúI am afraid‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ I am afraid!‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶‚Äù

This was tragic. The thump of his boots was the only sound in a shadowy world. I kept by his side with a comparatively ghostly, silent tread. By a strange illusion the road appeared to run up against a lot of low stars at no very great distance, but as we advanced new stretches of whitey-brown ribbon seemed to come up from under the black ground. I observed, as we went by, the lamp in my parlour in the farmhouse still burning. But I did not leave Fyne to run in and put it out. The impetus of his pedestrian excellence carried me past in his wake before I could make up my mind.

‚ÄúTell me, Fyne,‚Äù I cried, ‚Äúyou don‚Äôt think the girl was mad‚ÅÝ‚Äîdo you?‚Äù

He answered nothing. Soon the lighted beacon-like window of the cottage came into view. Then Fyne uttered a solemn: ‚ÄúCertainly not,‚Äù with profound assurance. But immediately after he added a ‚ÄúVery highly strung young person indeed,‚Äù which unsettled me again. Was it a tragedy?

‚ÄúNobody ever got up at six o‚Äôclock in the morning to commit suicide,‚Äù I declared crustily. ‚ÄúIt‚Äôs unheard of! This is a farce.‚Äù

As a matter of fact it was neither farce nor tragedy.

Coming up to the cottage we had a view of Mrs.¬ÝFyne inside still sitting in the strong light at the round table with folded arms. It looked as though she had not moved her very head by as much as an inch since we went away. She was amazing in a sort of unsubtle way; crudely amazing‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI thought. Why crudely? I don‚Äôt know. Perhaps because I saw her then in a crude light. I mean this materially‚ÅÝ‚Äîin the light of an unshaded lamp. Our mental conclusions depend so much on momentary physical sensations‚ÅÝ‚Äîdon‚Äôt they? If the lamp had been shaded I should perhaps have gone home after expressing politely my concern at the Fynes‚Äô unpleasant predicament.

Losing a girl-friend in that manner is unpleasant. It is also mysterious. So mysterious that a certain mystery attaches to the people to whom such a thing does happen. Moreover I had never really understood the Fynes; he with his solemnity which extended to the very eating of bread and butter; she with that air of detachment and resolution in breasting the common-place current of their unexciting life, in which the cutting of bread and butter appeared to me, by a long way, the most dangerous episode. Sometimes I amused myself by supposing that to their minds this world of ours must be wearing a perfectly overwhelming aspect, and that their heads contained respectively awfully serious and extremely desperate thoughts‚ÅÝ‚Äîand trying to imagine what an exciting time they must be having of it in the inscrutable depths of their being. This last was difficult to a volatile person (I am sure that to the Fynes I was a volatile person) and the amusement in itself was not very great; but still‚ÅÝ‚Äîin the country‚ÅÝ‚Äîaway from all mental stimulants!‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ My efforts had invested them with a sort of amusing profundity.

But when Fyne and I got back into the room, then in the searching, domestic, glare of the lamp, inimical to the play of fancy, I saw these two stripped of every vesture it had amused me to put on them for fun. Queer enough they were. Is there a human being that isn‚Äôt that‚ÅÝ‚Äîmore or less secretly? But whatever their secret, it was manifest to me that it was neither subtle nor profound. They were a good, stupid, earnest couple and very much bothered. They were that‚ÅÝ‚Äîwith the usual unshaded crudity of average people. There was nothing in them that the lamplight might not touch without the slightest risk of indiscretion.

Directly we had entered the room Fyne announced the result by saying ‚ÄúNothing‚Äù in the same tone as at the gate on his return from the railway station. And as then Mrs.¬ÝFyne uttered an incisive ‚ÄúIt‚Äôs what I‚Äôve said,‚Äù which might have been the veriest echo of her words in the garden. We three looked at each other as if on the brink of a disclosure. I don‚Äôt know whether she was vexed at my presence. It could hardly be called intrusion‚ÅÝ‚Äîcould it? Little Fyne began it. It had to go on. We stood before her, plastered with the same mud (Fyne was a sight!), scratched by the same brambles, conscious of the same experience. Yes. Before her. And she looked at us with folded arms, with an extraordinary fulness of assumed responsibility. I addressed her.

‚ÄúYou don‚Äôt believe in an accident, Mrs.¬ÝFyne, do you?‚Äù

She shook her head in curt negation while, caked in mud and inexpressibly serious-faced, Fyne seemed to be backing her up with all the weight of his solemn presence. Nothing more absurd could be conceived. It was delicious. And I went on in deferential accents: ‚ÄúAm I to understand then that you entertain the theory of suicide?‚Äù

I don‚Äôt know that I am liable to fits of delirium but by a sudden and alarming aberration while waiting for her answer I became mentally aware of three trained dogs dancing on their hind legs. I don‚Äôt know why. Perhaps because of the pervading solemnity. There‚Äôs nothing more solemn on earth than a dance of trained dogs.

‚ÄúShe has chosen to disappear. That‚Äôs all.‚Äù

In these words Mrs.¬ÝFyne answered me. The aggressive tone was too much for my endurance. In an instant I found myself out of the dance and down on all-fours so to speak, with liberty to bark and bite.

‚ÄúThe devil she has,‚Äù I cried. ‚ÄúHas chosen to‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ Like this, all at once, anyhow, regardless‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ I‚Äôve had the privilege of meeting that reckless and brusque young lady and I must say that with her air of an angry victim‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶‚Äù

‚ÄúPrecisely,‚Äù Mrs.¬ÝFyne said very unexpectedly like a steel trap going off. I stared at her. How provoking she was! So I went on to finish my tirade. ‚ÄúShe struck me at first sight as the most inconsiderate wrong-headed girl that I ever‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶‚Äù

‚ÄúWhy should a girl be more considerate than anyone else? More than any man, for instance?‚Äù inquired Mrs.¬ÝFyne with a still greater assertion of responsibility in her bearing.

Of course I exclaimed at this, not very loudly it is true, but forcibly. Were then the feelings of friends, relations and even of strangers to be disregarded? I asked Mrs.¬ÝFyne if she did not think it was a sort of duty to show elementary consideration not only for the natural feelings but even for the prejudices of one‚Äôs fellow-creatures.

Her answer knocked me over.

‚ÄúNot for a woman.‚Äù

Just like that. I confess that I went down flat. And while in that collapsed state I learned the true nature of Mrs.¬ÝFyne‚Äôs feminist doctrine. It was not political, it was not social. It was a knock-me-down doctrine‚ÅÝ‚Äîa practical individualistic doctrine. You would not thank me for expounding it to you at large. Indeed I think that she herself did not enlighten me fully. There must have been things not fit for a man to hear. But shortly, and as far as my bewilderment allowed me to grasp its na√Øve atrociousness, it was something like this: that no consideration, no delicacy, no tenderness, no scruples should stand in the way of a woman (who by the mere fact of her sex was the predestined victim of conditions created by men‚Äôs selfish passions, their vices and their abominable tyranny) from taking the shortest cut towards securing for herself the easiest possible existence. She had even the right to go out of existence without considering anyone‚Äôs feelings or convenience since some women‚Äôs existences were made impossible by the shortsighted baseness of men.

I looked at her, sitting before the lamp at one o‚Äôclock in the morning, with her mature, smooth-cheeked face of masculine shape robbed of its freshness by fatigue; at her eyes dimmed by this senseless vigil. I looked also at Fyne; the mud was drying on him; he was obviously tired. The weariness of solemnity. But he preserved an unflinching, endorsing, gravity of expression. Endorsing it all as became a good, convinced husband.

‚ÄúOh! I see,‚Äù I said. ‚ÄúNo consideration‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ Well I hope you like it.‚Äù

They amused me beyond the wildest imaginings of which I was capable. After the first shock, you understand, I recovered very quickly. The order of the world was safe enough. He was a civil servant and she his good and faithful wife. But when it comes to dealing with human beings anything, anything may be expected. So even my astonishment did not last very long. How far she developed and illustrated that conscienceless and austere doctrine to the girl-friends, who were mere transient shadows to her husband, I could not tell. Any length I supposed. And he looked on, acquiesced, approved, just for that very reason‚ÅÝ‚Äîbecause these pretty girls were but shadows to him. O! Most virtuous Fyne! He cast his eyes down. He didn‚Äôt like it. But I eyed him with hidden animosity for he had got me to run after him under somewhat false pretences.

Mrs.¬ÝFyne had only smiled at me very expressively, very self-confidently. ‚ÄúOh I quite understand that you accept the fullest responsibility,‚Äù I said. ‚ÄúI am the only ridiculous person in this‚ÅÝ‚Äîthis‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI don‚Äôt know how to call it‚ÅÝ‚Äîperformance. However, I‚Äôve nothing more to do here, so I‚Äôll say good-night‚ÅÝ‚Äîor good morning, for it must be past one.‚Äù

But before departing, in common decency, I offered to take any wires they might write. My lodgings were nearer the post-office than the cottage and I would send them off the first thing in the morning. I supposed they would wish to communicate, if only as to the disposal of the luggage, with the young lady‚Äôs relatives‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶

Fyne, he looked rather downcast by then, thanked me and declined.

‚ÄúThere is really no one,‚Äù he said, very grave.

‚ÄúNo one,‚Äù I exclaimed.

‚ÄúPractically,‚Äù said curt Mrs.¬ÝFyne.

And my curiosity was aroused again.

‚ÄúAh! I see. An orphan.‚Äù

Mrs.¬ÝFyne looked away weary and sombre, and Fyne said ‚ÄúYes‚Äù impulsively, and then qualified the affirmative by the quaint statement: ‚ÄúTo a certain extent.‚Äù

I became conscious of a languid, exhausted embarrassment, bowed to Mrs.¬ÝFyne, and went out of the cottage to be confronted outside its door by the bespangled, cruel revelation of the Immensity of the Universe. The night was not sufficiently advanced for the stars to have paled; and the earth seemed to me more profoundly asleep‚ÅÝ‚Äîperhaps because I was alone now. Not having Fyne with me to set the pace I let myself drift, rather than walk, in the direction of the farmhouse. To drift is the only reposeful sort of motion (ask any ship if it isn‚Äôt) and therefore consistent with thoughtfulness. And I pondered: How is one an orphan ‚Äúto a certain extent‚Äù?

No amount of solemnity could make such a statement other than bizarre. What a strange condition to be in. Very likely one of the parents only was dead? But no; it couldn‚Äôt be, since Fyne had said just before that ‚Äúthere was really no one‚Äù to communicate with. No one! And then remembering Mrs.¬ÝFyne‚Äôs snappy ‚ÄúPractically‚Äù my thoughts fastened upon that lady as a more tangible object of speculation.

I wondered‚ÅÝ‚Äîand wondering I doubted‚ÅÝ‚Äîwhether she really understood herself the theory she had propounded to me. Everything may be said‚ÅÝ‚Äîindeed ought to be said‚ÅÝ‚Äîproviding we know how to say it. She probably did not. She was not intelligent enough for that. She had no knowledge of the world. She had got hold of words as a child might get hold of some poisonous pills and play with them for ‚Äúdear, tiny little marbles.‚Äù No! The domestic-slave daughter of Carleon Anthony and the little Fyne of the Civil Service (that flower of civilization) were not intelligent people. They were commonplace, earnest, without smiles and without guile. But he had his solemnities and she had her reveries, her lurid, violent, crude reveries. And I thought with some sadness that all these revolts and indignations, all these protests, revulsions of feeling, pangs of suffering and of rage, expressed but the uneasiness of sensual beings trying for their share in the joys of form, colour, sensations‚ÅÝ‚Äîthe only riches of our world of senses. A poet may be a simple being but he is bound to be various and full of wiles, ingenious and irritable. I reflected on the variety of ways the ingenuity of the late bard of civilization would be able to invent for the tormenting of his dependants. Poets not being generally foresighted in practical affairs, no vision of consequences would restrain him. Yes. The Fynes were excellent people, but Mrs.¬ÝFyne wasn‚Äôt the daughter of a domestic tyrant for nothing. There were no limits to her revolt. But they were excellent people. It was clear that they must have been extremely good to that girl whose position in the world seemed somewhat difficult, with her face of a victim, her obvious lack of resignation and the bizarre status of orphan ‚Äúto a certain extent.‚Äù

Such were my thoughts, but in truth I soon ceased to trouble about all these people. I found that my lamp had gone out leaving behind an awful smell. I fled from it up the stairs and went to bed in the dark. My slumbers‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI suppose the one good in pedestrian exercise, confound it, is that it helps our natural callousness‚ÅÝ‚Äîmy slumbers were deep, dreamless and refreshing.

My appetite at breakfast was not affected by my ignorance of the facts, motives, events and conclusions. I think that to understand everything is not good for the intellect. A well-stocked intelligence weakens the impulse to action; an overstocked one leads gently to idiocy. But Mrs.¬ÝFyne‚Äôs individualist woman-doctrine, na√Øvely unscrupulous, flitted through my mind. The salad of unprincipled notions she put into these girl-friends‚Äô heads! Good innocent creature, worthy wife, excellent mother (of the strict governess type), she was as guileless of consequences as any determinist philosopher ever was.

As to honour‚ÅÝ‚Äîyou know‚ÅÝ‚Äîit‚Äôs a very fine medieval inheritance which women never got hold of. It wasn‚Äôt theirs. Since it may be laid as a general principle that women always get what they want we must suppose they didn‚Äôt want it. In addition they are devoid of decency. I mean masculine decency. Cautiousness too is foreign to them‚ÅÝ‚Äîthe heavy reasonable cautiousness which is our glory. And if they had it they would make of it a thing of passion, so that its own mother‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI mean the mother of cautiousness‚ÅÝ‚Äîwouldn‚Äôt recognize it. Prudence with them is a matter of thrill like the rest of sublunary contrivances. ‚ÄúSensation at any cost,‚Äù is their secret device. All the virtues are not enough for them; they want also all the crimes for their own. And why? Because in such completeness there is power‚ÅÝ‚Äîthe kind of thrill they love most‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶‚Äù

‚ÄúDo you expect me to agree to all this?‚Äù I interrupted.

‚ÄúNo, it isn‚Äôt necessary,‚Äù said Marlow, feeling the check to his eloquence but with a great effort at amiability. ‚ÄúYou need not even understand it. I continue: with such disposition what prevents women‚ÅÝ‚Äîto use the phrase an old boatswain of my acquaintance applied descriptively to his captain‚ÅÝ‚Äîwhat prevents them from ‚Äúcoming on deck and playing hell with the ship‚Äù generally, is that something in them precise and mysterious, acting both as restraint and as inspiration; their femininity in short which they think they can get rid of by trying hard, but can‚Äôt, and never will. Therefore we may conclude that, for all their enterprises, the world is and remains safe enough. Feeling, in my character of a lover of peace, soothed by that conclusion I prepared myself to enjoy a fine day.

And it was a fine day; a delicious day, with the horror of the Infinite veiled by the splendid tent of blue; a day innocently bright like a child with a washed face, fresh like an innocent young girl, suave in welcoming one‚Äôs respects like‚ÅÝ‚Äîlike a Roman prelate. I love such days. They are perfection for remaining indoors. And I enjoyed it temperamentally in a chair, my feet up on the sill of the open window, a book in my hands and the murmured harmonies of wind and sun in my heart making an accompaniment to the rhythms of my author. Then looking up from the page I saw outside a pair of grey eyes thatched by ragged yellowy-white eyebrows gazing at me solemnly over the toes of my slippers. There was a grave, furrowed brow surmounting that portentous gaze, a brown tweed cap set far back on the perspiring head.

‚ÄúCome inside,‚Äù I cried as heartily as my sinking heart would permit.

After a short but severe scuffle with his dog at the outer door, Fyne entered. I treated him without ceremony and only waved my hand towards a chair. Even before he sat down he gasped out:

‚ÄúWe‚Äôve heard‚ÅÝ‚Äîmidday post.‚Äù

Gasped out! The grave, immovable Fyne of the Civil Service, gasped! This was enough, you‚Äôll admit, to cause me to put my feet to the ground swiftly. That fellow was always making me do things in subtle discord with my meditative temperament. No wonder that I had but a qualified liking for him. I said with just a suspicion of jeering tone:

‚ÄúOf course. I told you last night on the road that it was a farce we were engaged in.‚Äù

He made the little parlour resound to its foundations with a note of anger positively sepulchral in its depth of tone. ‚ÄúFarce be hanged! She has bolted with my wife‚Äôs brother, Captain Anthony.‚Äù This outburst was followed by complete subsidence. He faltered miserably as he added from force of habit: ‚ÄúThe son of the poet, you know.‚Äù

A silence fell. Fyne‚Äôs several expressions were so many examples of varied consistency. This was the discomfiture of solemnity. My interest of course was revived.

‚ÄúBut hold on,‚Äù I said. ‚ÄúThey didn‚Äôt go together. Is it a suspicion or does she actually say that‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶‚Äù

‚ÄúShe has gone after him,‚Äù stated Fyne in comminatory tones. ‚ÄúBy previous arrangement. She confesses that much.‚Äù

He added that it was very shocking. I asked him whether he should have preferred them going off together; and on what ground he based that preference. This was sheer fun for me in regard of the fact that Fyne‚Äôs too was a runaway match, which even got into the papers in its time, because the late indignant poet had no discretion and sought to avenge this outrage publicly in some absurd way before a bewigged judge. The dejected gesture of little Fyne‚Äôs hand disarmed my mocking mood. But I could not help expressing my surprise that Mrs.¬ÝFyne had not detected at once what was brewing. Women were supposed to have an unerring eye.

He told me that his wife had been very much engaged in a certain work. I had always wondered how she occupied her time. It was in writing. Like her husband she too published a little book. Much later on I came upon it. It had nothing to do with pedestrianism. It was a sort of hand-book for women with grievances (and all women had them), a sort of compendious theory and practice of feminine free morality. It made you laugh at its transparent simplicity. But that authorship was revealed to me much later. I didn‚Äôt of course ask Fyne what work his wife was engaged on; but I marvelled to myself at her complete ignorance of the world, of her own sex and of the other kind of sinners. Yet, where could she have got any experience? Her father had kept her strictly cloistered. Marriage with Fyne was certainly a change but only to another kind of claustration. You may tell me that the ordinary powers of observation ought to have been enough. Why, yes! But, then, as she had set up for a guide and teacher, there was nothing surprising for me in the discovery that she was blind. That‚Äôs quite in order. She was a profoundly innocent person; only it would not have been proper to tell her husband so.

III

Thrift—and the Child

“But there was nothing improper in my observing to Fyne that, last night, Mrs. Fyne seemed to have some idea where that enterprising young lady had gone to. Fyne shook his head. No; his wife had been by no means so certain as she had pretended to be. She merely had her reasons to think, to hope, that the girl might have taken a room somewhere in London, had buried herself in town—in readiness or perhaps in horror of the approaching day—

“He ceased and sat solemnly dejected, in a brown study. ‘What day?’ I asked at last; but he did not hear me apparently. He diffused such portentous gloom into the atmosphere that I lost patience with him.

“ ‘What on earth are you so dismal about?’ I cried, being genuinely surprised and puzzled. ‘One would think the girl was a state prisoner under your care.’

“And suddenly I became still more surprised at myself, at the way I had somehow taken for granted things which did appear queer when one thought them out.

“ ‘But why this secrecy? Why did they elope—if it is an elopement? Was the girl afraid of your wife? And your brother-in-law? What on earth possesses him to make a clandestine match of it? Was he afraid of your wife too?’

“Fyne made an effort to rouse himself.

“ ‘Of course my brother-in-law, Captain Anthony, the son of …’ He checked himself as if trying to break a bad habit. ‘He would be persuaded by her. We have been most friendly to the girl!’

“ ‘She struck me as a foolish and inconsiderate little person. But why should you and your wife take to heart so strongly mere folly—or even a want of consideration?’

“ ‘It’s the most unscrupulous action,’ declared Fyne weightily—and sighed.

“ ‘I suppose she is poor,’ I observed after a short silence. ‘But after all …’

“ ‘You don’t know who she is.’ Fyne had regained his average solemnity.

“I confessed that I had not caught her name when his wife had introduced us to each other. ‘It was something beginning with an S⸺ wasn’t it?’ And then with the utmost coolness Fyne remarked that it did not matter. The name was not her name.

“ ‘Do you mean to say that you made a young lady known to me under a false name?’ I asked, with the amused feeling that the days of wonders and portents had not passed away yet. That the eminently serious Fynes should do such an exceptional thing was simply staggering. With a more hasty enunciation than usual little Fyne was sure that I would not demand an apology for this irregularity if I knew what her real name was. A sort of warmth crept into his deep tone.

“ ‘We have tried to befriend that girl in every way. She is the daughter and only child of de Barral.’

“Evidently he expected to produce a sensation; he kept his eyes fixed upon me prepared for some sign of it. But I merely returned his intense, awaiting gaze. For a time we stared at each other. Conscious of being reprehensibly dense I groped in the darkness of my mind: De Barral, De Barral—and all at once noise and light burst on me as if a window of my memory had been suddenly flung open on a street in the City. De Barral! But could it be the same? Surely not!

“ ‘The financier?’ I suggested half incredulous.

“ ‘Yes,’ said Fyne; and in this instance his native solemnity of tone seemed to be strangely appropriate. ‘The convict.’ ”

Marlow looked at me, significantly, and remarked in an explanatory tone:

“One somehow never thought of de Barral as having any children, or any other home than the offices of the ‘Orb’; or any other existence, associations or interests than financial. I see you remember the crash …”

“I was away in the Indian Seas at the time,” I said. ‘But of course—”

“Of course,” Marlow struck in. “All the world … You may wonder at my slowness in recognizing the name. But you know that my memory is merely a mausoleum of proper names. There they lie inanimate, awaiting the magic touch—and not very prompt in arising when called, either. The name is the first thing I forget of a man. It is but just to add that frequently it is also the last, and this accounts for my possession of a good many anonymous memories. In de Barral’s case, he got put away in my mausoleum in company with so many names of his own creation that really he had to throw off a monstrous heap of grisly bones before he stood before me at the call of the wizard Fyne. The fellow had a pretty fancy in names: the ‘Orb’ Deposit Bank, the ‘Sceptre’ Mutual Aid Society, the ‘Thrift and Independence’ Association. Yes, a very pretty taste in names; and nothing else besides—absolutely nothing—no other merit. Well yes. He had another name, but that’s pure luck—his own name of de Barral which he did not invent. I don’t think that a mere Jones or Brown could have fished out from the depths of the Incredible such a colossal manifestation of human folly as that man did. But it may be that I am underestimating the alacrity of human folly in rising to the bait. No doubt I am. The greed of that absurd monster is incalculable, unfathomable, inconceivable. The career of de Barral demonstrates that it will rise to a naked hook. He didn’t lure it with a fairy tale. He hadn’t enough imagination for it …”

“Was he a foreigner?” I asked. “It’s clearly a French name. I suppose it was his name?”

“Oh, he didn’t invent it. He was born to it, in Bethnal Green, as it came out during the proceedings. He was in the habit of alluding to his Scotch connections. But every great man has done that. The mother, I believe, was Scotch, right enough. The father de Barral whatever his origins retired from the Customs Service (tide-waiter I think), and started lending money in a very, very small way in the East End to people connected with the docks, stevedores, minor barge-owners, ship-chandlers, tally clerks, all sorts of very small fry. He made his living at it. He was a very decent man I believe. He had enough influence to place his only son as junior clerk in the account department of one of the Dock Companies. ‘Now, my boy,’ he said to him, ‘I’ve given you a fine start.’ But de Barral didn’t start. He stuck. He gave perfect satisfaction. At the end of three years he got a small rise of salary and went out courting in the evenings. He went courting the daughter of an old sea-captain who was a churchwarden of his parish and lived in an old badly preserved Georgian house with a garden: one of these houses standing in a reduced bit of ‘grounds’ that you discover in a labyrinth of the most sordid streets, exactly alike and composed of six-roomed hutches.

“Some of them were the vicarages of slum parishes. The old sailor had got hold of one cheap, and de Barral got hold of his daughter—which was a good bargain for him. The old sailor was very good to the young couple and very fond of their little girl. Mrs. de Barral was an equable, unassuming woman, at that time with a fund of simple gaiety, and with no ambitions; but, womanlike, she longed for change and for something interesting to happen now and then. It was she who encouraged de Barral to accept the offer of a post in the west-end branch of a great bank. It appears he shrank from such a great adventure for a long time. At last his wife’s arguments prevailed. Later on she used to say: ‘It’s the only time he ever listened to me; and I wonder now if it hadn’t been better for me to die before I ever made him go into that bank.’

“You may be surprised at my knowledge of these details. Well, I had them ultimately from Mrs. Fyne. Mrs. Fyne while yet Miss Anthony, in her days of bondage, knew Mrs. de Barral in her days of exile. Mrs. de Barral was living then in a big stone mansion with mullioned windows in a large damp park, called the Priory, adjoining the village where the refined poet had built himself a house.

“These were the days of de Barral’s success. He had bought the place without ever seeing it and had packed off his wife and child at once there to take possession. He did not know what to do with them in London. He himself had a suite of rooms in an hotel. He gave there dinner parties followed by cards in the evening. He had developed the gambling passion—or else a mere card mania—but at any rate he played heavily, for relaxation, with a lot of dubious hangers on.

“Meantime Mrs. de Barral, expecting him every day, lived at the Priory, with a carriage and pair, a governess for the child and many servants. The village people would see her through the railings wandering under the trees with her little girl lost in her strange surroundings. Nobody ever came near her. And there she died as some faithful and delicate animals die—from neglect, absolutely from neglect, rather unexpectedly and without any fuss. The village was sorry for her because, though obviously worried about something, she was good to the poor and was always ready for a chat with any of the humble folks. Of course they knew that she wasn’t a lady—not what you would call a real lady. And even her acquaintance with Miss Anthony was only a cottage-door, a village-street acquaintance. Carleon Anthony was a tremendous aristocrat (his father had been a ‘restoring’ architect) and his daughter was not allowed to associate with anyone but the county young ladies. Nevertheless in defiance of the poet’s wrathful concern for undefiled refinement there were some quiet, melancholy strolls to and fro in the great avenue of chestnuts leading to the park-gate, during which Mrs. de Barral came to call Miss Anthony ‘my dear’—and even ‘my poor dear.’ The lonely soul had no one to talk to but that not very happy girl. The governess despised her. The housekeeper was distant in her manner. Moreover Mrs. de Barral was no foolish gossiping woman. But she made some confidences to Miss Anthony. Such wealth was a terrific thing to have thrust upon one she affirmed. Once she went so far as to confess that she was dying with anxiety. Mr. de Barral (so she referred to him) had been an excellent husband and an exemplary father but ‘you see my dear I have had a great experience of him. I am sure he won’t know what to do with all that money people are giving to him to take care of for them. He’s as likely as not to do something rash. When he comes here I must have a good long serious talk with him, like the talks we often used to have together in the good old times of our life.’ And then one day a cry of anguish was wrung from her: ‘My dear, he will never come here, he will never, never come!’

“She was wrong. He came to the funeral, was extremely cut up, and holding the child tightly by the hand wept bitterly at the side of the grave. Miss Anthony, at the cost of a whole week of sneers and abuse from the poet, saw it all with her own eyes. De Barral clung to the child like a drowning man. He managed, though, to catch the half-past five fast train, travelling to town alone in a reserved compartment, with all the blinds down …”

“Leaving the child?” I said interrogatively.

“Yes. Leaving … He shirked the problem. He was born that way. He had no idea what to do with her or for that matter with anything or anybody including himself. He bolted back to his suite of rooms in the hotel. He was the most helpless … She might have been left in the Priory to the end of time had not the high-toned governess threatened to send in her resignation. She didn’t care for the child a bit, and the lonely, gloomy Priory had got on her nerves. She wasn’t going to put up with such a life and, having just come out of some ducal family, she bullied de Barral in a very lofty fashion. To pacify her he took a splendidly furnished house in the most expensive part of Brighton for them, and now and then ran down for a weekend, with a trunk full of exquisite sweets and with his hat full of money. The governess spent it for him in extra ducal style. She was nearly forty and harboured a secret taste for patronizing young men of sorts—of a certain sort. But of that Mrs. Fyne of course had no personal knowledge then; she told me however that even in the Priory days she had suspected her of being an artificial, heartless, vulgar-minded woman with the lowest possible ideals. But de Barral did not know it. He literally did not know anything …”

“But tell me, Marlow,” I interrupted, “how do you account for this opinion? He must have been a personality in a sense—in some one sense surely. You don’t work the greatest material havoc of a decade at least, in a commercial community, without having something in you.”

Marlow shook his head.

“He was a mere sign, a portent. There was nothing in him. Just about that time the word Thrift was to the fore. You know the power of words. We pass through periods dominated by this or that word—it may be development, or it may be competition, or education, or purity or efficiency or even sanctity. It is the word of the time. Well just then it was the word Thrift which was out in the streets walking arm in arm with righteousness, the inseparable companion and backer up of all such national catchwords, looking everybody in the eye as it were. The very drabs of the pavement, poor things, didn’t escape the fascination … However! … Well the greatest portion of the press were screeching in all possible tones, like a confounded company of parrots instructed by some devil with a taste for practical jokes, that the financier de Barral was helping the great moral evolution of our character towards the newly-discovered virtue of Thrift. He was helping it by all these great establishments of his, which made the moral merits of Thrift manifest to the most callous hearts, simply by promising to pay ten percent interest on all deposits. And you didn’t want necessarily to belong to the well-to-do classes in order to participate in the advantages of virtue. If you had but a spare sixpence in the world and went and gave it to de Barral it was Thrift! It’s quite likely that he himself believed it. He must have. It’s inconceivable that he alone should stand out against the infatuation of the whole world. He hadn’t enough intelligence for that. But to look at him one couldn’t tell …”

“You did see him then?” I said with some curiosity.

“I did. Strange, isn’t it? It was only once, but as I sat with the distressed Fyne who had suddenly resuscitated his name buried in my memory with other dead labels of the past, I may say I saw him again, I saw him with great vividness of recollection, as he appeared in the days of his glory or splendour. No! Neither of these words will fit his success. There was never any glory or splendour about that figure. Well, let us say in the days when he was, according to the majority of the daily press, a financial force working for the improvement of the character of the people. I’ll tell you how it came about.

“At that time I used to know a podgy, wealthy, bald little man having chambers in the Albany; a financier too, in his way, carrying out transactions of an intimate nature and of no moral character; mostly with young men of birth and expectations—though I dare say he didn’t withhold his ministrations from elderly plebeians either. He was a true democrat; he would have done business (a sharp kind of business) with the devil himself. Everything was fly that came into his web. He received the applicants in an alert, jovial fashion which was quite surprising. It gave relief without giving too much confidence, which was just as well perhaps. His business was transacted in an apartment furnished like a drawing-room, the walls hung with several brown, heavily-framed, oil paintings. I don’t know if they were good, but they were big, and with their elaborate, tarnished gilt-frames had a melancholy dignity. The man himself sat at a shining, inlaid writing table which looked like a rare piece from a museum of art; his chair had a high, oval, carved back, upholstered in faded tapestry; and these objects made of the costly black Havana cigar, which he rolled incessantly from the middle to the left corner of his mouth and back again, an inexpressibly cheap and nasty object. I had to see him several times in the interest of a poor devil so unlucky that he didn’t even have a more competent friend than myself to speak for him at a very difficult time in his life.

“I don’t know at what hour my private financier began his day, but he used to give one appointments at unheard of times: such as a quarter to eight in the morning, for instance. On arriving one found him busy at that marvellous writing table, looking very fresh and alert, exhaling a faint fragrance of scented soap and with the cigar already well alight. You may believe that I entered on my mission with many unpleasant forebodings; but there was in that fat, admirably washed, little man such a profound contempt for mankind that it amounted to a species of good nature; which, unlike the milk of genuine kindness, was never in danger of turning sour. Then, once, during a pause in business, while we were waiting for the production of a document for which he had sent (perhaps to the cellar?) I happened to remark, glancing round the room, that I had never seen so many fine things assembled together out of a collection. Whether this was unconscious diplomacy on my part, or not, I shouldn’t like to say—but the remark was true enough, and it pleased him extremely. ‘It is a collection,’ he said emphatically. ‘Only I live right in it, which most collectors don’t. But I see that you know what you are looking at. Not many people who come here on business do. Stable fittings are more in their way.’

“I don’t know whether my appreciation helped to advance my friend’s business but at any rate it helped our intercourse. He treated me with a shade of familiarity as one of the initiated.

“The last time I called on him to conclude the transaction we were interrupted by a person, something like a cross between a bookmaker and a private secretary, who, entering through a door which was not the anteroom door, walked up and stooped to whisper into his ear.

“ ‘Eh? What? Who, did you say?’

“The nondescript person stooped and whispered again, adding a little louder: ‘Says he won’t detain you a moment.’

“My little man glanced at me, said ‘Ah! Well,’ irresolutely. I got up from my chair and offered to come again later. He looked whimsically alarmed. ‘No, no. It’s bad enough to lose my money but I don’t want to waste any more of my time over your friend. We must be done with this today. Just go and have a look at that garniture de cheminée yonder. There’s another, something like it, in the castle of Laeken, but mine’s much superior in design.’

“I moved accordingly to the other side of that big room. The garniture was very fine. But while pretending to examine it I watched my man going forward to meet a tall visitor, who said, ‘I thought you would be disengaged so early. It’s only a word or two’—and after a whispered confabulation of no more than a minute, reconduct him to the door and shake hands ceremoniously. ‘Not at all, not at all. Very pleased to be of use. You can depend absolutely on my information’—‘Oh thank you, thank you. I just looked in.’ ‘Certainly, quite right. Any time … Good morning.’

“I had a good look at the visitor while they were exchanging these civilities. He was clad in black. I remember perfectly that he wore a flat, broad, black satin tie in which was stuck a large cameo pin; and a small turn down collar. His hair, discoloured and silky, curled slightly over his ears. His cheeks were hairless and round, and apparently soft. He held himself very upright, walked with small steps and spoke gently in an inward voice. Perhaps from contrast with the magnificent polish of the room and the neatness of its owner, he struck me as dingy, indigent, and, if not exactly humble, then much subdued by evil fortune.

“I wondered greatly at my fat little financier’s civility to that dubious personage when he asked me, as we resumed our respective seats, whether I knew who it was that had just gone out. On my shaking my head negatively he smiled queerly, said ‘De Barral,’ and enjoyed my surprise. Then becoming grave: ‘That’s a deep fellow, if you like. We all know where he started from and where he got to; but nobody knows what he means to do.’ He became thoughtful for a moment and added as if speaking to himself, ‘I wonder what his game is.’

“And, you know, there was no game, no game of any sort, or shape or kind. It came out plainly at the trial. As I’ve told you before, he was a clerk in a bank, like thousands of others. He got that berth as a second start in life and there he stuck again, giving perfect satisfaction. Then one day as though a supernatural voice had whispered into his ear or some invisible fly had stung him, he put on his hat, went out into the street and began advertising. That’s absolutely all that there was to it. He caught in the street the word of the time and harnessed it to his preposterous chariot.

“One remembers his first modest advertisements headed with the magic word Thrift, Thrift, Thrift, thrice repeated; promising ten percent on all deposits and giving the address of the Thrift and Independence Aid Association in Vauxhall Bridge Road. Apparently nothing more was necessary. He didn’t even explain what he meant to do with the money he asked the public to pour into his lap. Of course he meant to lend it out at high rates of interest. He did so—but he did it without system, plan, foresight or judgment. And as he frittered away the sums that flowed in, he advertised for more—and got it. During a period of general business prosperity he set up The Orb Bank and The Sceptre Trust, simply, it seems for advertising purposes. They were mere names. He was totally unable to organize anything, to promote any sort of enterprise if it were only for the purpose of juggling with the shares. At that time he could have had for the asking any number of Dukes, retired Generals, active M.P.’s, ex-ambassadors and so on as Directors to sit at the wildest boards of his invention. But he never tried. He had no real imagination. All he could do was to publish more advertisements and open more branch offices of the Thrift and Independence, of The Orb, of The Sceptre, for the receipt of deposits; first in this town, then in that town, north and south—everywhere where he could find suitable premises at a moderate rent. For this was the great characteristic of the management. Modesty, moderation, simplicity. Neither The Orb nor The Sceptre nor yet their parent the Thrift and Independence had built for themselves the usual palaces. For this abstention they were praised in silly public prints as illustrating in their management the principle of Thrift for which they were founded. The fact is that de Barral simply didn’t think of it. Of course he had soon moved from Vauxhall Bridge Road. He knew enough for that. What he got hold of next was an old, enormous, rat-infested brick house in a small street off the Strand. Strangers were taken in front of the meanest possible, begrimed, yellowy, flat brick wall, with two rows of unadorned window-holes one above the other, and were exhorted with bated breath to behold and admire the simplicity of the headquarters of the great financial force of the day. The word thrift perched right up on the roof in giant gilt letters, and two enormous shield-like brass-plates curved round the corners on each side of the doorway were the only shining spots in de Barral’s business outfit. Nobody knew what operations were carried on inside except this—that if you walked in and tendered your money over the counter it would be calmly taken from you by somebody who would give you a printed receipt. That and no more. It appears that such knowledge is irresistible. People went in and tendered; and once it was taken from their hands their money was more irretrievably gone from them than if they had thrown it into the sea. This then, and nothing else was being carried on in there …”

“Come, Marlow,” I said, “you exaggerate surely—if only by your way of putting things. It’s too startling.”

“I exaggerate!” he defended himself. “My way of putting things! My dear fellow I have merely stripped the rags of business verbiage and financial jargon off my statements. And you are startled! I am giving you the naked truth. It’s true too that nothing lays itself open to the charge of exaggeration more than the language of naked truth. What comes with a shock is admitted with difficulty. But what will you say to the end of his career?

“It was of course sensational and tolerably sudden. It began with the Orb Deposit Bank. Under the name of that institution de Barral with the frantic obstinacy of an unimaginative man had been financing an Indian prince who was prosecuting a claim for immense sums of money against the government. It was an enormous number of scores of lakhs—a miserable remnant of his ancestors’ treasures—that sort of thing. And it was all authentic enough. There was a real prince; and the claim too was sufficiently real—only unfortunately it was not a valid claim. So the prince lost his case on the last appeal and the beginning of de Barral’s end became manifest to the public in the shape of a half-sheet of note paper wafered by the four corners on the closed door of The Orb offices notifying that payment was stopped at that establishment.

“Its consort The Sceptre collapsed within the week. I won’t say in American parlance that suddenly the bottom fell out of the whole of de Barral concerns. There never had been any bottom to it. It was like the cask of Danaides into which the public had been pleased to pour its deposits. That they were gone was clear; and the bankruptcy proceedings which followed were like a sinister farce, bursts of laughter in a setting of mute anguish—that of the depositors; hundreds of thousands of them. The laughter was irresistible; the accompaniment of the bankrupt’s public examination.

“I don’t know if it was from utter lack of all imagination or from the possession in undue proportion of a particular kind of it, or from both—and the three alternatives are possible—but it was discovered that this man who had been raised to such a height by the credulity of the public was himself more gullible than any of his depositors. He had been the prey of all sorts of swindlers, adventurers, visionaries and even lunatics. Wrapping himself up in deep and imbecile secrecy he had gone in for the most fantastic schemes: a harbour and docks on the coast of Patagonia, quarries in Labrador—suchlike speculations. Fisheries to feed a canning Factory on the banks of the Amazon was one of them. A principality to be bought in Madagascar was another. As the grotesque details of these incredible transactions came out one by one ripples of laughter ran over the closely packed court—each one a little louder than the other. The audience ended by fairly roaring under the cumulative effect of absurdity. The Registrar laughed, the barristers laughed, the reporters laughed, the serried ranks of the miserable depositors watching anxiously every word, laughed like one man. They laughed hysterically—the poor wretches—on the verge of tears.

“There was only one person who remained unmoved. It was de Barral himself. He preserved his serene, gentle expression, I am told (for I have not witnessed those scenes myself), and looked around at the people with an air of placid sufficiency which was the first hint to the world of the man’s overweening, unmeasurable conceit, hidden hitherto under a diffident manner. It could be seen too in his dogged assertion that if he had been given enough time and a lot more money everything would have come right. And there were some people (yes, amongst his very victims) who more than half believed him, even after the criminal prosecution which soon followed. When placed in the dock he lost his steadiness as if some sustaining illusion had gone to pieces within him suddenly. He ceased to be himself in manner completely, and even in disposition, in so far that his faded neutral eyes matching his discoloured hair so well, were discovered then to be capable of expressing a sort of underhand hate. He was at first defiant, then insolent, then broke down and burst into tears; but it might have been from rage. Then he calmed down, returned to his soft manner of speech and to that unassuming quiet bearing which had been usual with him even in his greatest days. But it seemed as though in this moment of change he had at last perceived what a power he had been; for he remarked to one of the prosecuting counsel who had assumed a lofty moral tone in questioning him, that—yes, he had gambled—he liked cards. But that only a year ago a host of smart people would have been only too pleased to take a hand at cards with him. Yes—he went on—some of the very people who were there accommodated with seats on the bench; and turning upon the counsel ‘You yourself as well,’ he cried. He could have had half the town at his rooms to fawn upon him if he had cared for that sort of thing. ‘Why, now I think of it, it took me most of my time to keep people, just of your sort, off me,’ he ended with a good humoured—quite unobtrusive, contempt, as though the fact had dawned upon him for the first time.

“This was the moment, the only moment, when he had perhaps all the audience in Court with him, in a hush of dreary silence. And then the dreary proceedings were resumed. For all the outside excitement it was the most dreary of all celebrated trials. The bankruptcy proceedings had exhausted all the laughter there was in it. Only the fact of widespread ruin remained, and the resentment of a mass of people for having been fooled by means too simple to save their self-respect from a deep wound which the cleverness of a consummate scoundrel would not have inflicted. A shamefaced amazement attended these proceedings in which de Barral was not being exposed alone. For himself his only cry was: Time! Time! Time would have set everything right. In time some of these speculations of his were certain to have succeeded. He repeated this defence, this excuse, this confession of faith, with wearisome iteration. Everything he had done or left undone had been to gain time. He had hypnotized himself with the word. Sometimes, I am told, his appearance was ecstatic, his motionless pale eyes seemed to be gazing down the vista of future ages. Time—and of course, more money. ‘Ah! If only you had left me alone for a couple of years more,’ he cried once in accents of passionate belief. ‘The money was coming in all right.’ The deposits you understand—the savings of Thrift. Oh yes they had been coming in to the very last moment. And he regretted them. He had arrived to regard them as his own by a sort of mystical persuasion. And yet it was a perfectly true cry, when he turned once more on the counsel who was beginning a question with the words ‘You have had all these immense sums …’ with the indignant retort ‘What have I had out of them?’

“It was perfectly true. He had had nothing out of them—nothing of the prestigious or the desirable things of the earth, craved for by predatory natures. He had gratified no tastes, had known no luxury; he had built no gorgeous palaces, had formed no splendid galleries out of these ‘immense sums.’ He had not even a home. He had gone into these rooms in an hotel and had stuck there for years, giving no doubt perfect satisfaction to the management. They had twice raised his rent to show I suppose their high sense of his distinguished patronage. He had bought for himself out of all the wealth streaming through his fingers neither adulation nor love, neither splendour nor comfort. There was something perfect in his consistent mediocrity. His very vanity seemed to miss the gratification of even the mere show of power. In the days when he was most fully in the public eye the invincible obscurity of his origins clung to him like a shadowy garment. He had handled millions without ever enjoying anything of what is counted as precious in the community of men, because he had neither the brutality of temperament nor the fineness of mind to make him desire them with the will power of a masterful adventurer …”

“You seem to have studied the man,” I observed.

“Studied,” repeated Marlow thoughtfully. “No! Not studied. I had no opportunities. You know that I saw him only on that one occasion I told you of. But it may be that a glimpse and no more is the proper way of seeing an individuality; and de Barral was that, in virtue of his very deficiencies for they made of him something quite unlike one’s preconceived ideas. There were also very few materials accessible to a man like me to form a judgment from. But in such a case I verify believe that a little is as good as a feast—perhaps better. If one has a taste for that kind of thing the merest starting-point becomes a coign of vantage, and then by a series of logically deducted verisimilitudes one arrives at truth—or very near the truth—as near as any circumstantial evidence can do. I have not studied de Barral but that is how I understand him so far as he could be understood through the din of the crash; the wailing and gnashing of teeth, the newspaper contents bills, ‘The Thrift Frauds. Cross-examination of the accused. Extra special’—blazing fiercely; the charitable appeals for the victims, the grave tones of the dailies rumbling with compassion as if they were the national bowels. All this lasted a whole week of industrious sittings. A pressman whom I knew told me ‘He’s an idiot.’ Which was possible. Before that I overheard once somebody declaring that he had a criminal type of face; which I knew was untrue. The sentence was pronounced by artificial light in a stifling poisonous atmosphere. Something edifying was said by the judge weightily, about the retribution overtaking the perpetrator of ‘the most heartless frauds on an unprecedented scale.’ I don’t understand these things much, but it appears that he had juggled with accounts, cooked balance sheets, had gathered in deposits months after he ought to have known himself to be hopelessly insolvent, and done enough of other things, highly reprehensible in the eyes of the law, to earn for himself seven years’ penal servitude. The sentence making its way outside met with a good reception. A small mob composed mainly of people who themselves did not look particularly clever and scrupulous, leavened by a slight sprinkling of genuine pickpockets amused itself by cheering in the most penetrating, abominable cold drizzle that I remember. I happened to be passing there on my way from the East End where I had spent my day about the Docks with an old chum who was looking after the fitting out of a new ship. I am always eager, when allowed, to call on a new ship. They interest me like charming young persons.

“I got mixed up in that crowd seething with an animosity as senseless as things of the street always are, and it was while I was laboriously making my way out of it that the pressman of whom I spoke was jostled against me. He did me the justice to be surprised. ‘What? You here! The last person in the world … If I had known I could have got you inside. Plenty of room. Interest been over for the last three days. Got seven years. Well, I am glad.’

“ ‘Why are you glad? Because he’s got seven years?’ I asked, greatly incommoded by the pressure of a hulking fellow who was remarking to some of his equally oppressive friends that the ‘beggar ought to have been poleaxed.’ I don’t know whether he had ever confided his savings to de Barral but if so, judging from his appearance, they must have been the proceeds of some successful burglary. The pressman by my side said ‘No,’ to my question. He was glad because it was all over. He had suffered greatly from the heat and the bad air of the court. The clammy, raw, chill of the streets seemed to affect his liver instantly. He became contemptuous and irritable and plied his elbows viciously making way for himself and me.

“A dull affair this. All such cases were dull. No really dramatic moments. The bookkeeping of The Orb and all the rest of them was certainly a burlesque revelation but the public did not care for revelations of that kind. Dull dog that de Barral—he grumbled. He could not or would not take the trouble to characterize for me the appearance of that man now officially a criminal (we had gone across the road for a drink) but told me with a sourly, derisive snigger that, after the sentence had been pronounced the fellow clung to the dock long enough to make a sort of protest. ‘You haven’t given me time. If I had been given time I would have ended by being made a peer like some of them.’ And he had permitted himself his very first and last gesture in all these days, raising a hard-clenched fist above his head.

“The pressman disapproved of that manifestation. It was not his business to understand it. Is it ever the business of any pressman to understand anything? I guess not. It would lead him too far away from the actualities which are the daily bread of the public mind. He probably thought the display worth very little from a picturesque point of view; the weak voice; the colourless personality as incapable of an attitude as a bedpost, the very fatuity of the clenched hand so ineffectual at that time and place—no, it wasn’t worth much. And then, for him, an accomplished craftsman in his trade, thinking was distinctly ‘bad business.’ His business was to write a readable account. But I who had nothing to write, I permitted myself to use my mind as we sat before our still untouched glasses. And the disclosure which so often rewards a moment of detachment from mere visual impressions gave me a thrill very much approaching a shudder. I seemed to understand that, with the shock of the agonies and perplexities of his trial, the imagination of that man, whose moods, notions and motives wore frequently an air of grotesque mystery—that his imagination had been at last roused into activity. And this was awful. Just try to enter into the feelings of a man whose imagination wakes up at the very moment he is about to enter the tomb …’

“You must not think,” went on Marlow after a pause, “that on that morning with Fyne I went consciously in my mind over all this, let us call it information; no, better say, this fund of knowledge which I had, or rather which existed, in me in regard to de Barral. Information is something one goes out to seek and puts away when found as you might do a piece of lead: ponderous, useful, unvibrating, dull. Whereas knowledge comes to one, this sort of knowledge, a chance acquisition preserving in its repose a fine resonant quality … But as such distinctions touch upon the transcendental I shall spare you the pain of listening to them. There are limits to my cruelty. No! I didn’t reckon up carefully in my mind all this I have been telling you. How could I have done so, with Fyne right there in the room? He sat perfectly still, statuesque in homely fashion, after having delivered himself of his effective assent: ‘Yes. The convict,’ and I, far from indulging in a reminiscent excursion into the past, remained sufficiently in the present to muse in a vague, absentminded way on the respectable proportions and on the (upon the whole) comely shape of his great pedestrian’s calves, for he had thrown one leg over his knee, carelessly, to conceal the trouble of his mind by an air of ease. But all the same the knowledge was in me, the awakened resonance of which I spoke just now; I was aware of it on that beautiful day, so fresh, so warm and friendly, so accomplished—an exquisite courtesy of the much abused English climate when it makes up its meteorological mind to behave like a perfect gentleman. Of course the English climate is never a rough. It suffers from spleen somewhat frequently—but that is gentlemanly too, and I don’t mind going to meet him in that mood. He has his days of grey, veiled, polite melancholy, in which he is very fascinating. How seldom he lapses into a blustering manner, after all! And then it is mostly in a season when, appropriately enough, one may go out and kill something. But his fine days are the best for stopping at home, to read, to think, to muse—even to dream; in fact to live fully, intensely and quietly, in the brightness of comprehension, in that receptive glow of the mind, the gift of the clear, luminous and serene weather.

“That day I had intended to live intensely and quietly, basking in the weather’s glory which would have lent enchantment to the most unpromising of intellectual prospects. For a companion I had found a book, not bemused with the cleverness of the day—a fine-weather book, simple and sincere like the talk of an unselfish friend. But looking at little Fyne seated in the room I understood that nothing would come of my contemplative aspirations; that in one way or another I should be let in for some form of severe exercise. Walking, it would be, I feared, since, for me, that idea was inseparably associated with the visual impression of Fyne. Where, why, how, a rapid striding rush could be brought in helpful relation to the good Fyne’s present trouble and perplexity I could not imagine; except on the principle that senseless pedestrianism was Fyne’s panacea for all the ills and evils bodily and spiritual of the universe. It could be of no use for me to say or do anything. It was bound to come. Contemplating his muscular limb encased in a golf-stocking, and under the strong impression of the information he had just imparted I said wondering, rather irrationally:

“ ‘And so de Barral had a wife and child! That girl’s his daughter. And how …’

“Fyne interrupted me by stating again earnestly, as though it were something not easy to believe, that his wife and himself had tried to befriend the girl in every way—indeed they had! I did not doubt him for a moment, of course, but my wonder at this was more rational. At that hour of the morning, you mustn’t forget, I knew nothing as yet of Mrs. Fyne’s contact (it was hardly more) with de Barral’s wife and child during their exile at the Priory, in the culminating days of that man’s fame.

“Fyne who had come over, it was clear, solely to talk to me on that subject, gave me the first hint of this initial, merely out of doors, connection. ‘The girl was quite a child then,’ he continued. ‘Later on she was removed out of Mrs. Fyne’s reach in charge of a governess—a very unsatisfactory person,’ he explained. His wife had then—h’m—met him; and on her marriage she lost sight of the child completely. But after the birth of Polly (Polly was the third Fyne girl) she did not get on very well, and went to Brighton for some months to recover her strength—and there, one day in the street, the child (she wore her hair down her back still) recognized her outside a shop and rushed, actually rushed, into Mrs. Fyne’s arms. Rather touching this. And so, disregarding the cold impertinence of that … h’m … governess, his wife naturally responded.

“He was solemnly fragmentary. I broke in with the observation that it must have been before the crash.

“Fyne nodded with deepened gravity, stating in his bass tone—

“ ‘Just before,’ and indulged himself with a weighty period of solemn silence.

“De Barral, he resumed suddenly, was not coming to Brighton for weekends regularly, then. Must have been conscious already of the approaching disaster. Mrs. Fyne avoided being drawn into making his acquaintance, and this suited the views of the governess person, very jealous of any outside influence. But in any case it would not have been an easy matter. Extraordinary, stiff-backed, thin figure all in black, the observed of all, while walking hand-in-hand with the girl; apparently shy, but—and here Fyne came very near showing something like insight—probably nursing under a diffident manner a considerable amount of secret arrogance. Mrs. Fyne pitied Flora de Barral’s fate long before the catastrophe. Most unfortunate guidance. Very unsatisfactory surroundings. The girl was known in the streets, was stared at in public places as if she had been a sort of princess, but she was kept with a very ominous consistency, from making any acquaintances—though of course there were many people no doubt who would have been more than willing to—h’m—make themselves agreeable to Miss de Barral. But this did not enter into the plans of the governess, an intriguing person hatching a most sinister plot under her severe air of distant, fashionable exclusiveness. Good little Fyne’s eyes bulged with solemn horror as he revealed to me, in agitated speech, his wife’s more than suspicions, at the time, of that, Mrs., Mrs. What’s her name’s perfidious conduct. She actually seemed to have—Mrs. Fyne asserted—formed a plot already to marry eventually her charge to an impecunious relation of her own—a young man with furtive eyes and something impudent in his manner, whom that woman called her nephew, and whom she was always having down to stay with her.

“ ‘And perhaps not her nephew. No relation at all’—Fyne emitted with a convulsive effort this, the most awful part of the suspicions Mrs. Fyne used to impart to him piecemeal when he came down to spend his weekends gravely with her and the children. The Fynes, in their good-natured concern for the unlucky child of the man busied in stirring casually so many millions, spent the moments of their weekly reunion in wondering earnestly what could be done to defeat the most wicked of conspiracies, trying to invent some tactful line of conduct in such extraordinary circumstances. I could see them, simple, and scrupulous, worrying honestly about that unprotected big girl while looking at their own little girls playing on the seashore. Fyne assured me that his wife’s rest was disturbed by the great problem of interference.

“ ‘It was very acute of Mrs. Fyne to spot such a deep game,’ I said, wondering to myself where her acuteness had gone to now, to let her be taken unawares by a game so much simpler and played to the end under her very nose. But then, at that time, when her nightly rest was disturbed by the dread of the fate preparing for de Barral’s unprotected child, she was not engaged in writing a compendious and ruthless handbook on the theory and practice of life, for the use of women with a grievance. She could as yet, before the task of evolving the philosophy of rebellious action had affected her intuitive sharpness, perceive things which were, I suspect, moderately plain. For I am inclined to believe that the woman whom chance had put in command of Flora de Barral’s destiny took no very subtle pains to conceal her game. She was conscious of being a complete master of the situation, having once for all established her ascendancy over de Barral. She had taken all her measures against outside observation of her conduct; and I could not help smiling at the thought what a ghastly nuisance the serious, innocent Fynes must have been to her. How exasperated she must have been by that couple falling into Brighton as completely unforeseen as a bolt from the blue—if not so prompt. How she must have hated them!

“But I conclude she would have carried out whatever plan she might have formed. I can imagine de Barral accustomed for years to defer to her wishes and, either through arrogance, or shyness, or simply because of his unimaginative stupidity, remaining outside the social pale, knowing no one but some card-playing cronies; I can picture him to myself terrified at the prospect of having the care of a marriageable girl thrust on his hands, forcing on him a complete change of habits and the necessity of another kind of existence which he would not even have known how to begin. It is evident to me that Mrs. What’s her name would have had her atrocious way with very little trouble even if the excellent Fynes had been able to do something. She would simply have bullied de Barral in a lofty style. There’s nothing more subservient than an arrogant man when his arrogance has once been broken in some particular instance.

“However there was no time and no necessity for anyone to do anything. The situation itself vanished in the financial crash as a building vanishes in an earthquake—here one moment and gone the next with only an ill-omened, slight, preliminary rumble. Well, to say ‘in a moment’ is an exaggeration perhaps; but that everything was over in just twenty-four hours is an exact statement. Fyne was able to tell me all about it; and the phrase that would depict the nature of the change best is: an instant and complete destitution. I don’t understand these matters very well, but from Fyne’s narrative it seemed as if the creditors or the depositors, or the competent authorities, had got hold in the twinkling of an eye of everything de Barral possessed in the world, down to his watch and chain, the money in his trousers’ pocket, his spare suits of clothes, and I suppose the cameo pin out of his black satin cravat. Everything! I believe he gave up the very wedding ring of his late wife. The gloomy Priory with its damp park and a couple of farms had been made over to Mrs. de Barral; but when she died (without making a will) it reverted to him, I imagine. They got that of course; but it was a mere crumb in a Sahara of starvation, a drop in the thirsty ocean. I dare say that not a single soul in the world got the comfort of as much as a recovered threepenny bit out of the estate. Then, less than crumbs, less than drops, there were to be grabbed, the lease of the big Brighton house, the furniture therein, the carriage and pair, the girl’s riding horse, her costly trinkets; down to the heavily gold-mounted collar of her pedigree St. Bernard. The dog too went: the most noble-looking item in the beggarly assets.

“What however went first of all or rather vanished was nothing in the nature of an asset. It was that plotting governess with the trick of a ‘perfect lady’ manner (severely conventional) and the soul of a remorseless brigand. When a woman takes to any sort of unlawful man-trade, there’s nothing to beat her in the way of thoroughness. It’s true that you will find people who’ll tell you that this terrific virulence in breaking through all established things, is altogether the fault of men. Such people will ask you with a clever air why the servile wars were always the most fierce, desperate and atrocious of all wars. And you may make such answer as you can—even the eminently feminine one, if you choose, so typical of the women’s literal mind ‘I don’t see what this has to do with it!’ How many arguments have been knocked over (I won’t say knocked down) by these few words! For if we men try to put the spaciousness of all experiences into our reasoning and would fain put the Infinite itself into our love, it isn’t, as some writer has remarked, ‘It isn’t women’s doing.’ Oh no. They don’t care for these things. That sort of aspiration is not much in their way; and it shall be a funny world, the world of their arranging, where the Irrelevant would fantastically step in to take the place of the sober humdrum Imaginative …”

I raised my hand to stop my friend Marlow.

“Do you really believe what you have said?” I asked, meaning no offence, because with Marlow one never could be sure.

“Only on certain days of the year,” said Marlow readily with a malicious smile. “Today I have been simply trying to be spacious and I perceive I’ve managed to hurt your susceptibilities which are consecrated to women. When you sit alone and silent you are defending in your mind the poor women from attacks which cannot possibly touch them. I wonder what can touch them? But to soothe your uneasiness I will point out again that an Irrelevant world would be very amusing, if the women take care to make it as charming as they alone can, by preserving for us certain well-known, well-established, I’ll almost say hackneyed, illusions, without which the average male creature cannot get on. And that condition is very important. For there is nothing more provoking than the Irrelevant when it has ceased to amuse and charm; and then the danger would be of the subjugated masculinity in its exasperation, making some brusque, unguarded movement and accidentally putting its elbow through the fine tissue of the world of which I speak. And that would be fatal to it. For nothing looks more irretrievably deplorable than fine tissue which has been damaged. The women themselves would be the first to become disgusted with their own creation.

“There was something of women’s highly practical sanity and also of their irrelevancy in the conduct of Miss de Barral’s amazing governess. It appeared from Fyne’s narrative that the day before the first rumble of the cataclysm the questionable young man arrived unexpectedly in Brighton to stay with his ‘Aunt.’ To all outward appearance everything was going on normally; the fellow went out riding with the girl in the afternoon as he often used to do—a sight which never failed to fill Mrs. Fyne with indignation. Fyne himself was down there with his family for a whole week and was called to the window to behold the iniquity in its progress and to share in his wife’s feelings. There was not even a groom with them. And Mrs. Fyne’s distress was so strong at this glimpse of the unlucky girl all unconscious of her danger riding smilingly by, that Fyne began to consider seriously whether it wasn’t their plain duty to interfere at all risks—simply by writing a letter to de Barral. He said to his wife with a solemnity I can easily imagine ‘You ought to undertake that task, my dear. You have known his wife after all. That’s something at any rate.’ On the other hand the fear of exposing Mrs. Fyne to some nasty rebuff worried him exceedingly. Mrs. Fyne on her side gave way to despondency. Success seemed impossible. Here was a woman for more than five years in charge of the girl and apparently enjoying the complete confidence of the father. What, that would be effective, could one say, without proofs, without … This Mr. de Barral must be, Mrs. Fyne pronounced, either a very stupid or a downright bad man, to neglect his child so.

“You will notice that perhaps because of Fyne’s solemn view of our transient life and Mrs. Fyne’s natural capacity for responsibility, it had never occurred to them that the simplest way out of the difficulty was to do nothing and dismiss the matter as no concern of theirs. Which in a strict worldly sense it certainly was not. But they spent, Fyne told me, a most disturbed afternoon, considering the ways and means of dealing with the danger hanging over the head of the girl out for a ride (and no doubt enjoying herself) with an abominable scamp.

V

The Tea-Party

“Amiable personality,” I observed seeing Fyne on the point of falling into a brown study. But I could not help adding with meaning: “He hadn’t the gift of prophecy though.”

Fyne got up suddenly with a muttered “No, evidently not.” He was gloomy, hesitating. I supposed that he would not wish to play chess that afternoon. This would dispense me from leaving my rooms on a day much too fine to be wasted in walking exercise. And I was disappointed when picking up his cap he intimated to me his hope of seeing me at the cottage about four o’clock—as usual.

“It wouldn’t be as usual.” I put a particular stress on that remark. He admitted, after a short reflection, that it would not be. No. Not as usual. In fact it was his wife who hoped, rather, for my presence. She had formed a very favourable opinion of my practical sagacity.

This was the first I ever heard of it. I had never suspected that Mrs. Fyne had taken the trouble to distinguish in me the signs of sagacity or folly. The few words we had exchanged last night in the excitement—or the bother—of the girl’s disappearance, were the first moderately significant words which had ever passed between us. I had felt myself always to be in Mrs. Fyne’s view her husband’s chess-player and nothing else—a convenience—almost an implement.

“I am highly flattered,” I said. “I have always heard that there are no limits to feminine intuition; and now I am half inclined to believe it is so. But still I fail to see in what way my sagacity, practical or otherwise, can be of any service to Mrs. Fyne. One man’s sagacity is very much like any other man’s sagacity. And with you at hand—”

Fyne, manifestly not attending to what I was saying, directed straight at me his worried solemn eyes and struck in:

“Yes, yes. Very likely. But you will come—won’t you?”

I had made up my mind that no Fyne of either sex would make me walk three miles (there and back to their cottage) on this fine day. If the Fynes had been an average sociable couple one knows only because leisure must be got through somehow, I would have made short work of that special invitation. But they were not that. Their undeniable humanity had to be acknowledged. At the same time I wanted to have my own way. So I proposed that I should be allowed the pleasure of offering them a cup of tea at my rooms.

A short reflective pause—and Fyne accepted eagerly in his own and his wife’s name. A moment after I heard the click of the gate-latch and then in an ecstasy of barking from his demonstrative dog his serious head went past my window on the other side of the hedge, its troubled gaze fixed forward, and the mind inside obviously employed in earnest speculation of an intricate nature. One at least of his wife’s girl-friends had become more than a mere shadow for him. I surmised however that it was not of the girl-friend but of his wife that Fyne was thinking. He was an excellent husband.

I prepared myself for the afternoon’s hospitalities, calling in the farmer’s wife and reviewing with her the resources of the house and the village. She was a helpful woman. But the resources of my sagacity I did not review. Except in the gross material sense of the afternoon tea I made no preparations for Mrs. Fyne.

It was impossible for me to make any such preparations. I could not tell what sort of sustenance she would look for from my sagacity. And as to taking stock of the wares of my mind no one I imagine is anxious to do that sort of thing if it can be avoided. A vaguely grandiose state of mental self-confidence is much too agreeable to be disturbed recklessly by such a delicate investigation. Perhaps if I had had a helpful woman at my elbow, a dear, flattering acute, devoted woman … There are in life moments when one positively regrets not being married. No! I don’t exaggerate. I have said—moments, not years or even days. Moments. The farmer’s wife obviously could not be asked to assist. She could not have been expected to possess the necessary insight and I doubt whether she would have known how to be flattering enough. She was being helpful in her own way, with an extraordinary black bonnet on her head, a good mile off by that time, trying to discover in the village shops a piece of eatable cake. The pluck of women! The optimism of the dear creatures!

And she managed to find something which looked eatable. That’s all I know as I had no opportunity to observe the more intimate effects of that comestible. I myself never eat cake, and Mrs. Fyne, when she arrived punctually, brought with her no appetite for cake. She had no appetite for anything. But she had a thirst—the sign of deep, of tormenting emotion. Yes it was emotion, not the brilliant sunshine—more brilliant than warm as is the way of our discreet self-repressed, distinguished, insular sun, which would not turn a real lady scarlet—not on any account. Mrs. Fyne looked even cool. She wore a white skirt and coat; a white hat with a large brim reposed on her smoothly arranged hair. The coat was cut something like an army mess-jacket and the style suited her. I dare say there are many youthful subalterns, and not the worst-looking too, who resemble Mrs. Fyne in the type of face, in the sunburnt complexion, down to that something alert in bearing. But not many would have had that aspect breathing a readiness to assume any responsibility under Heaven. This is the sort of courage which ripens late in life and of course Mrs. Fyne was of mature years for all her unwrinkled face.

She looked round the room, told me positively that I was very comfortable there; to which I assented, humbly, acknowledging my undeserved good fortune.

“Why undeserved?” she wanted to know.

“I engaged these rooms by letter without asking any questions. It might have been an abominable hole,” I explained to her. “I always do things like that. I don’t like to be bothered. This is no great proof of sagacity—is it? Sagacious people I believe like to exercise that faculty. I have heard that they can’t even help showing it in the veriest trifles. It must be very delightful. But I know nothing of it. I think that I have no sagacity—no practical sagacity.”

Fyne made an inarticulate bass murmur of protest. I asked after the children whom I had not seen yet since my return from town. They had been very well. They were always well. Both Fyne and Mrs. Fyne spoke of the rude health of their children as if it were a result of moral excellence; in a peculiar tone which seemed to imply some contempt for people whose children were liable to be unwell at times. One almost felt inclined to apologize for the inquiry. And this annoyed me; unreasonably, I admit, because the assumption of superior merit is not a very exceptional weakness. Anxious to make myself disagreeable by way of retaliation I observed in accents of interested civility that the dear girls must have been wondering at the sudden disappearance of their mother’s young friend. Had they been putting any awkward questions about Miss Smith. Wasn’t it as Miss Smith that Miss de Barral had been introduced to me?

Mrs. Fyne, staring fixedly but also colouring deeper under her tan, told me that the children had never liked Flora very much. She hadn’t the high spirits which endear grown-ups to healthy children, Mrs. Fyne explained unflinchingly. Flora had been staying at the cottage several times before. Mrs. Fyne assured me that she often found it very difficult to have her in the house.

“But what else could we do?” she exclaimed.

That little cry of distress quite genuine in its inexpressiveness, altered my feeling towards Mrs. Fyne. It would have been so easy to have done nothing and to have thought no more about it. My liking for her began while she was trying to tell me of the night she spent by the girl’s bedside, the night before her departure with her unprepossessing relative. That Mrs. Fyne found means to comfort the child I doubt very much. She had not the genius for the task of undoing that which the hate of an infuriated woman had planned so well.

You will tell me perhaps that children’s impressions are not durable. That’s true enough. But here, child is only a manner of speaking. The girl was within a few days of her sixteenth birthday; she was old enough to be matured by the shock. The very effort she had to make in conveying the impression to Mrs. Fyne, in remembering the details, in finding adequate words—or any words at all—was in itself a terribly enlightening, an ageing process. She had talked a long time, uninterrupted by Mrs. Fyne, childlike enough in her wonder and pain, pausing now and then to interject the pitiful query: “It was cruel of her. Wasn’t it cruel, Mrs. Fyne?”

For Charley she found excuses. He at any rate had not said anything, while he had looked very gloomy and miserable. He couldn’t have taken part against his aunt—could he? But after all he did, when she called upon him, take “that cruel woman away.” He had dragged her out by the arm. She had seen that plainly. She remembered it. That was it! The woman was mad. “Oh! Mrs. Fyne, don’t tell me she wasn’t mad. If you had only seen her face …”

But Mrs. Fyne was unflinching in her idea that as much truth as could be told was due in the way of kindness to the girl, whose fate she feared would be to live exposed to the hardest realities of unprivileged existences. She explained to her that there were in the world evil-minded, selfish people. Unscrupulous people … These two persons had been after her father’s money. The best thing she could do was to forget all about them.

“After papa’s money? I don’t understand,” poor Flora de Barral had murmured, and lay still as if trying to think it out in the silence and shadows of the room where only a night-light was burning. Then she had a long shivering fit while holding tight the hand of Mrs. Fyne whose patient immobility by the bedside of that brutally murdered childhood did infinite honour to her humanity. That vigil must have been the more trying because I could see very well that at no time did she think the victim particularly charming or sympathetic. It was a manifestation of pure compassion, of compassion in itself, so to speak, not many women would have been capable of displaying with that unflinching steadiness. The shivering fit over, the girl’s next words in an outburst of sobs were, “Oh! Mrs. Fyne, am I really such a horrid thing as she has made me out to be?”

“No, no!” protested Mrs. Fyne. “It is your former governess who is horrid and odious. She is a vile woman. I cannot tell you that she was mad but I think she must have been beside herself with rage and full of evil thoughts. You must try not to think of these abominations, my dear child.”

They were not fit for anyone to think of much, Mrs. Fyne commented to me in a curt positive tone. All that had been very trying. The girl was like a creature struggling under a net.

“But how can I forget? she called my father a cheat and a swindler! Do tell me Mrs. Fyne that it isn’t true. It can’t be true. How can it be true?”

She sat up in bed with a sudden wild motion as if to jump out and flee away from the sound of the words which had just passed her own lips. Mrs. Fyne restrained her, soothed her, induced her at last to lay her head on her pillow again, assuring her all the time that nothing this woman had had the cruelty to say deserved to be taken to heart. The girl, exhausted, cried quietly for a time. It may be she had noticed something evasive in Mrs. Fyne’s assurances. After a while, without stirring, she whispered brokenly:

“That awful woman told me that all the world would call papa these awful names. Is it possible? Is it possible?”

Mrs. Fyne kept silent.

“Do say something to me, Mrs. Fyne,” the daughter of de Barral insisted in the same feeble whisper.

Again Mrs. Fyne assured me that it had been very trying. Terribly trying. “Yes, thanks, I will.” She leaned back in the chair with folded arms while I poured another cup of tea for her, and Fyne went out to pacify the dog which, tied up under the porch, had become suddenly very indignant at somebody having the audacity to walk along the lane. Mrs. Fyne stirred her tea for a long time, drank a little, put the cup down and said with that air of accepting all the consequences:

“Silence would have been unfair. I don’t think it would have been kind either. I told her that she must be prepared for the world passing a very severe judgment on her father …”

* * * * *

“Wasn’t it admirable,” cried Marlow interrupting his narrative. “Admirable!” And as I looked dubiously at this unexpected enthusiasm he started justifying it after his own manner.

“I say admirable because it was so characteristic. It was perfect. Nothing short of genius could have found better. And this was nature! As they say of an artist’s work: this was a perfect Fyne. Compassion—judiciousness—something correctly measured. None of your dishevelled sentiment. And right! You must confess that nothing could have been more right. I had a mind to shout “Brava! Brava!” but I did not do that. I took a piece of cake and went out to bribe the Fyne dog into some sort of self-control. His sharp comical yapping was unbearable, like stabs through one’s brain, and Fyne’s deeply modulated remonstrances abashed the vivacious animal no more than the deep, patient murmur of the sea abashes a nigger minstrel on a popular beach. Fyne was beginning to swear at him in low, sepulchral tones when I appeared. The dog became at once wildly demonstrative, half strangling himself in his collar, his eyes and tongue hanging out in the excess of his incomprehensible affection for me. This was before he caught sight of the cake in my hand. A series of vertical springs high up in the air followed, and then, when he got the cake, he instantly lost his interest in everything else.

Fyne was slightly vexed with me. As kind a master as any dog could wish to have, he yet did not approve of cake being given to dogs. The Fyne dog was supposed to lead a Spartan existence on a diet of repulsive biscuits with an occasional dry, hygienic, bone thrown in. Fyne looked down gloomily at the appeased animal, I too looked at that fool-dog; and (you know how one’s memory gets suddenly stimulated) I was reminded visually, with an almost painful distinctness, of the ghostly white face of the girl I saw last accompanied by that dog—deserted by that dog. I almost heard her distressed voice as if on the verge of resentful tears calling to the dog, the unsympathetic dog. Perhaps she had not the power of evoking sympathy, that personal gift of direct appeal to the feelings. I said to Fyne, mistrusting the supine attitude of the dog:

“Why don’t you let him come inside?”

Oh dear no! He couldn’t think of it! I might indeed have saved my breath, I knew it was one of the Fynes’ rules of life, part of their solemnity and responsibility, one of those things that were part of their unassertive but ever present superiority, that their dog must not be allowed in. It was most improper to intrude the dog into the houses of the people they were calling on—if it were only a careless bachelor in farmhouse lodgings and a personal friend of the dog. It was out of the question. But they would let him bark one’s sanity away outside one’s window. They were strangely consistent in their lack of imaginative sympathy. I didn’t insist but simply led the way back to the parlour, hoping that no wayfarer would happen along the lane for the next hour or so to disturb the dog’s composure.

Mrs. Fyne seated immovable before the table charged with plates, cups, jugs, a cold teapot, crumbs, and the general litter of the entertainment turned her head towards us.

“You see, Mr. Marlow,” she said in an unexpectedly confidential tone: “they are so utterly unsuited for each other.”

At the moment I did not know how to apply this remark. I thought at first of Fyne and the dog. Then I adjusted it to the matter in hand which was neither more nor less than an elopement. Yes, by Jove! It was something very much like an elopement—with certain unusual characteristics of its own which made it in a sense equivocal. With amused wonder I remembered that my sagacity was requisitioned in such a connection. How unexpected! But we never know what tests our gifts may be put to. Sagacity dictated caution first of all. I believe caution to be the first duty of sagacity. Fyne sat down as if preparing himself to witness a joust, I thought.

“Do you think so, Mrs. Fyne?” I said sagaciously. “Of course you are in a position …” I was continuing with caution when she struck out vivaciously for immediate assent.

“Obviously! Clearly! You yourself must admit …”

“But, Mrs. Fyne,” I remonstrated, “you forget that I don’t know your brother.”

This argument which was not only sagacious but true, overwhelmingly true, unanswerably true, seemed to surprise her.

I wondered why. I did not know enough of her brother for the remotest guess at what he might be like. I had never set eyes on the man. I didn’t know him so completely that by contrast I seemed to have known Miss de Barral—whom I had seen twice (altogether about sixty minutes) and with whom I had exchanged about sixty words—from the cradle so to speak. And perhaps, I thought, looking down at Mrs. Fyne (I had remained standing) perhaps she thinks that this ought to be enough for a sagacious assent.

She kept silent; and I looking at her with polite expectation, went on addressing her mentally in a mood of familiar approval which would have astonished her had it been audible: You my dear at any rate are a sincere woman …”

“I call a woman sincere,” Marlow began again after giving me a cigar and lighting one himself, “I call a woman sincere when she volunteers a statement resembling remotely in form what she really would like to say, what she really thinks ought to be said if it were not for the necessity to spare the stupid sensitiveness of men. The women’s rougher, simpler, more upright judgment, embraces the whole truth, which their tact, their mistrust of masculine idealism, ever prevents them from speaking in its entirety. And their tact is unerring. We could not stand women speaking the truth. We could not bear it. It would cause infinite misery and bring about most awful disturbances in this rather mediocre, but still idealistic fool’s paradise in which each of us lives his own little life—the unit in the great sum of existence. And they know it. They are merciful. This generalization does not apply exactly to Mrs. Fyne’s outburst of sincerity in a matter in which neither my affections nor my vanity were engaged. That’s why, may be, she ventured so far. For a woman she chose to be as open as the day with me. There was not only the form but almost the whole substance of her thought in what she said. She believed she could risk it. She had reasoned somewhat in this way; there’s a man, possessing a certain amount of sagacity …”

Marlow paused with a whimsical look at me. The last few words he had spoken with the cigar in his teeth. He took it out now by an ample movement of his arm and blew a thin cloud.

“You smile? It would have been more kind to spare my blushes. But as a matter of fact I need not blush. This is not vanity; it is analysis. We’ll let sagacity stand. But we must also note what sagacity in this connection stands for. When you see this you shall see also that there was nothing in it to alarm my modesty. I don’t think Mrs. Fyne credited me with the possession of wisdom tempered by common sense. And had I had the wisdom of the Seven Sages of Antiquity, she would not have been moved to confidence or admiration. The secret scorn of women for the capacity to consider judiciously and to express profoundly a meditated conclusion is unbounded. They have no use for these lofty exercises which they look upon as a sort of purely masculine game—game meaning a respectable occupation devised to kill time in this man-arranged life which must be got through somehow. What women’s acuteness really respects are the inept “ideas” and the sheeplike impulses by which our actions and opinions are determined in matters of real importance. For if women are not rational they are indeed acute. Even Mrs. Fyne was acute. The good woman was making up to her husband’s chess-player simply because she had scented in him that small portion of ‘femininity,’ that drop of superior essence of which I am myself aware; which, I gratefully acknowledge, has saved me from one or two misadventures in my life either ridiculous or lamentable, I am not very certain which. It matters very little. Anyhow misadventures. Observe that I say ‘femininity,’ a privilege—not ‘feminism,’ an attitude. I am not a feminist. It was Fyne who on certain solemn grounds had adopted that mental attitude; but it was enough to glance at him sitting on one side, to see that he was purely masculine to his finger-tips, masculine solidly, densely, amusingly—hopelessly.

I did glance at him. You don’t get your sagacity recognized by a man’s wife without feeling the propriety and even the need to glance at the man now and again. So I glanced at him. Very masculine. So much so that “hopelessly” was not the last word of it. He was helpless. He was bound and delivered by it. And if by the obscure promptings of my composite temperament I beheld him with malicious amusement, yet being in fact, by definition and especially from profound conviction, a man, I could not help sympathizing with him largely. Seeing him thus disarmed, so completely captive by the very nature of things I was moved to speak to him kindly.

“Well. And what do you think of it?”

“I don’t know. How’s one to tell? But I say that the thing is done now and there’s an end of it,” said the masculine creature as bluntly as his innate solemnity permitted.

Mrs. Fyne moved a little in her chair. I turned to her and remarked gently that this was a charge, a criticism, which was often made. Some people always ask: What could he see in her? Others wonder what she could have seen in him? Expressions of unsuitability.

She said with all the emphasis of her quietly folded arms:

“I know perfectly well what Flora has seen in my brother.”

I bowed my head to the gust but pursued my point.

“And then the marriage in most cases turns out no worse than the average, to say the least of it.”

Mrs. Fyne was disappointed by the optimistic turn of my sagacity. She rested her eyes on my face as though in doubt whether I had enough femininity in my composition to understand the case.

I waited for her to speak. She seemed to be asking herself; Is it after all, worth while to talk to that man? You understand how provoking this was. I looked in my mind for something appallingly stupid to say, with the object of distressing and teasing Mrs. Fyne. It is humiliating to confess a failure. One would think that a man of average intelligence could command stupidity at will. But it isn’t so. I suppose it’s a special gift or else the difficulty consists in being relevant. Discovering that I could find no really telling stupidity, I turned to the next best thing; a platitude. I advanced, in a common-sense tone, that, surely, in the matter of marriage a man had only himself to please.

Mrs. Fyne received this without the flutter of an eyelid. Fyne’s masculine breast, as might have been expected, was pierced by that old, regulation shaft. He grunted most feelingly. I turned to him with false simplicity. “Don’t you agree with me?”

“The very thing I’ve been telling my wife,” he exclaimed in his extra-manly bass. “We have been discussing—”

A discussion in the Fyne ménage! How portentous! Perhaps the very first difference they had ever had: Mrs. Fyne unflinching and ready for any responsibility, Fyne solemn and shrinking—the children in bed upstairs; and outside the dark fields, the shadowy contours of the land on the starry background of the universe, with the crude light of the open window like a beacon for the truant who would never come back now; a truant no longer but a downright fugitive. Yet a fugitive carrying off spoils. It was the flight of a raider—or a traitor? This affair of the purloined brother, as I had named it to myself, had a very puzzling physiognomy. The girl must have been desperate, I thought, hearing the grave voice of Fyne well enough but catching the sense of his words not at all, except the very last words which were:

“Of course, it’s extremely distressing.”

I looked at him inquisitively. What was distressing him? The purloining of the son of the poet-tyrant by the daughter of the financier-convict. Or only, if I may say so, the wind of their flight disturbing the solemn placidity of the Fynes’ domestic atmosphere. My incertitude did not last long, for he added:

“Mrs. Fyne urges me to go to London at once.”

One could guess at, almost see, his profound distaste for the journey, his distress at a difference of feeling with his wife. With his serious view of the sublunary comedy Fyne suffered from not being able to agree solemnly with her sentiment as he was accustomed to do, in recognition of having had his way in one supreme instance; when he made her elope with him—the most momentous step imaginable in a young lady’s life. He had been really trying to acknowledge it by taking the rightness of her feeling for granted on every other occasion. It had become a sort of habit at last. And it is never pleasant to break a habit. The man was deeply troubled. I said: “Really! To go to London!”

He looked dumbly into my eyes. It was pathetic and funny. “And you of course feel it would be useless,” I pursued.

He evidently felt that, though he said nothing. He only went on blinking at me with a solemn and comical slowness. “Unless it be to carry there the family’s blessing,” I went on, indulging my chaffing humour steadily, in a rather sneaking fashion, for I dared not look at Mrs. Fyne, to my right. No sound or movement came from that direction. “You think very naturally that to match mere good, sound reasons, against the passionate conclusions of love is a waste of intellect bordering on the absurd.”

He looked surprised as if I had discovered something very clever. He, dear man, had thought of nothing at all.

He simply knew that he did not want to go to London on that mission. Mere masculine delicacy. In a moment he became enthusiastic.

“Yes! Yes! Exactly. A man in love … You hear, my dear? Here you have an independent opinion—”

“Can anything be more hopeless,” I insisted to the fascinated little Fyne, “than to pit reason against love. I must confess however that in this case when I think of that poor girl’s sharp chin I wonder if …”

My levity was too much for Mrs. Fyne. Still leaning back in her chair she exclaimed:

“Mr. Marlow!”

* * * * *

As if mysteriously affected by her indignation the absurd Fyne dog began to bark in the porch. It might have been at a trespassing bumble-bee however. That animal was capable of any eccentricity. Fyne got up quickly and went out to him. I think he was glad to leave us alone to discuss that matter of his journey to London. A sort of anti-sentimental journey. He, too, apparently, had confidence in my sagacity. It was touching, this confidence. It was at any rate more genuine than the confidence his wife pretended to have in her husband’s chess-player, of three successive holidays. Confidence be hanged! Sagacity—indeed! She had simply marched in without a shadow of misgiving to make me back her up. But she had delivered herself into my hands …”

Interrupting his narrative Marlow addressed me in his tone between grim jest and grim earnest:

“Perhaps you didn’t know that my character is upon the whole rather vindictive.”

“No, I didn’t know,” I said with a grin. “That’s rather unusual for a sailor. They always seemed to me the least vindictive body of men in the world.”

“H’m! Simple souls,” Marlow muttered moodily. “Want of opportunity. The world leaves them alone for the most part. For myself it’s towards women that I feel vindictive mostly, in my small way. I admit that it is small. But then the occasions in themselves are not great. Mainly I resent that pretence of winding us round their dear little fingers, as of right. Not that the result ever amounts to much generally. There are so very few momentous opportunities. It is the assumption that each of us is a combination of a kid and an imbecile which I find provoking—in a small way; in a very small way. You needn’t stare as though I were breathing fire and smoke out of my nostrils. I am not a women-devouring monster. I am not even what is technically called “a brute.” I hope there’s enough of a kid and an imbecile in me to answer the requirements of some really good woman eventually—some day … Some day. Why do you gasp? You don’t suppose I should be afraid of getting married? That supposition would be offensive …”

“I wouldn’t dream of offending you,” I said.

“Very well. But meantime please remember that I was not married to Mrs. Fyne. That lady’s little finger was none of my legal property. I had not run off with it. It was Fyne who had done that thing. Let him be wound round as much as his backbone could stand—or even more, for all I cared. His rushing away from the discussion on the transparent pretence of quieting the dog confirmed my notion of there being a considerable strain on his elasticity. I confronted Mrs. Fyne resolved not to assist her in her eminently feminine occupation of thrusting a stick in the spokes of another woman’s wheel.

She tried to preserve her calm-eyed superiority. She was familiar and olympian, fenced in by the tea-table, that excellent symbol of domestic life in its lighter hour and its perfect security. In a few severely unadorned words she gave me to understand that she had ventured to hope for some really helpful suggestion from me. To this almost chiding declaration—because my vindictiveness seldom goes further than a bit of teasing—I said that I was really doing my best. And being a physiognomist …”

“Being what?” she interrupted me.

“A physiognomist,” I repeated raising my voice a little. “A physiognomist, Mrs. Fyne. And on the principles of that science a pointed little chin is a sufficient ground for interference. You want to interfere—do you not?”

Her eyes grew distinctly bigger. She had never been bantered before in her life. The late subtle poet’s method of making himself unpleasant was merely savage and abusive. Fyne had been always solemnly subservient. What other men she knew I cannot tell but I assume they must have been gentlemanly creatures. The girl-friends sat at her feet. How could she recognize my intention. She didn’t know what to make of my tone.

“Are you serious in what you say?” she asked slowly. And it was touching. It was as if a very young, confiding girl had spoken. I felt myself relenting.

“No. I am not, Mrs. Fyne,” I said. “I didn’t know I was expected to be serious as well as sagacious. No. That science is farcical and therefore I am not serious. It’s true that most sciences are farcical except those which teach us how to put things together.”

“The question is how to keep these two people apart,” she struck in. She had recovered. I admired the quickness of women’s wit. Mental agility is a rare perfection. And aren’t they agile! Aren’t they—just! And tenacious! When they once get hold you may uproot the tree but you won’t shake them off the branch. In fact the more you shake … But only look at the charm of contradictory perfections! No wonder men give in—generally. I won’t say I was actually charmed by Mrs. Fyne. I was not delighted with her. What affected me was not what she displayed but something which she could not conceal. And that was emotion—nothing less. The form of her declaration was dry, almost peremptory—but not its tone. Her voice faltered just the least bit, she smiled faintly; and as we were looking straight at each other I observed that her eyes were glistening in a peculiar manner. She was distressed. And indeed that Mrs. Fyne should have appealed to me at all was in itself the evidence of her profound distress. “By Jove she’s desperate too,” I thought. This discovery was followed by a movement of instinctive shrinking from this unreasonable and unmasculine affair. They were all alike, with their supreme interest aroused only by fighting with each other about some man: a lover, a son, a brother.

“But do you think there’s time yet to do anything?” I asked.

She had an impatient movement of her shoulders without detaching herself from the back of the chair. Time! Of course? It was less than forty-eight hours since she had followed him to London … I am no great clerk at those matters but I murmured vaguely an allusion to special licences. We couldn’t tell what might have happened to-day already. But she knew better, scornfully. Nothing had happened.

“Nothing’s likely to happen before next Friday week—if then.”

This was wonderfully precise. Then after a pause she added that she should never forgive herself if some effort were not made, an appeal.

“To your brother?” I asked.

“Yes. John ought to go to-morrow. Nine o’clock train.”

“So early as that!” I said. But I could not find it in my heart to pursue this discussion in a jocular tone. I submitted to her several obvious arguments, dictated apparently by common sense but in reality by my secret compassion. Mrs. Fyne brushed them aside, with the semi-conscious egoism of all safe, established, existences. They had known each other so little. Just three weeks. And of that time, too short for the birth of any serious sentiment, the first week had to be deducted. They would hardly look at each other to begin with. Flora barely consented to acknowledge Captain Anthony’s presence. Good morning—good night—that was all—absolutely the whole extent of their intercourse. Captain Anthony was a silent man, completely unused to the society of girls of any sort and so shy in fact that he avoided raising his eyes to her face at the table. It was perfectly absurd. It was even inconvenient, embarrassing to her—Mrs. Fyne. After breakfast Flora would go off by herself for a long walk and Captain Anthony (Mrs. Fyne referred to him at times also as Roderick) joined the children. But he was actually too shy to get on terms with his own nieces.

This would have sounded pathetic if I hadn’t known the Fyne children who were at the same time solemn and malicious, and nursed a secret contempt for all the world. No one could get on terms with those fresh and comely young monsters! They just tolerated their parents and seemed to have a sort of mocking understanding among themselves against all outsiders, yet with no visible affection for each other. They had the habit of exchanging derisive glances which to a shy man must have been very trying. They thought their uncle no doubt a bore and perhaps an ass.

I was not surprised to hear that very soon Anthony formed the habit of crossing the two neighbouring fields to seek the shade of a clump of elms at a good distance from the cottage. He lay on the grass and smoked his pipe all the morning. Mrs. Fyne wondered at her brother’s indolent habits. He had asked for books it is true but there were but few in the cottage. He read them through in three days and then continued to lie contentedly on his back with no other companion but his pipe. Amazing indolence! The live-long morning, Mrs. Fyne, busy writing upstairs in the cottage, could see him out of the window. She had a very long sight, and these elms were grouped on a rise of the ground. His indolence was plainly exposed to her criticism on a gentle green slope. Mrs. Fyne wondered at it; she was disgusted too. But having just then ‘commenced author,’ as you know, she could not tear herself away from the fascinating novelty. She let him wallow in his vice. I imagine Captain Anthony must have had a rather pleasant time in a quiet way. It was, I remember, a hot dry summer, favourable to contemplative life out of doors. And Mrs. Fyne was scandalized. Women don’t understand the force of a contemplative temperament. It simply shocks them. They feel instinctively that it is the one which escapes best the domination of feminine influences. The dear girls were exchanging jeering remarks about “lazy uncle Roderick” openly, in her indulgent hearing. And it was so strange, she told me, because as a boy he was anything but indolent. On the contrary. Always active.

I remarked that a man of thirty-five was no longer a boy. It was an obvious remark but she received it without favour. She told me positively that the best, the nicest men remained boys all their lives. She was disappointed not to be able to detect anything boyish in her brother. Very, very sorry. She had not seen him for fifteen years or thereabouts, except on three or four occasions for a few hours at a time. No. Not a trace of the boy, he used to be, left in him.

She fell silent for a moment and I mused idly on the boyhood of little Fyne. I could not imagine what it might have been like. His dominant trait was clearly the remnant of still earlier days, because I’ve never seen such staring solemnity as Fyne’s except in a very young baby. But where was he all that time? Didn’t he suffer contamination from the indolence of Captain Anthony, I inquired. I was told that Mr. Fyne was very little at the cottage at the time. Some colleague of his was convalescing after a severe illness in a little seaside village in the neighbourhood and Fyne went off every morning by train to spend the day with the elderly invalid who had no one to look after him. It was a very praiseworthy excuse for neglecting his brother-in-law “the son of the poet, you know,” with whom he had nothing in common even in the remotest degree. If Captain Anthony (Roderick) had been a pedestrian it would have been sufficient; but he was not. Still, in the afternoon, he went sometimes for a slow casual stroll, by himself of course, the children having definitely cold-shouldered him, and his only sister being busy with that inflammatory book which was to blaze upon the world a year or more afterwards. It seems however that she was capable of detaching her eyes from her task now and then, if only for a moment, because it was from that garret fitted out for a study that one afternoon she observed her brother and Flora de Barral coming down the road side by side. They had met somewhere accidentally (which of them crossed the other’s path, as the saying is, I don’t know), and were returning to tea together. She noticed that they appeared to be conversing without constraint.

“I had the simplicity to be pleased,” Mrs. Fyne commented with a dry little laugh. “Pleased for both their sakes.” Captain Anthony shook off his indolence from that day forth, and accompanied Miss Flora frequently on her morning walks. Mrs. Fyne remained pleased. She could now forget them comfortably and give herself up to the delights of audacious thought and literary composition. Only a week before the blow fell she, happening to raise her eyes from the paper, saw two figures seated on the grass under the shade of the elms. She could make out the white blouse. There could be no mistake.

“I suppose they imagined themselves concealed by the hedge. They forgot no doubt I was working in the garret,” she said bitterly. “Or perhaps they didn’t care. They were right. I am rather a simple person …” She laughed again … “I was incapable of suspecting such duplicity.”

“Duplicity is a strong word, Mrs. Fyne—isn’t it?” I expostulated. “And considering that Captain Anthony himself …”

“Oh well—perhaps,” she interrupted me. Her eyes which never strayed away from mine, her set features, her whole immovable figure, how well I knew those appearances of a person who has “made up her mind.” A very hopeless condition that, specially in women. I mistrusted her concession so easily, so stonily made. She reflected a moment. “Yes. I ought to have said—ingratitude, perhaps.”

After having thus disengaged her brother and pushed the poor girl a little further off as it were—isn’t women’s cleverness perfectly diabolic when they are really put on their mettle?—after having done these things and also made me feel that I was no match for her, she went on scrupulously: “One doesn’t like to use that word either. The claim is very small. It’s so little one could do for her. Still …”

“I dare say,” I exclaimed, throwing diplomacy to the winds. “But really, Mrs. Fyne, it’s impossible to dismiss your brother like this out of the business …”

“She threw herself at his head,” Mrs. Fyne uttered firmly.

“He had no business to put his head in the way, then,” I retorted with an angry laugh. I didn’t restrain myself because her fixed stare seemed to express the purpose to daunt me. I was not afraid of her, but it occurred to me that I was within an ace of drifting into a downright quarrel with a lady and, besides, my guest. There was the cold teapot, the emptied cups, emblems of hospitality. It could not be. I cut short my angry laugh while Mrs. Fyne murmured with a slight movement of her shoulders, “He! Poor man! Oh come …”

By a great effort of will I found myself able to smile amiably, to speak with proper softness.

“My dear Mrs. Fyne, you forget that I don’t know him—not even by sight. It’s difficult to imagine a victim as passive as all that; but granting you the (I very nearly said: imbecility, but checked myself in time) innocence of Captain Anthony, don’t you think now, frankly, that there is a little of your own fault in what has happened. You bring them together, you leave your brother to himself!”

She sat up and leaning her elbow on the table sustained her head in her open palm casting down her eyes. Compunction? It was indeed a very off-hand way of treating a brother come to stay for the first time in fifteen years. I suppose she discovered very soon that she had nothing in common with that sailor, that stranger, fashioned and marked by the sea of long voyages. In her strong-minded way she had scorned pretences, had gone to her writing which interested her immensely. A very praiseworthy thing your sincere conduct—if it didn’t at times resemble brutality so much. But I don’t think it was compunction. That sentiment is rare in women …”

“Is it?” I interrupted indignantly.

“You know more women than I do,” retorted the unabashed Marlow. “You make it your business to know them—don’t you? You go about a lot amongst all sorts of people. You are a tolerably honest observer. Well, just try to remember how many instances of compunction you have seen. I am ready to take your bare word for it. Compunction! Have you ever seen as much as its shadow? Have you ever? Just a shadow—a passing shadow! I tell you it is so rare that you may call it non-existent. They are too passionate. Too pedantic. Too courageous with themselves—perhaps. No I don’t think for a moment that Mrs. Fyne felt the slightest compunction at her treatment of her sea-going brother. What he thought of it who can tell? It is possible that he wondered why he had been so insistently urged to come. It is possible that he wondered bitterly—or contemptuously—or humbly. And it may be that he was only surprised and bored. Had he been as sincere in his conduct as his only sister he would have probably taken himself off at the end of the second day. But perhaps he was afraid of appearing brutal. I am not far removed from the conviction that between the sincerities of his sister and of his dear nieces, Captain Anthony of the Ferndale must have had his loneliness brought home to his bosom for the first time of his life, at an age, thirty-five or thereabouts, when one is mature enough to feel the pang of such a discovery. Angry or simply sad but certainly disillusioned he wanders about and meets the girl one afternoon and under the sway of a strong feeling forgets his shyness. This is no supposition. It is a fact. There was such a meeting in which the shyness must have perished before we don’t know what encouragement, or in the community of mood made apparent by some casual word. You remember that Mrs. Fyne saw them one afternoon coming back to the cottage together. Don’t you think that I have hit on the psychology of the situation? …”

“Doubtless …” I began to ponder.

“I was very certain of my conclusions at the time,” Marlow went on impatiently. “But don’t think for a moment that Mrs. Fyne in her new attitude and toying thoughtfully with a teaspoon was about to surrender. She murmured:

“It’s the last thing I should have thought could happen.”

“You didn’t suppose they were romantic enough,” I suggested dryly.

She let it pass and with great decision but as if speaking to herself,

“Roderick really must be warned.”

She didn’t give me the time to ask of what precisely. She raised her head and addressed me.

“I am surprised and grieved more than I can tell you at Mr. Fyne’s resistance. We have been always completely at one on every question. And that we should differ now on a point touching my brother so closely is a most painful surprise to me.” Her hand rattled the teaspoon brusquely by an involuntary movement. “It is intolerable,” she added tempestuously—for Mrs. Fyne that is. I suppose she had nerves of her own like any other woman.

Under the porch where Fyne had sought refuge with the dog there was silence. I took it for a proof of deep sagacity. I don’t mean on the part of the dog. He was a confirmed fool.

I said:

“You want absolutely to interfere … ?” Mrs. Fyne nodded just perceptibly … “Well—for my part … but I don’t really know how matters stand at the present time. You have had a letter from Miss de Barral. What does that letter say?”

“She asks for her valise to be sent to her town address,” Mrs. Fyne uttered reluctantly and stopped. I waited a bit—then exploded.

“Well! What’s the matter? Where’s the difficulty? Does your husband object to that? You don’t mean to say that he wants you to appropriate the girl’s clothes?”

“Mr. Marlow!”

“Well, but you talk of a painful difference of opinion with your husband, and then, when I ask for information on the point, you bring out a valise. And only a few moments ago you reproached me for not being serious. I wonder who is the serious person of us two now.”

She smiled faintly and in a friendly tone, from which I concluded at once that she did not mean to show me the girl’s letter, she said that undoubtedly the letter disclosed an understanding between Captain Anthony and Flora de Barral.

“What understanding?” I pressed her. “An engagement is an understanding.”

“There is no engagement—not yet,” she said decisively. “That letter, Mr. Marlow, is couched in very vague terms. That is why—”

I interrupted her without ceremony.

“You still hope to interfere to some purpose. Isn’t it so? Yes? But how should you have liked it if anybody had tried to interfere between you and Mr. Fyne at the time when your understanding with each other could still have been described in vague terms?”

She had a genuine movement of astonished indignation. It is with the accent of perfect sincerity that she cried out at me:

“But it isn’t at all the same thing! How can you!”

Indeed how could I! The daughter of a poet and the daughter of a convict are not comparable in the consequences of their conduct if their necessity may wear at times a similar aspect. Amongst these consequences I could perceive undesirable cousins for these dear healthy girls, and such like, possible causes of embarrassment in the future.

“No! You can’t be serious,” Mrs. Fyne’s smouldering resentment broke out again. “You haven’t thought—”

“Oh yes, Mrs. Fyne! I have thought. I am still thinking. I am even trying to think like you.”

“Mr. Marlow,” she said earnestly. “Believe me that I really am thinking of my brother in all this …” I assured her that I quite believed she was. For there is no law of nature making it impossible to think of more than one person at a time. Then I said:

“She has told him all about herself of course.”

“All about her life,” assented Mrs. Fyne with an air, however, of making some mental reservation which I did not pause to investigate. “Her life!” I repeated. “That girl must have had a mighty bad time of it.”

“Horrible,” Mrs. Fyne admitted with a ready frankness very creditable under the circumstances, and a warmth of tone which made me look at her with a friendly eye. “Horrible! No! You can’t imagine the sort of vulgar people she became dependent on … You know her father never attempted to see her while he was still at large. After his arrest he instructed that relative of his—the odious person who took her away from Brighton—not to let his daughter come to the court during the trial. He refused to hold any communication with her whatever.”

I remembered what Mrs. Fyne had told me before of the view she had years ago of de Barral clinging to the child at the side of his wife’s grave and later on of these two walking hand in hand the observed of all eyes by the sea. Pictures from Dickens—pregnant with pathos.

VII

On the Pavement

‚ÄúFyne was not willing to talk; but as I had been already let into the secret, the fair-minded little man recognized that I had some right to information if I insisted on it. And I did insist, after the third game. We were yet some way from the end of our journey.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòOh, if you want to know,‚Äô was his somewhat impatient opening. And then he talked rather volubly. First of all his wife had not given him to read the letter received from Flora (I had suspected him of having it in his pocket), but had told him all about the contents. It was not at all what it should have been even if the girl had wished to affirm her right to disregard the feelings of all the world. Her own had been trampled in the dirt out of all shape. Extraordinary thing to say‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI would admit, for a young girl of her age. The whole tone of that letter was wrong, quite wrong. It was certainly not the product of a‚ÅÝ‚Äîsay, of a well-balanced mind.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòIf she were given some sort of footing in this world,‚Äô I said, ‚Äòif only no bigger than the palm of my hand, she would probably learn to keep a better balance.‚Äô

‚ÄúFyne ignored this little remark. His wife, he said, was not the sort of person to be addressed mockingly on a serious subject. There was an unpleasant strain of levity in that letter, extending even to the references to Captain Anthony himself. Such a disposition was enough, his wife had pointed out to him, to alarm one for the future, had all the circumstances of that preposterous project been as satisfactory as in fact they were not. Other parts of the letter seemed to have a challenging tone‚ÅÝ‚Äîas if daring them (the Fynes) to approve her conduct. And at the same time implying that she did not care, that it was for their own sakes that she hoped they would ‚Äògo against the world‚ÅÝ‚Äîthe horrid world which had crushed poor papa.‚Äô

‚ÄúFyne called upon me to admit that this was pretty cool‚ÅÝ‚Äîconsidering. And there was another thing, too. It seems that for the last six months (she had been assisting two ladies who kept a kindergarten school in Bayswater‚ÅÝ‚Äîa mere pittance), Flora had insisted on devoting all her spare time to the study of the trial. She had been looking up files of old newspapers, and working herself up into a state of indignation with what she called the injustice and the hypocrisy of the prosecution. Her father, Fyne reminded me, had made some palpable hits in his answers in Court, and she had fastened on them triumphantly. She had reached the conclusion of her father‚Äôs innocence, and had been brooding over it. Mrs.¬ÝFyne had pointed out to him the danger of this.

‚ÄúThe train ran into the station and Fyne, jumping out directly it came to a standstill, seemed glad to cut short the conversation. We walked in silence a little way, boarded a bus, then walked again. I don‚Äôt suppose that since the days of his childhood, when surely he was taken to see the Tower, he had been once east of Temple Bar. He looked about him sullenly; and when I pointed out in the distance the rounded front of the Eastern Hotel at the bifurcation of two very broad, mean, shabby thoroughfares, rising like a grey stucco tower above the lowly roofs of the dirty-yellow, two-storey houses, he only grunted disapprovingly.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI wouldn‚Äôt lay too much stress on what you have been telling me,‚Äô I observed quietly as we approached that unattractive building. ‚ÄòNo man will believe a girl who has just accepted his suit to be not well balanced‚ÅÝ‚Äîyou know.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòOh! Accepted his suit,‚Äô muttered Fyne, who seemed to have been very thoroughly convinced indeed. ‚ÄòIt may have been the other way about.‚Äô And then he added: ‚ÄòI am going through with it.‚Äô

‚ÄúI said that this was very praiseworthy but that a certain moderation of statement‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ He waved his hand at me and mended his pace. I guessed that he was anxious to get his mission over as quickly as possible. He barely gave himself time to shake hands with me and made a rush at the narrow glass door with the words Hotel Entrance on it. It swung to behind his back with no more noise than the snap of a toothless jaw.

‚ÄúThe absurd temptation to remain and see what would come of it got over my better judgment. I hung about irresolute, wondering how long an embassy of that sort would take, and whether Fyne on coming out would consent to be communicative. I feared he would be shocked at finding me there, would consider my conduct incorrect, conceivably treat me with contempt. I walked off a few paces. Perhaps it would be possible to read something on Fyne‚Äôs face as he came out; and, if necessary, I could always eclipse myself discreetly through the door of one of the bars. The ground floor of the Eastern Hotel was an unabashed pub, with plate-glass fronts, a display of brass rails, and divided into many compartments each having its own entrance.

‚ÄúBut of course all this was silly. The marriage, the love, the affairs of Captain Anthony were none of my business. I was on the point of moving down the street for good when my attention was attracted by a girl approaching the hotel entrance from the west. She was dressed very modestly in black. It was the white straw hat of a good form and trimmed with a bunch of pale roses which had caught my eye. The whole figure seemed familiar. Of course! Flora de Barral. She was making for the hotel, she was going in. And Fyne was with Captain Anthony! To meet him could not be pleasant for her. I wished to save her from the awkwardness, and as I hesitated what to do she looked up and our eyes happened to meet just as she was turning off the pavement into the hotel doorway. Instinctively I extended my arm. It was enough to make her stop. I suppose she had some faint notion that she had seen me before somewhere. She walked slowly forward, prudent and attentive, watching my faint smile.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòExcuse me,‚Äô I said directly she had approached me near enough. ‚ÄòPerhaps you would like to know that Mr.¬ÝFyne is upstairs with Captain Anthony at this moment.‚Äô

‚ÄúShe uttered a faint ‚ÄòAh! Mr.¬ÝFyne!‚Äô I could read in her eyes that she had recognized me now. Her serious expression extinguished the imbecile grin of which I was conscious. I raised my hat. She responded with a slow inclination of the head while her luminous, mistrustful, maiden‚Äôs glance seemed to whisper, ‚ÄòWhat is this one doing here?‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI came up to town with Fyne this morning,‚Äô I said in a businesslike tone. ‚ÄòI have to see a friend in East India Dock. Fyne and I parted this moment at the door here‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶‚Äô The girl regarded me with darkening eyes‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ ‚ÄòMrs.¬ÝFyne did not come with her husband,‚Äô I went on, then hesitated before that white face so still in the pearly shadow thrown down by the hat-brim. ‚ÄòBut she sent him,‚Äô I murmured by way of warning.

‚ÄúHer eyelids fluttered slowly over the fixed stare. I imagine she was not much disconcerted by this development. ‚ÄòI live a long way from here,‚Äô she whispered.

‚ÄúI said perfunctorily, ‚ÄòDo you?‚Äô And we remained gazing at each other. The uniform paleness of her complexion was not that of an anaemic girl. It had a transparent vitality and at that particular moment the faintest possible rosy tinge, the merest suspicion of colour; an equivalent, I suppose, in any other girl to blushing like a peony while she told me that Captain Anthony had arranged to show her the ship that morning.

‚ÄúIt was easy to understand that she did not want to meet Fyne. And when I mentioned in a discreet murmur that he had come because of her letter she glanced at the hotel door quickly, and moved off a few steps to a position where she could watch the entrance without being seen. I followed her. At the junction of the two thoroughfares she stopped in the thin traffic of the broad pavement and turned to me with an air of challenge. ‚ÄòAnd so you know.‚Äô

‚ÄúI told her that I had not seen the letter. I had only heard of it. She was a little impatient. ‚ÄòI mean all about me.‚Äô

‚ÄúYes. I knew all about her. The distress of Mr.¬Ýand Mrs.¬ÝFyne‚ÅÝ‚Äîespecially of Mrs.¬ÝFyne‚ÅÝ‚Äîwas so great that they would have shared it with anybody almost‚ÅÝ‚Äînot belonging to their circle of friends. I happened to be at hand‚ÅÝ‚Äîthat was all.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòYou understand that I am not their friend. I am only a holiday acquaintance.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòShe was not very much upset?‚Äô queried Flora de Barral, meaning, of course, Mrs.¬ÝFyne. And I admitted that she was less so than her husband‚ÅÝ‚Äîand even less than myself. Mrs.¬ÝFyne was a very self-possessed person which nothing could startle out of her extreme theoretical position. She did not seem startled when Fyne and I proposed going to the quarry.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòYou put that notion into their heads,‚Äô the girl said.

‚ÄúI advanced that the notion was in their heads already. But it was much more vividly in my head since I had seen her up there with my own eyes, tempting Providence.

‚ÄúShe was looking at me with extreme attention, and murmured:

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòIs that what you called it to them? Tempting‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòNo. I told them that you were making up your mind and I came along just then. I told them that you were saved by me. My shout checked you‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶‚Äô She moved her head gently from right to left in negation‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ ‚ÄòNo? Well, have it your own way.‚Äô

‚ÄúI thought to myself: She has found another issue. She wants to forget now. And no wonder. She wants to persuade herself that she had never known such an ugly and poignant minute in her life. ‚ÄòAfter all,‚Äô I conceded aloud, ‚Äòthings are not always what they seem.‚Äô

‚ÄúHer little head with its deep blue eyes, eyes of tenderness and anger under the black arch of fine eyebrows was very still. The mouth looked very red in the white face peeping from under the veil, the little pointed chin had in its form something aggressive. Slight and even angular in her modest black dress she was an appealing and‚ÅÝ‚Äîyes‚ÅÝ‚Äîshe was a desirable little figure.

‚ÄúHer lips moved very fast asking me:

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòAnd they believed you at once?‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòYes, they believed me at once. Mrs.¬ÝFyne‚Äôs word to us was ‚ÄòGo!‚Äô

‚ÄúA white gleam between the red lips was so short that I remained uncertain whether it was a smile or a ferocious baring of little even teeth. The rest of the face preserved its innocent, tense and enigmatical expression. She spoke rapidly.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòNo, it wasn‚Äôt your shout. I had been there some time before you saw me. And I was not there to tempt Providence, as you call it. I went up there for‚ÅÝ‚Äîfor what you thought I was going to do. Yes. I climbed two fences. I did not mean to leave anything to Providence. There seem to be people for whom Providence can do nothing. I suppose you are shocked to hear me talk like that?‚Äô

‚ÄúI shook my head. I was not shocked. What had kept her back all that time, till I appeared on the scene below, she went on, was neither fear nor any other kind of hesitation. One reaches a point, she said with appalling youthful simplicity, where nothing that concerns one matters any longer. But something did keep her back. I should have never guessed what it was. She herself confessed that it seemed absurd to say. It was the Fyne dog.

‚ÄúFlora de Barral paused, looking at me, with a peculiar expression and then went on. You see, she imagined the dog had become extremely attached to her. She took it into her head that he might fall over or jump down after her. She tried to drive him away. She spoke sternly to him. It only made him more frisky. He barked and jumped about her skirt in his usual, idiotic, high spirits. He scampered away in circles between the pines charging upon her and leaping as high as her waist. She commanded, ‚ÄòGo away. Go home.‚Äô She even picked up from the ground a bit of a broken branch and threw it at him. At this his delight knew no bounds; his rushes became faster, his yapping louder; he seemed to be having the time of his life. She was convinced that the moment she threw herself down he would spring over after her as if it were part of the game. She was vexed almost to tears. She was touched too. And when he stood still at some distance as if suddenly rooted to the ground wagging his tail slowly and watching her intensely with his shining eyes another fear came to her. She imagined herself gone and the creature sitting on the brink, its head thrown up to the sky and howling for hours. This thought was not to be borne. Then my shout reached her ears.

‚ÄúShe told me all this with simplicity. My voice had destroyed her poise‚ÅÝ‚Äîthe suicide poise of her mind. Every act of ours, the most criminal, the most mad presupposes a balance of thought, feeling and will, like a correct attitude for an effective stroke in a game. And I had destroyed it. She was no longer in proper form for the act. She was not very much annoyed. Next day would do. She would have to slip away without attracting the notice of the dog. She thought of the necessity almost tenderly. She came down the path carrying her despair with lucid calmness. But when she saw herself deserted by the dog, she had an impulse to turn round, go up again and be done with it. Not even that animal cared for her‚ÅÝ‚Äîin the end.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI really did think that he was attached to me. What did he want to pretend for, like this? I thought nothing could hurt me any more. Oh yes. I would have gone up, but I felt suddenly so tired. So tired. And then you were there. I didn‚Äôt know what you would do. You might have tried to follow me and I didn‚Äôt think I could run‚ÅÝ‚Äînot up hill‚ÅÝ‚Äînot then.‚Äô

‚ÄúShe had raised her white face a little, and it was queer to hear her say these things. At that time of the morning there are comparatively few people out in that part of the town. The broad interminable perspective of the East India Dock Road, the great perspective of drab brick walls, of grey pavement, of muddy roadway rumbling dismally with loaded carts and vans lost itself in the distance, imposing and shabby in its spacious meanness of aspect, in its immeasurable poverty of forms, of colouring, of life‚ÅÝ‚Äîunder a harsh, unconcerned sky dried by the wind to a clear blue. It had been raining during the night. The sunshine itself seemed poor. From time to time a few bits of paper, a little dust and straw whirled past us on the broad flat promontory of the pavement before the rounded front of the hotel.

‚ÄúFlora de Barral was silent for a while. I said:

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòAnd next day you thought better of it.‚Äô

‚ÄúAgain she raised her eyes to mine with that peculiar expression of informed innocence; and again her white cheeks took on the faintest tinge of pink‚ÅÝ‚Äîthe merest shadow of a blush.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòNext day,‚Äô she uttered distinctly, ‚ÄòI didn‚Äôt think. I remembered. That was enough. I remembered what I should never have forgotten. Never. And Captain Anthony arrived at the cottage in the evening.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòAh yes. Captain Anthony,‚Äô I murmured. And she repeated also in a murmur, ‚ÄòYes! Captain Anthony.‚Äô The faint flush of warm life left her face. I subdued my voice still more and not looking at her: ‚ÄòYou found him sympathetic?‚Äô I ventured.

‚ÄúHer long dark lashes went down a little with an air of calculated discretion. At least so it seemed to me. And yet no one could say that I was inimical to that girl. But there you are! Explain it as you may, in this world the friendless, like the poor, are always a little suspect, as if honesty and delicacy were only possible to the privileged few.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòWhy do you ask?‚Äô she said after a time, raising her eyes suddenly to mine in an effect of candour which on the same principle (of the disinherited not being to be trusted) might have been judged equivocal.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòIf you mean what right I have‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶‚Äô She move slightly a hand in a worn brown glove as much as to say she could not question anyone‚Äôs right against such an outcast as herself.

‚ÄúI ought to have been moved perhaps; but I only noted the total absence of humility‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ ‚ÄòNo right at all,‚Äô I continued, ‚Äòbut just interest. Mrs.¬ÝFyne‚ÅÝ‚Äîit‚Äôs too difficult to explain how it came about‚ÅÝ‚Äîhas talked to me of you‚ÅÝ‚Äîwell‚ÅÝ‚Äîextensively.‚Äô

‚ÄúNo doubt Mrs.¬ÝFyne had told me the truth, Flora said brusquely with an unexpected hoarseness of tone. This very dress she was wearing had been given her by Mrs.¬ÝFyne. Of course I looked at it. It could not have been a recent gift. Close-fitting and black, with heliotrope silk facings under a figured net, it looked far from new, just on this side of shabbiness; in fact, it accentuated the slightness of her figure, it went well in its suggestion of half mourning with the white face in which the unsmiling red lips alone seemed warm with the rich blood of life and passion.

‚ÄúLittle Fyne was staying up there an unconscionable time. Was he arguing, preaching, remonstrating? Had he discovered in himself a capacity and a taste for that sort of thing? Or was he perhaps, in an intense dislike for the job, beating about the bush and only puzzling Captain Anthony, the providential man, who, if he expected the girl to appear at any moment, must have been on tenterhooks all the time, and beside himself with impatience to see the back of his brother-in-law. How was it that he had not got rid of Fyne long before in any case? I don‚Äôt mean by actually throwing him out of the window, but in some other resolute manner.

‚ÄúSurely Fyne had not impressed him. That he was an impressionable man I could not doubt. The presence of the girl there on the pavement before me proved this up to the hilt‚ÅÝ‚Äîand, well, yes, touchingly enough.

‚ÄúIt so happened that in their wanderings to and fro our glances met. They met and remained in contact more familiar than a handclasp, more communicative, more expressive. There was something comic too in the whole situation, in the poor girl and myself waiting together on the broad pavement at a corner public-house for the issue of Fyne‚Äôs ridiculous mission. But the comic when it is human becomes quickly painful. Yes, she was infinitely anxious. And I was asking myself whether this poignant tension of her suspense depended‚ÅÝ‚Äîto put it plainly‚ÅÝ‚Äîon hunger or love.

‚ÄúThe answer would have been of some interest to Captain Anthony. For my part, in the presence of a young girl I always become convinced that the dreams of sentiment‚ÅÝ‚Äîlike the consoling mysteries of Faith‚ÅÝ‚Äîare invincible; that it is never, never reason which governs men and women.

‚ÄúYet what sentiment could there have been on her part? I remembered her tone only a moment since when she said: ‚ÄòThat evening Captain Anthony arrived at the cottage.‚Äô And considering, too, what the arrival of Captain Anthony meant in this connection, I wondered at the calmness with which she could mention that fact. He arrived at the cottage. In the evening. I knew that late train. He probably walked from the station. The evening would be well advanced. I could almost see a dark indistinct figure opening the wicket gate of the garden. Where was she? Did she see him enter? Was she somewhere near by and did she hear without the slightest premonition his chance and fateful footsteps on the flagged path leading to the cottage door? In the shadow of the night made more cruelly sombre for her by the very shadow of death he must have appeared too strange, too remote, too unknown to impress himself on her thought as a living force‚ÅÝ‚Äîsuch a force as a man can bring to bear on a woman‚Äôs destiny.

‚ÄúShe glanced towards the hotel door again; I followed suit and then our eyes met once more, this time intentionally. A tentative, uncertain intimacy was springing up between us two. She said simply: ‚ÄòYou are waiting for Mr.¬ÝFyne to come out; are you?‚Äô

‚ÄúI admitted to her that I was waiting to see Mr.¬ÝFyne come out. That was all. I had nothing to say to him.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI have said yesterday all I had to say to him,‚Äô I added meaningly. ‚ÄòI have said it to them both, in fact. I have also heard all they had to say.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòAbout me?‚Äô she murmured.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòYes. The conversation was about you.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI wonder if they told you everything.‚Äô

‚ÄúIf she wondered I could do nothing else but wonder too. But I did not tell her that. I only smiled. The material point was that Captain Anthony should be told everything. But as to that I was very certain that the good sister would see to it. Was there anything more to disclose‚ÅÝ‚Äîsome other misery, some other deception of which that girl had been a victim? It seemed hardly probable. It was not even easy to imagine. What struck me most was her‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI suppose I must call it‚ÅÝ‚Äîcomposure. One could not tell whether she understood what she had done. One wondered. She was not so much unreadable as blank; and I did not know whether to admire her for it or dismiss her from my thoughts as a passive butt of ferocious misfortune.

‚ÄúLooking back at the occasion when we first got on speaking terms on the road by the quarry, I had to admit that she presented some points of a problematic appearance. I don‚Äôt know why I imagined Captain Anthony as the sort of man who would not be likely to take the initiative; not perhaps from indifference but from that peculiar timidity before women which often enough is found in conjunction with chivalrous instincts, with a great need for affection and great stability of feelings. Such men are easily moved. At the least encouragement they go forward with the eagerness, with the recklessness of starvation. This accounted for the suddenness of the affair. No! With all her inexperience this girl could not have found any great difficulty in her conquering enterprise. She must have begun it. And yet there she was, patient, almost unmoved, almost pitiful, waiting outside like a beggar, without a right to anything but compassion, for a promised dole.

‚ÄúEvery moment people were passing close by us, singly, in two and threes; the inhabitants of that end of the town where life goes on unadorned by grace or splendour; they passed us in their shabby garments, with sallow faces, haggard, anxious or weary, or simply without expression, in an unsmiling sombre stream not made up of lives but of mere unconsidered existences whose joys, struggles, thoughts, sorrows and their very hopes were miserable, glamourless, and of no account in the world. And when one thought of their reality to themselves one‚Äôs heart became oppressed. But of all the individuals who passed by none appeared to me for the moment so pathetic in unconscious patience as the girl standing before me; none more difficult to understand. It is perhaps because I was thinking of things which I could not ask her about.

‚ÄúIn fact we had nothing to say to each other; but we two, strangers as we really were to each other, had dealt with the most intimate and final of subjects, the subject of death. It had created a sort of bond between us. It made our silence weighty and uneasy. I ought to have left her there and then; but, as I think I‚Äôve told you before, the fact of having shouted her away from the edge of a precipice seemed somehow to have engaged my responsibility as to this other leap. And so we had still an intimate subject between us to lend more weight and more uneasiness to our silence. The subject of marriage. I use the word not so much in reference to the ceremony itself (I had no doubt of this, Captain Anthony being a decent fellow) or in view of the social institution in general, as to which I have no opinion, but in regard to the human relation. The first two views are not particularly interesting. The ceremony, I suppose, is adequate; the institution, I dare say, is useful or it would not have endured. But the human relation thus recognized is a mysterious thing in its origins, character and consequences. Unfortunately you can‚Äôt buttonhole familiarly a young girl as you would a young fellow. I don‚Äôt think that even another woman could really do it. She would not be trusted. There is not between women that fund of at least conditional loyalty which men may depend on in their dealings with each other. I believe that any woman would rather trust a man. The difficulty in such a delicate case was how to get on terms.

‚ÄúSo we held our peace in the odious uproar of that wide roadway thronged with heavy carts. Great vans carrying enormous piled-up loads advanced swaying like mountains. It was as if the whole world existed only for selling and buying and those who had nothing to do with the movement of merchandise were of no account.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòYou must be tired,‚Äô I said. One had to say something if only to assert oneself against that wearisome, passionless and crushing uproar. She raised her eyes for a moment. No, she was not. Not very. She had not walked all the way. She came by train as far as Whitechapel Station and had only walked from there.

‚ÄúShe had had an ugly pilgrimage; but whether of love or of necessity who could tell? And that precisely was what I should have liked to get at. This was not however a question to be asked point-blank, and I could not think of any effective circumlocution. It occurred to me too that she might conceivably know nothing of it herself‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI mean by reflection. That young woman had been obviously considering death. She had gone the length of forming some conception of it. But as to its companion fatality‚ÅÝ‚Äîlove, she, I was certain, had never reflected upon its meaning.

‚ÄúWith that man in the hotel, whom I did not know, and this girl standing before me in the street I felt that it was an exceptional case. He had broken away from his surroundings; she stood outside the pale. One aspect of conventions which people who declaim against them lose sight of is that conventions make both joy and suffering easier to bear in a becoming manner. But those two were outside all conventions. They would be as untrammelled in a sense as the first man and the first woman. The trouble was that I could not imagine anything about Flora de Barral and the brother of Mrs.¬ÝFyne. Or, if you like, I could imagine anything which comes practically to the same thing. Darkness and chaos are first cousins. I should have liked to ask the girl for a word which would give my imagination its line. But how was one to venture so far? I can be rough sometimes but I am not naturally impertinent. I would have liked to ask her for instance: ‚ÄòDo you know what you have done with yourself?‚Äô A question like that. Anyhow it was time for one of us to say something. A question it must be. And the question I asked was: ‚ÄòSo he‚Äôs going to show you the ship?‚Äô

‚ÄúShe seemed glad I had spoken at last and glad of the opportunity to speak herself.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòYes. He said he would‚ÅÝ‚Äîthis morning. Did you say you did not know Captain Anthony?‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòNo. I don‚Äôt know him. Is he anything like his sister?‚Äô

‚ÄúShe looked startled and murmured ‚ÄòSister!‚Äô in a puzzled tone which astonished me. ‚ÄòOh! Mrs.¬ÝFyne,‚Äô she exclaimed, recollecting herself, and avoiding my eyes while I looked at her curiously.

‚ÄúWhat an extraordinary detachment! And all the time the stream of shabby people was hastening by us, with the continuous dreary shuffling of weary footsteps on the flagstones. The sunshine falling on the grime of surfaces, on the poverty of tones and forms seemed of an inferior quality, its joy faded, its brilliance tarnished and dusty. I had to raise my voice in the dull vibrating noise of the roadway.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòYou don‚Äôt mean to say you have forgotten the connection?‚Äô

‚ÄúShe cried readily enough: ‚ÄòI wasn‚Äôt thinking.‚Äô And then, while I wondered what could have been the images occupying her brain at this time, she asked me: ‚ÄòYou didn‚Äôt see my letter to Mrs.¬ÝFyne‚ÅÝ‚Äîdid you?‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòNo. I didn‚Äôt,‚Äô I shouted. Just then the racket was distracting, a pair-horse trolly lightly loaded with loose rods of iron passing slowly very near us. ‚ÄòI wasn‚Äôt trusted so far.‚Äô And remembering Mrs.¬ÝFyne‚Äôs hints that the girl was unbalanced, I added: ‚ÄòWas it an unreserved confession you wrote?‚Äô

‚ÄúShe did not answer me for a time, and as I waited I thought that there‚Äôs nothing like a confession to make one look mad; and that of all confessions a written one is the most detrimental all round. Never confess! Never, never! An untimely joke is a source of bitter regret always. Sometimes it may ruin a man; not because it is a joke, but because it is untimely. And a confession of whatever sort is always untimely. The only thing which makes it supportable for a while is curiosity. You smile? Ah, but it is so, or else people would be sent to the rightabout at the second sentence. How many sympathetic souls can you reckon on in the world? One in ten, one in a hundred‚ÅÝ‚Äîin a thousand‚ÅÝ‚Äîin ten thousand? Ah! What a sell these confessions are! What a horrible sell! You seek sympathy, and all you get is the most evanescent sense of relief‚ÅÝ‚Äîif you get that much. For a confession, whatever it may be, stirs the secret depths of the hearer‚Äôs character. Often depths that he himself is but dimly aware of. And so the righteous triumph secretly, the lucky are amused, the strong are disgusted, the weak either upset or irritated with you according to the measure of their sincerity with themselves. And all of them in their hearts brand you for either mad or impudent‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶‚Äù

I had seldom seen Marlow so vehement, so pessimistic, so earnestly cynical before. I cut his declamation short by asking what answer Flora de Barral had given to his question. ‚ÄúDid the poor girl admit firing off her confidences at Mrs.¬ÝFyne‚ÅÝ‚Äîeight pages of close writing‚ÅÝ‚Äîthat sort of thing?‚Äù

Marlow shook his head.

‚ÄúShe did not tell me. I accepted her silence, as a kind of answer and remarked that it would have been better if she had simply announced the fact to Mrs.¬ÝFyne at the cottage. ‚ÄòWhy didn‚Äôt you do it?‚Äô I asked point-blank.

‚ÄúShe said: ‚ÄòI am not a very plucky girl.‚Äô She looked up at me and added meaningly: ‚ÄòAnd you know it. And you know why.‚Äô

‚ÄúI must remark that she seemed to have become very subdued since our first meeting at the quarry. Almost a different person from the defiant, angry and despairing girl with quivering lips and resentful glances.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI thought it was very sensible of you to get away from that sheer drop,‚Äô I said.

‚ÄúShe looked up with something of that old expression.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòThat‚Äôs not what I mean. I see you will have it that you saved my life. Nothing of the kind. I was concerned for that vile little beast of a dog. No! It was the idea of‚ÅÝ‚Äîof doing away with myself which was cowardly. That‚Äôs what I meant by saying I am not a very plucky girl.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòOh!‚Äô I retorted airily. ‚ÄòThat little dog. He isn‚Äôt really a bad little dog.‚Äô But she lowered her eyelids and went on:

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI was so miserable that I could think only of myself. This was mean. It was cruel too. And besides I had not given it up‚ÅÝ‚Äînot then.‚Äô‚Ää‚Äù

Marlow changed his tone.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI don‚Äôt know much of the psychology of self-destruction. It‚Äôs a sort of subject one has few opportunities to study closely. I knew a man once who came to my rooms one evening, and while smoking a cigar confessed to me moodily that he was trying to discover some graceful way of retiring out of existence. I didn‚Äôt study his case, but I had a glimpse of him the other day at a cricket match, with some women, having a good time. That seems a fairly reasonable attitude. Considered as a sin, it is a case for repentance before the throne of a merciful God. But I imagine that Flora de Barral‚Äôs religion under the care of the distinguished governess could have been nothing but outward formality. Remorse in the sense of gnawing shame and unavailing regret is only understandable to me when some wrong had been done to a fellow-creature. But why she, that girl who existed on sufferance, so to speak‚ÅÝ‚Äîwhy she should writhe inwardly with remorse because she had once thought of getting rid of a life which was nothing in every respect but a curse‚ÅÝ‚Äîthat I could not understand. I thought it was very likely some obscure influence of common forms of speech, some traditional or inherited feeling‚ÅÝ‚Äîa vague notion that suicide is a legal crime; words of old moralists and preachers which remain in the air and help to form all the authorized moral conventions. Yes, I was surprised at her remorse. But lowering her glance unexpectedly till her dark eyelashes seemed to rest against her white cheeks she presented a perfectly demure aspect. It was so attractive that I could not help a faint smile. That Flora de Barral should ever, in any aspect, have the power to evoke a smile was the very last thing I should have believed. She went on after a slight hesitation:

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòOne day I started for there, for that place.‚Äô

‚ÄúLook at the influence of a mere play of physiognomy! If you remember what we were talking about you will hardly believe that I caught myself grinning down at that demure little girl. I must say too that I felt more friendly to her at the moment than ever before.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòOh, you did? To take that jump? You are a determined young person. Well, what happened that time?‚Äô

‚ÄúAn almost imperceptible alteration in her bearing; a slight droop of her head perhaps‚ÅÝ‚Äîa mere nothing‚ÅÝ‚Äîmade her look more demure than ever.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI had left the cottage,‚Äô she began a little hurriedly. ‚ÄòI was walking along the road‚ÅÝ‚Äîyou know, the road. I had made up my mind I was not coming back this time.‚Äô

‚ÄúI won‚Äôt deny that these words spoken from under the brim of her hat (oh yes, certainly, her head was down‚ÅÝ‚Äîshe had put it down) gave me a thrill; for indeed I had never doubted her sincerity. It could never have been a make-believe despair.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòYes,‚Äô I whispered. ‚ÄòYou were going along the road.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòWhen‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶‚Äô Again she hesitated with an effect of innocent shyness worlds asunder from tragic issues; then glided on‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ ‚ÄòWhen suddenly Captain Anthony came through a gate out of a field.‚Äô

‚ÄúI coughed down the beginning of a most improper fit of laughter, and felt ashamed of myself. Her eyes raised for a moment seemed full of innocent suffering and unexpressed menace in the depths of the dilated pupils within the rings of sombre blue. It was‚ÅÝ‚Äîhow shall I say it?‚ÅÝ‚Äîa night effect when you seem to see vague shapes and don‚Äôt know what reality you may come upon at any time. Then she lowered her eyelids again, shutting all mysteriousness out of the situation except for the sobering memory of that glance, nightlike in the sunshine, expressively still in the brutal unrest of the street.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòSo Captain Anthony joined you‚ÅÝ‚Äîdid he?‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòHe opened a field-gate and walked out on the road. He crossed to my side and went on with me. He had his pipe in his hand. He said: ‚ÄúAre you going far this morning?‚Äù‚Ää‚Äô

‚ÄúThese words (I was watching her white face as she spoke) gave me a slight shudder. She remained demure, almost prim. And I remarked:

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòYou have been talking together before, of course.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòNot more than twenty words altogether since he arrived,‚Äô she declared without emphasis. ‚ÄòThat day he had said ‚ÄúGood morning‚Äù to me when we met at breakfast two hours before. And I said good morning to him. I did not see him afterwards till he came out on the road.‚Äô

‚ÄúI thought to myself that this was not accidental. He had been observing her. I felt certain also that he had not been asking any questions of Mrs.¬ÝFyne.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI wouldn‚Äôt look at him,‚Äô said Flora de Barral. ‚ÄòI had done with looking at people. He said to me: ‚ÄúMy sister does not put herself out much for us. We had better keep each other company. I have read every book there is in that cottage.‚Äù I walked on. He did not leave me. I thought he ought to. But he didn‚Äôt. He didn‚Äôt seem to notice that I would not talk to him.‚Äô

‚ÄúShe was now perfectly still. The wretched little parasol hung down against her dress from her joined hands. I was rigid with attention. It isn‚Äôt every day that one culls such a volunteered tale on a girl‚Äôs lips. The ugly street-noises swelling up for a moment covered the next few words she said. It was vexing. The next word I heard was ‚Äòworried.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòIt worried you to have him there, walking by your side.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòYes. Just that,‚Äô she went on with downcast eyes. There was something prettily comical in her attitude and her tone, while I pictured to myself a poor white-faced girl walking to her death with an unconscious man striding by her side. Unconscious? I don‚Äôt know. First of all, I felt certain that this was no chance meeting. Something had happened before. Was he a man for a coup-de-foudre, the lightning stroke of love? I don‚Äôt think so. That sort of susceptibility is luckily rare. A world of inflammable lovers of the Romeo and Juliet type would very soon end in barbarism and misery. But it is a fact that in every man (not in every woman) there lives a lover; a lover who is called out in all his potentialities often by the most insignificant little things‚ÅÝ‚Äîas long as they come at the psychological moment: the glimpse of a face at an unusual angle, an evanescent attitude, the curve of a cheek often looked at before, perhaps, but then, at the moment, charged with astonishing significance. These are great mysteries, of course. Magic signs.

‚ÄúI don‚Äôt know in what the sign consisted in this case. It might have been her pallor (it wasn‚Äôt pasty nor yet papery) that white face with eyes like blue gleams of fire and lips like red coals. In certain lights, in certain poises of head it suggested tragic sorrow. Or it might have been her wavy hair. Or even just that pointed chin stuck out a little, resentful and not particularly distinguished, doing away with the mysterious aloofness of her fragile presence. But anyway at a given moment Anthony must have suddenly seen the girl. And then, that something had happened to him. Perhaps nothing more than the thought coming into his head that this was ‚Äòa possible woman.‚Äô

‚ÄúFollowed this waylaying! Its resolute character makes me think it was the chin‚Äôs doing; that ‚Äòcommon mortal‚Äô touch which stands in such good stead to some women. Because men, I mean really masculine men, those whose generations have evolved an ideal woman, are often very timid. Who wouldn‚Äôt be before the ideal? It‚Äôs your sentimental trifler, who has just missed being nothing at all, who is enterprising, simply because it is easy to appear enterprising when one does not mean to put one‚Äôs belief to the test.

‚ÄúWell, whatever it was that encouraged him, Captain Anthony stuck to Flora de Barral in a manner which in a timid man might have been called heroic if it had not been so simple. Whether policy, diplomacy, simplicity, or just inspiration, he kept up his talk, rather deliberate, with very few pauses. Then suddenly as if recollecting himself:

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòIt‚Äôs funny. I don‚Äôt think you are annoyed with me for giving you my company unasked. But why don‚Äôt you say something?‚Äô

‚ÄúI asked Miss de Barral what answer she made to this query.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI made no answer,‚Äô she said in that even, unemotional low voice which seemed to be her voice for delicate confidences. ‚ÄòI walked on. He did not seem to mind. We came to the foot of the quarry where the road winds up hill, past the place where you were sitting by the roadside that day. I began to wonder what I should do. After we reached the top Captain Anthony said that he had not been for a walk with a lady for years and years‚ÅÝ‚Äîalmost since he was a boy. We had then come to where I ought to have turned off and struck across a field. I thought of making a run of it. But he would have caught me up. I knew he would; and, of course, he would not have allowed me. I couldn‚Äôt give him the slip.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòWhy didn‚Äôt you ask him to leave you?‚Äô I inquired curiously.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòHe would not have taken any notice,‚Äô she went on steadily. ‚ÄòAnd what could I have done then? I could not have started quarrelling with him‚ÅÝ‚Äîcould I? I hadn‚Äôt enough energy to get angry. I felt very tired suddenly. I just stumbled on straight along the road. Captain Anthony told me that the family‚ÅÝ‚Äîsome relations of his mother‚ÅÝ‚Äîhe used to know in Liverpool was broken up now, and he had never made any friends since. All gone their different ways. All the girls married. Nice girls they were and very friendly to him when he was but little more than a boy. He repeated: ‚ÄòVery nice, cheery, clever girls.‚Äô I sat down on a bank against a hedge and began to cry.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòYou must have astonished him not a little,‚Äô I observed.

‚ÄúAnthony, it seems, remained on the road looking down at her. He did not offer to approach her, neither did he make any other movement or gesture. Flora de Barral told me all this. She could see him through her tears, blurred to a mere shadow on the white road, and then again becoming more distinct, but always absolutely still and as if lost in thought before a strange phenomenon which demanded the closest possible attention.

‚ÄúFlora learned later that he had never seen a woman cry; not in that way, at least. He was impressed and interested by the mysteriousness of the effect. She was very conscious of being looked at, but was not able to stop herself crying. In fact, she was not capable of any effort. Suddenly he advanced two steps, stooped, caught hold of her hands lying on her lap and pulled her up to her feet; she found herself standing close to him almost before she realized what he had done. Some people were coming briskly along the road and Captain Anthony muttered: ‚ÄòYou don‚Äôt want to be stared at. What about that stile over there? Can we go back across the fields?‚Äô

‚ÄúShe snatched her hands out of his grasp (it seems he had omitted to let them go), marched away from him and got over the stile. It was a big field sprinkled profusely with white sheep. A trodden path crossed it diagonally. After she had gone more than halfway she turned her head for the first time. Keeping five feet or so behind, Captain Anthony was following her with an air of extreme interest. Interest or eagerness. At any rate she caught an expression on his face which frightened her. But not enough to make her run. And indeed it would have had to be something incredibly awful to scare into a run a girl who had come to the end of her courage to live.

‚ÄúAs if encouraged by this glance over the shoulder Captain Anthony came up boldly, and now that he was by her side, she felt his nearness intimately, like a touch. She tried to disregard this sensation. But she was not angry with him now. It wasn‚Äôt worth while. She was thankful that he had the sense not to ask questions as to this crying. Of course he didn‚Äôt ask because he didn‚Äôt care. No one in the world cared for her, neither those who pretended nor yet those who did not pretend. She preferred the latter.

‚ÄúCaptain Anthony opened for her a gate into another field; when they got through he kept walking abreast, elbow to elbow almost. His voice growled pleasantly in her very ear. Staying in this dull place was enough to give anyone the blues. His sister scribbled all day. It was positively unkind. He alluded to his nieces as rude, selfish monkeys, without either feelings or manners. And he went on to talk about his ship being laid up for a month and dismantled for repairs. The worst was that on arriving in London he found he couldn‚Äôt get the rooms he was used to, where they made him as comfortable as such a confirmed sea-dog as himself could be anywhere on shore.

‚ÄúIn the effort to subdue by dint of talking and to keep in check the mysterious, the profound attraction he felt already for that delicate being of flesh and blood, with pale cheeks, with darkened eyelids and eyes scalded with hot tears, he went on speaking of himself as a confirmed enemy of life on shore‚ÅÝ‚Äîa perfect terror to a simple man, what with the fads and proprieties and the ceremonies and affectations. He hated all that. He wasn‚Äôt fit for it. There was no rest and peace and security but on the sea.

‚ÄúThis gave one a view of Captain Anthony as a hermit withdrawn from a wicked world. It was amusingly unexpected to me and nothing more. But it must have appealed straight to that bruised and battered young soul. Still shrinking from his nearness she had ended by listening to him with avidity. His deep murmuring voice soothed her. And she thought suddenly that there was peace and rest in the grave too.

‚ÄúShe heard him say: ‚ÄòLook at my sister. She isn‚Äôt a bad woman by any means. She asks me here because it‚Äôs right and proper, I suppose, but she has no use for me. There you have your shore people. I quite understand anybody crying. I would have been gone already, only, truth to say, I haven‚Äôt any friends to go to.‚Äô He added brusquely: ‚ÄòAnd you?‚Äô

‚ÄúShe made a slight negative sign. He must have been observing her, putting two and two together. After a pause he said simply: ‚ÄòWhen I first came here I thought you were governess to these girls. My sister didn‚Äôt say a word about you to me.‚Äô

‚ÄúThen Flora spoke for the first time.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòMrs.¬ÝFyne is my best friend.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòSo she is mine,‚Äô he said without the slightest irony or bitterness, but added with conviction: ‚ÄòThat shows you what life ashore is. Much better be out of it.‚Äô

‚ÄúAs they were approaching the cottage he was heard again as though a long silent walk had not intervened: ‚ÄòBut anyhow I shan‚Äôt ask her anything about you.‚Äô

‚ÄúHe stopped short and she went on alone. His last words had impressed her. Everything he had said seemed somehow to have a special meaning under its obvious conversational sense. Till she went in at the door of the cottage she felt his eyes resting on her.

‚ÄúThat is it. He had made himself felt. That girl was, one may say, washing about with slack limbs in the ugly surf of life with no opportunity to strike out for herself, when suddenly she had been made to feel that there was somebody beside her in the bitter water. A most considerable moral event for her; whether she was aware of it or not. They met again at the one o‚Äôclock dinner. I am inclined to think that, being a healthy girl under her frail appearance, and fast walking and what I may call relief-crying (there are many kinds of crying) making one hungry, she made a good meal. It was Captain Anthony who had no appetite. His sister commented on it in a curt, businesslike manner, and the eldest of his delightful nieces said mockingly: ‚ÄòYou have been taking too much exercise this morning, Uncle Roderick.‚Äô The mild Uncle Roderick turned upon her with a ‚ÄòWhat do you know about it, young lady?‚Äô so charged with suppressed savagery that the whole round table gave one gasp and went dumb for the rest of the meal. He took no notice whatever of Flora de Barral. I don‚Äôt think it was from prudence or any calculated motive. I believe he was so full of her aspects that he did not want to look in her direction when there were other people to hamper his imagination.

‚ÄúYou understand I am piecing here bits of disconnected statements. Next day Flora saw him leaning over the field-gate. When she told me this, I didn‚Äôt of course ask her how it was she was there. Probably she could not have told me how it was she was there. The difficulty here is to keep steadily in view the then conditions of her existence, a combination of dreariness and horror.

‚ÄúThat hermit-like but not exactly misanthropic sailor was leaning over the gate moodily. When he saw the white-faced restless Flora drifting like a lost thing along the road he put his pipe in his pocket and called out ‚ÄòGood morning, Miss Smith‚Äô in a tone of amazing happiness. She, with one foot in life and the other in a nightmare, was at the same time inert and unstable, and very much at the mercy of sudden impulses. She swerved, came distractedly right up to the gate and looking straight into his eyes: ‚ÄòI am not Miss Smith. That‚Äôs not my name. Don‚Äôt call me by it.‚Äô

‚ÄúShe was shaking as if in a passion. His eyes expressed nothing; he only unlatched the gate in silence, grasped her arm and drew her in. Then closing it with a kick‚ÅÝ‚Äî

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòNot your name? That‚Äôs all one to me. Your name‚Äôs the least thing about you I care for.‚Äô He was leading her firmly away from the gate though she resisted slightly. There was a sort of joy in his eyes which frightened her. ‚ÄòYou are not a princess in disguise,‚Äô he said with an unexpected laugh she found bloodcurdling. ‚ÄòAnd that‚Äôs all I care for. You had better understand that I am not blind and not a fool. And then it‚Äôs plain for even a fool to see that things have been going hard with you. You are on a lee shore and eating your heart out with worry.‚Äô

‚ÄúWhat seemed most awful to her was the elated light in his eyes, the rapacious smile that would come and go on his lips as if he were gloating over her misery. But her misery was his opportunity and he rejoiced while the tenderest pity seemed to flood his whole being. He pointed out to her that she knew who he was. He was Mrs.¬ÝFyne‚Äôs brother. And, well, if his sister was the best friend she had in the world, then, by Jove, it was about time somebody came along to look after her a little.

‚ÄúFlora had tried more than once to free herself, but he tightened his grasp of her arm each time and even shook it a little without ceasing to speak. The nearness of his face intimidated her. He seemed striving to look her through. It was obvious the world had been using her ill. And even as he spoke with indignation the very marks and stamp of this ill-usage of which he was so certain seemed to add to the inexplicable attraction he felt for her person. It was not pity alone, I take it. It was something more spontaneous, perverse and exciting. It gave him the feeling that if only he could get hold of her, no woman would belong to him so completely as this woman.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòWhatever your troubles,‚Äô he said, ‚ÄòI am the man to take you away from them; that is, if you are not afraid. You told me you had no friends. Neither have I. Nobody ever cared for me as far as I can remember. Perhaps you could. Yes, I live on the sea. But who would you be parting from? No one. You have no one belonging to you.‚Äô

‚ÄúAt this point she broke away from him and ran. He did not pursue her. The tall hedges tossing in the wind, the wide fields, the clouds driving over the sky and the sky itself wheeled about her in masses of green and white and blue as if the world were breaking up silently in a whirl, and her foot at the next step were bound to find the void. She reached the gate all right, got out, and, once on the road, discovered that she had not the courage to look back. The rest of that day she spent with the Fyne girls who gave her to understand that she was a slow and unprofitable person. Long after tea, nearly at dusk, Captain Anthony (the son of the poet) appeared suddenly before her in the little garden in front of the cottage. They were alone for the moment. The wind had dropped. In the calm evening air the voices of Mrs.¬ÝFyne and the girls strolling aimlessly on the road could be heard. He said to her severely:

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòYou have understood?‚Äô

‚ÄúShe looked at him in silence.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòThat I love you,‚Äô he finished.

‚ÄúShe shook her head the least bit.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòDon‚Äôt you believe me?‚Äô he asked in a low, infuriated voice.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòNobody would love me,‚Äô she answered in a very quiet tone. ‚ÄòNobody could.‚Äô

‚ÄúHe was dumb for a time, astonished beyond measure, as he well might have been. He doubted his ears. He was outraged.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòEh? What? Can‚Äôt love you? What do you know about it? It‚Äôs my affair, isn‚Äôt it? You dare say that to a man who has just told you! You must be mad!‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòVery nearly,‚Äô she said with the accent of pent-up sincerity, and even relieved because she was able to say something which she felt was true. For the last few days she had felt herself several times near that madness which is but an intolerable lucidity of apprehension.

‚ÄúThe clear voices of Mrs.¬ÝFyne and the girls were coming nearer, sounding affected in the peace of the passion-laden earth. He began storming at her hastily.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòNonsense! Nobody can‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ Indeed! Pah! You‚Äôll have to be shown that somebody can. I can. Nobody‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶‚Äô He made a contemptuous hissing noise. ‚ÄòMore likely you can‚Äôt. They have done something to you. Something‚Äôs crushed your pluck. You can‚Äôt face a man‚ÅÝ‚Äîthat‚Äôs what it is. What made you like this? Where do you come from? You have been put upon. The scoundrels‚ÅÝ‚Äîwhoever they are, men or women, seem to have robbed you of your very name. You say you are not Miss Smith. Who are you, then?‚Äô

‚ÄúShe did not answer. He muttered, ‚ÄòNot that I care,‚Äô and fell silent, because the fatuous self-confident chatter of the Fyne girls could be heard at the very gate. But they were not going to bed yet. They passed on. He waited a little in silence and immobility, then stamped his foot and lost control of himself. He growled at her in a savage passion. She felt certain that he was threatening her and calling her names. She was no stranger to abuse, as we know, but there seemed to be a particular kind of ferocity in this which was new to her. She began to tremble. The especially terrifying thing was that she could not make out the nature of these awful menaces and names. Not a word. Yet it was not the shrinking anguish of her other experiences of angry scenes. She made a mighty effort, though her knees were knocking together, and in an expiring voice demanded that he should let her go indoors. ‚ÄòDon‚Äôt stop me. It‚Äôs no use. It‚Äôs no use,‚Äô she repeated faintly, feeling an invincible obstinacy rising within her, yet without anger against that raging man.

‚ÄúHe became articulate suddenly, and, without raising his voice, perfectly audible.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòNo use! No use! You dare stand here and tell me that‚ÅÝ‚Äîyou white-faced wisp, you wreath of mist, you little ghost of all the sorrow in the world. You dare! Haven‚Äôt I been looking at you? You are all eyes. What makes your cheeks always so white as if you had seen something‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ Don‚Äôt speak. I love it‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ No use! And you really think that I can now go to sea for a year or more, to the other side of the world somewhere, leaving you behind. Why! You would vanish‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ what little there is of you. Some rough wind will blow you away altogether. You have no holding ground on earth. Well, then trust yourself to me‚ÅÝ‚Äîto the sea‚ÅÝ‚Äîwhich is deep like your eyes.‚Äô

‚ÄúShe said: ‚ÄòImpossible.‚Äô He kept quiet for a while, then asked in a totally changed tone, a tone of gloomy curiosity:

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòYou can‚Äôt stand me then? Is that it?‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòNo,‚Äô she said, more steady herself. ‚ÄòI am not thinking of you at all.‚Äô

‚ÄúThe inane voices of the Fyne girls were heard over the sombre fields calling to each other, thin and clear. He muttered: ‚ÄòYou could try to. Unless you are thinking of somebody else.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòYes. I am thinking of somebody else, of someone who has nobody to think of him but me.‚Äô

‚ÄúHis shadowy form stepped out of her way, and suddenly leaned sideways against the wooden support of the porch. And as she stood still, surprised by this staggering movement, his voice spoke up in a tone quite strange to her.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòGo in then. Go out of my sight‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI thought you said nobody could love you.‚Äô

‚ÄúShe was passing him when suddenly he struck her as so forlorn that she was inspired to say: ‚ÄòNo one has ever loved me‚ÅÝ‚Äînot in that way‚ÅÝ‚Äîif that‚Äôs what you mean. Nobody would.‚Äô

‚ÄúHe detached himself brusquely from the post, and she did not shrink; but Mrs.¬ÝFyne and the girls were already at the gate.

‚ÄúAll he understood was that everything was not over yet. There was no time to lose; Mrs.¬ÝFyne and the girls had come in at the gate. He whispered ‚ÄòWait‚Äô with such authority (he was the son of Carleon Anthony, the domestic autocrat) that it did arrest her for a moment, long enough to hear him say that he could not be left like this to puzzle over her nonsense all night. She was to slip down again into the garden later on, as soon as she could do so without being heard. He would be there waiting for her till‚ÅÝ‚Äîtill daylight. She didn‚Äôt think he could go to sleep, did she? And she had better come, or‚ÅÝ‚Äîhe broke off on an unfinished threat.

‚ÄúShe vanished into the unlighted cottage just as Mrs.¬ÝFyne came up to the porch. Nervous, holding her breath in the darkness of the living-room, she heard her best friend say: ‚ÄòYou ought to have joined us, Roderick.‚Äô And then: ‚ÄòHave you seen Miss Smith anywhere?‚Äô

‚ÄúFlora shuddered, expecting Anthony to break out into betraying imprecations on Miss Smith‚Äôs head, and cause a painful and humiliating explanation. She imagined him full of his mysterious ferocity. To her great surprise, Anthony‚Äôs voice sounded very much as usual, with perhaps a slight tinge of grimness. ‚ÄòMiss Smith! No. I‚Äôve seen no Miss Smith.‚Äô

‚ÄúMrs.¬ÝFyne seemed satisfied‚ÅÝ‚Äîand not much concerned really.

‚ÄúFlora, relieved, got clear away to her room upstairs, and shutting her door quietly, dropped into a chair. She was used to reproaches, abuse, to all sorts of wicked ill usage‚ÅÝ‚Äîshort of actual beating on her body. Otherwise inexplicable angers had cut and slashed and trampled down her youth without mercy‚ÅÝ‚Äîand mainly, it appeared, because she was the financier de Barral‚Äôs daughter and also condemned to a degrading sort of poverty through the action of treacherous men who had turned upon her father in his hour of need. And she thought with the tenderest possible affection of that upright figure buttoned up in a long frock-coat, soft-voiced and having but little to say to his girl. She seemed to feel his hand closed round hers. On his flying visits to Brighton he would always walk hand in hand with her. People stared covertly at them; the band was playing; and there was the sea‚ÅÝ‚Äîthe blue gaiety of the sea. They were quietly happy together‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ It was all over!

‚ÄúAn immense anguish of the present wrung her heart, and she nearly cried aloud. That dread of what was before her which had been eating up her courage slowly in the course of odious years, flamed up into an access of panic, that sort of headlong panic which had already driven her out twice to the top of the cliff-like quarry. She jumped up saying to herself: ‚ÄòWhy not now? At once! Yes. I‚Äôll do it now‚ÅÝ‚Äîin the dark!‚Äô The very horror of it seemed to give her additional resolution.

‚ÄúShe came down the staircase quietly, and only on the point of opening the door and because of the discovery that it was unfastened, she remembered Captain Anthony‚Äôs threat to stay in the garden all night. She hesitated. She did not understand the mood of that man clearly. He was violent. But she had gone beyond the point where things matter. What would he think of her coming down to him‚ÅÝ‚Äîas he would naturally suppose. And even that didn‚Äôt matter. He could not despise her more than she despised herself. She must have been lightheaded because the thought came into her mind that should he get into ungovernable fury from disappointment, and perchance strangle her, it would be as good a way to be done with it as any.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòYou had that thought,‚Äô I exclaimed in wonder.

‚ÄúWith downcast eyes and speaking with an almost painstaking precision (her very lips, her red lips, seemed to move just enough to be heard and no more), she said that, yes, the thought came into her head. This makes one shudder at the mysterious ways girls acquire knowledge. For this was a thought, wild enough, I admit, but which could only have come from the depths of that sort of experience which she had not had, and went far beyond a young girl‚Äôs possible conception of the strongest and most veiled of human emotions.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòHe was there, of course?‚Äô I said.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòYes, he was there.‚Äô She saw him on the path directly she stepped outside the porch. He was very still. It was as though he had been standing there with his face to the door for hours.

‚ÄúShaken up by the changing moods of passion and tenderness, he must have been ready for any extravagance of conduct. Knowing the profound silence each night brought to that nook of the country, I could imagine them having the feeling of being the only two people on the wide earth. A row of six or seven lofty elms just across the road opposite the cottage made the night more obscure in that little garden. If these two could just make out each other that was all.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòWell! And were you very much terrified?‚Äô I asked.

‚ÄúShe made me wait a little before she said, raising her eyes: ‚ÄòHe was gentleness itself.‚Äô

‚ÄúI noticed three abominable, drink-sodden loafers, sallow and dirty, who had come to range themselves in a row within ten feet of us against the front of the public-house. They stared at Flora de Barral‚Äôs back with unseeing, mournful fixity.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòLet‚Äôs move this way a little,‚Äô I proposed.

‚ÄúShe turned at once and we made a few paces; not too far to take us out of sight of the hotel door, but very nearly. I could just keep my eyes on it. After all, I had not been so very long with the girl. If you were to disentangle the words we actually exchanged from my comments you would see that they were not so very many, including everything she had so unexpectedly told me of her story. No, not so very many. And now it seemed as though there would be no more. No! I could expect no more. The confidence was wonderful enough in its nature as far as it went, and perhaps not to have been expected from any other girl under the sun. And I felt a little ashamed. The origin of our intimacy was too gruesome. It was as if listening to her I had taken advantage of having seen her poor bewildered, scared soul without its veils. But I was curious, too; or, to render myself justice without false modesty‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI was anxious; anxious to know a little more.

‚ÄúI felt like a blackmailer all the same when I made my attempt with a lighthearted remark.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòAnd so you gave up that walk you proposed to take?‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòYes, I gave up the walk,‚Äô she said slowly before raising her downcast eyes. When she did so it was with an extraordinary effect. It was like catching sight of a piece of blue sky, of a stretch of open water. And for a moment I understood the desire of that man to whom the sea and sky of his solitary life had appeared suddenly incomplete without that glance which seemed to belong to them both. He was not for nothing the son of a poet. I looked into those unabashed eyes while the girl went on, her demure appearance and precise tone changed to a very earnest expression. Woman is various indeed.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòBut I want you to understand, Mr.‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶‚Äô she had actually to think of my name‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ ‚ÄòMr.¬ÝMarlow, that I have written to Mrs.¬ÝFyne that I haven‚Äôt been‚ÅÝ‚Äîthat I have done nothing to make Captain Anthony behave to me as he had behaved. I haven‚Äôt. I haven‚Äôt. It isn‚Äôt my doing. It isn‚Äôt my fault‚ÅÝ‚Äîif she likes to put it in that way. But she, with her ideas, ought to understand that I couldn‚Äôt, that I couldn‚Äôt‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ I know she hates me now. I think she never liked me. I think nobody ever cared for me. I was told once nobody could care for me; and I think it is true. At any rate I can‚Äôt forget it.‚Äô

‚ÄúHer abominable experience with the governess had implanted in her unlucky breast a lasting doubt, an ineradicable suspicion of herself and of others. I said:

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòRemember, Miss de Barral, that to be fair you must trust a man altogether‚ÅÝ‚Äîor not at all.‚Äô

‚ÄúShe dropped her eyes suddenly. I thought I heard a faint sigh. I tried to take a light tone again, and yet it seemed impossible to get off the ground which gave me my standing with her.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòMrs.¬ÝFyne is absurd. She‚Äôs an excellent woman, but really you could not be expected to throw away your chance of life simply that she might cherish a good opinion of your memory. That would be excessive.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòIt was not of my life that I was thinking while Captain Anthony was‚ÅÝ‚Äîwas speaking to me,‚Äô said Flora de Barral with an effort.

‚ÄúI told her that she was wrong then. She ought to have been thinking of her life, and not only of her life but of the life of the man who was speaking to her too. She let me finish, then shook her head impatiently.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI mean‚ÅÝ‚Äîdeath.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòWell,‚Äô I said, ‚Äòwhen he stood before you there, outside the cottage, he really stood between you and that. I have it out of your own mouth. You can‚Äôt deny it.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòIf you will have it that he saved my life, then he has got it. It was not for me. Oh no! It was not for me that I‚ÅÝ‚ÄîIt was not fear! There!‚Äô She finished petulantly: ‚ÄòAnd you may just as well know it.‚Äô

‚ÄúShe hung her head and swung the parasol slightly to and fro. I thought a little.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòDo you know French, Miss de Barral?‚Äô I asked.

‚ÄúShe made a sign with her head that she did, but without showing any surprise at the question and without ceasing to swing her parasol.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòWell then, somehow or other I have the notion that Captain Anthony is what the French call un galant homme. I should like to think he is being treated as he deserves.‚Äô

‚ÄúThe form of her lips (I could see them under the brim of her hat) was suddenly altered into a line of seriousness. The parasol stopped swinging.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI have given him what he wanted‚ÅÝ‚Äîthat‚Äôs myself,‚Äô she said without a tremor and with a striking dignity of tone.

‚ÄúImpressed by the manner and the directness of the words, I hesitated for a moment what to say. Then made up my mind to clear up the point.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòAnd you have got what you wanted? Is that it?‚Äô

‚ÄúThe daughter of the egregious financier de Barral did not answer at once this question going to the heart of things. Then raising her head and gazing wistfully across the street noisy with the endless transit of innumerable bargains, she said with intense gravity:

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòHe has been most generous.‚Äô

‚ÄúI was pleased to hear these words. Not that I doubted the infatuation of Roderick Anthony, but I was pleased to hear something which proved that she was sensible and open to the sentiment of gratitude which in this case was significant. In the face of man‚Äôs desire a girl is excusable if she thinks herself priceless. I mean a girl of our civilization which has established a dithyrambic phraseology for the expression of love. A man in love will accept any convention exalting the object of his passion and in this indirect way his passion itself. In what way the captain of the ship Ferndale gave proofs of lover-like lavishness I could not guess very well. But I was glad she was appreciative. It is lucky that small things please women. And it is not silly of them to be thus pleased. It is in small things that the deepest loyalty, that which they need most, the loyalty of the passing moment, is best expressed.

‚ÄúShe had remained thoughtful, letting her deep motionless eyes rest on the streaming jumble of traffic. Suddenly she said:

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòAnd I wanted to ask you‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ I was really glad when I saw you actually here. Who would have expected you here, at this spot, before this hotel! I certainly never‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ You see it meant a lot to me. You are the only person who knows‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ who knows for certain‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòKnows what?‚Äô I said, not discovering at first what she had in her mind. Then I saw it. ‚ÄòWhy can‚Äôt you leave that alone?‚Äô I remonstrated, rather annoyed at the invidious position she was forcing on me in a sense. ‚ÄòIt‚Äôs true that I was the only person to see,‚Äô I added. ‚ÄòBut, as it happens, after your mysterious disappearance I told the Fynes the story of our meeting.‚Äô

‚ÄúHer eyes raised to mine had an expression of dreamy, unfathomable candour, if I dare say so. And if you wonder what I mean I can only say that I have seen the sea wear such an expression on one or two occasions shortly before sunrise on a calm, fresh day. She said as if meditating aloud that she supposed the Fynes were not likely to talk about that. She couldn‚Äôt imagine any connection in which‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ Why should they?

‚ÄúAs her tone had become interrogatory I assented. ‚ÄòTo be sure. There‚Äôs no reason whatever‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äô thinking to myself that they would be more likely indeed to keep quiet about it. They had other things to talk of. And then remembering little Fyne stuck upstairs for an unconscionable time, enough to blurt out everything he ever knew in his life, I reflected that he would assume naturally that Captain Anthony had nothing to learn from him about Flora de Barral. It had been up to now my assumption too. I saw my mistake. The sincerest of women will make no unnecessary confidences to a man. And this is as it should be.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòNo‚ÅÝ‚Äîno!‚Äô I said reassuringly. ‚ÄòIt‚Äôs most unlikely. Are you much concerned?‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòWell, you see, when I came down,‚Äô she said again in that precise demure tone, ‚Äòwhen I came down‚ÅÝ‚Äîinto the garden Captain Anthony misunderstood‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòOf course he would. Men are so conceited,‚Äô I said.

‚ÄúI saw it well enough that he must have thought she had come down to him. What else could he have thought? And then he had been ‚Äògentleness itself.‚Äô A new experience for that poor, delicate, and yet so resisting creature. Gentleness in passion! What could have been more seductive to the scared, starved heart of that girl? Perhaps had he been violent, she might have told him that what she came down to keep was the tryst of death‚ÅÝ‚Äînot of love. It occurred to me as I looked at her, young, fragile in aspect, and intensely alive in her quietness, that perhaps she did not know herself then what sort of tryst she was coming down to keep.

‚ÄúShe smiled faintly, almost awkwardly as if she were totally unused to smiling, at my cheap jocularity. Then she said with that forced precision, a sort of conscious primness:

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI didn‚Äôt want him to know.‚Äô

‚ÄúI approved heartily. Quite right. Much better. Let him ever remain under his misapprehension which was so much more flattering for him.

‚ÄúI tried to keep it in the tone of comedy; but she was, I believe, too simple to understand my intention. She went on, looking down.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòOh! You think so? When I saw you I didn‚Äôt know why you were here. I was glad when you spoke to me because this is exactly what I wanted to ask you for. I wanted to ask you if you ever meet Captain Anthony‚ÅÝ‚Äîby any chance‚ÅÝ‚Äîanywhere‚ÅÝ‚Äîyou are a sailor too, are you not?‚ÅÝ‚Äîthat you would never mention‚ÅÝ‚Äînever‚ÅÝ‚Äîthat‚ÅÝ‚Äîthat you had seen me over there.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòMy dear young lady,‚Äô I cried, horror-struck at the supposition. ‚ÄòWhy should I? What makes you think I should dream of‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶‚Äô

‚ÄúShe had raised her head at my vehemence. She did not understand it. The world had treated her so dishonourably that she had no notion even of what mere decency of feeling is like. It was not her fault. Indeed, I don‚Äôt know why she should have put her trust in anybody‚Äôs promises.

‚ÄúBut I thought it would be better to promise. So I assured her that she could depend on my absolute silence.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI am not likely to ever set eyes on Captain Anthony,‚Äô I added with conviction‚ÅÝ‚Äîas a further guarantee.

‚ÄúShe accepted my assurance in silence, without a sign. Her gravity had in it something acute, perhaps because of that chin. While we were still looking at each other she declared:

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòThere‚Äôs no deception in it really. I want you to believe that if I am here, like this, today, it is not from fear. It is not!‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI quite understand,‚Äô I said. But her firm yet self-conscious gaze became doubtful. ‚ÄòI do,‚Äô I insisted. ‚ÄòI understand perfectly that it was not of death that you were afraid.‚Äô

‚ÄúShe lowered her eyes slowly, and I went on:

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòAs to life, that‚Äôs another thing. And I don‚Äôt know that one ought to blame you very much‚ÅÝ‚Äîthough it seemed rather an excessive step. I wonder now if it isn‚Äôt the ugliness rather than the pain of the struggle which‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶‚Äô

‚ÄúShe shuddered visibly: ‚ÄòBut I do blame myself,‚Äô she exclaimed with feeling. ‚ÄòI am ashamed.‚Äô And, dropping her head, she looked in a moment the very picture of remorse and shame.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòWell, you will be going away from all its horrors,‚Äô I said. ‚ÄòAnd surely you are not afraid of the sea. You are a sailor‚Äôs granddaughter, I understand.‚Äô

‚ÄúShe sighed deeply. She remembered her grandfather only a little. He was a clean-shaven man with a ruddy complexion and long, perfectly white hair. He used to take her on his knee, and putting his face near hers, talk to her in loving whispers. If only he were alive now‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶‚Ää!

‚ÄúShe remained silent for a while.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòAren‚Äôt you anxious to see the ship?‚Äô I asked.

‚ÄúShe lowered her head still more so that I could not see anything of her face.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI don‚Äôt know,‚Äô she murmured.

‚ÄúI had already the suspicion that she did not know her own feelings. All this work of the merest chance had been so unexpected, so sudden. And she had nothing to fall back upon, no experience but such as to shake her belief in every human being. She was dreadfully and pitifully forlorn. It was almost in order to comfort my own depression that I remarked cheerfully:

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòWell, I know of somebody who must be growing extremely anxious to see you.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI am before my time,‚Äô she confessed simply, rousing herself. ‚ÄòI had nothing to do. So I came out.‚Äô

‚ÄúI had the sudden vision of a shabby, lonely little room at the other end of the town. It had grown intolerable to her restlessness. The mere thought of it oppressed her. Flora de Barral was looking frankly at her chance confidant.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòAnd I came this way,‚Äô she went on. ‚ÄòI appointed the time myself yesterday, but Captain Anthony would not have minded. He told me he was going to look over some business papers till I came.‚Äô

‚ÄúThe idea of the son of the poet, the rescuer of the most forlorn damsel of modern times, the man of violence, gentleness and generosity, sitting up to his neck in ship‚Äôs accounts amused me. ‚ÄòI am sure he would not have minded,‚Äô I said, smiling. But the girl‚Äôs stare was sombre, her thin white face seemed pathetically careworn.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI can hardly believe yet,‚Äô she murmured anxiously.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòIt‚Äôs quite real. Never fear,‚Äô I said encouragingly, but had to change my tone at once. ‚ÄòYou had better go down that way a little,‚Äô I directed her abruptly.

‚ÄúI had seen Fyne come striding out of the hotel door. The intelligent girl, without staying to ask questions, walked away from me quietly down one street while I hurried on to meet Fyne coming up the other at his efficient pedestrian gait. My object was to stop him getting as far as the corner. He must have been thinking too hard to be aware of his surroundings. I put myself in his way, and he nearly walked into me.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòHallo!‚Äô I said.

‚ÄúHis surprise was extreme. ‚ÄòYou here! You don‚Äôt mean to say you have been waiting for me?‚Äô

‚ÄúI said negligently that I had been detained by unexpected business in the neighbourhood, and thus happened to catch sight of him coming out.

‚ÄúHe stared at me with solemn distraction, obviously thinking of something else. I suggested that he had better take the next city-ward tramcar. He was inattentive, and I perceived that he was profoundly perturbed. As Miss de Barral (she had moved out of sight) could not possibly approach the hotel door as long as we remained where we were I proposed that we should wait for the car on the other side of the street. He obeyed rather the slight touch on his arm than my words, and while we were crossing the wide roadway in the midst of the lumbering wheeled traffic, he exclaimed in his deep tone, ‚ÄòI don‚Äôt know which of these two is more mad than the other!‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòReally!‚Äô I said, pulling him forward from under the noses of two enormous sleepy-headed carthorses. He skipped wildly out of the way and up on the curbstone with a purely instinctive precision; his mind had nothing to do with his movements. In the middle of his leap, and while in the act of sailing gravely through the air, he continued to relieve his outraged feelings.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòYou would never believe! They are mad!‚Äô

‚ÄúI took care to place myself in such a position that to face me he had to turn his back on the hotel across the road. I believe he was glad I was there to talk to. But I thought there was some misapprehension in the first statement he shot out at me without loss of time, that Captain Anthony had been glad to see him. It was indeed difficult to believe that, directly he opened the door, his wife‚Äôs ‚Äòsailor-brother‚Äô had positively shouted: ‚ÄòOh, it‚Äôs you! The very man I wanted to see.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI found him sitting there,‚Äô went on Fyne impressively in his effortless, grave chest voice, ‚Äòdrafting his will.‚Äô

‚ÄúThis was unexpected, but I preserved a noncommittal attitude, knowing full well that our actions in themselves are neither mad nor sane. But I did not see what there was to be excited about. And Fyne was distinctly excited. I understood it better when I learned that the captain of the Ferndale wanted little Fyne to be one of the trustees. He was leaving everything to his wife. Naturally, a request which involved him into sanctioning in a way a proceeding which he had been sent by his wife to oppose, must have appeared sufficiently mad to Fyne.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòMe! Me, of all people in the world!‚Äô he repeated portentously. But I could see that he was frightened. Such want of tact!

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòHe knew I came from his sister. You don‚Äôt put a man into such an awkward position,‚Äô complained Fyne. ‚ÄòIt made me speak much more strongly against all this very painful business than I would have had the heart to do otherwise.‚Äô

‚ÄúI pointed out to him concisely, and keeping my eyes on the door of the hotel, that he and his wife were the only bond with the land Captain Anthony had. Who else could he have asked?

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI explained to him that he was breaking this bond,‚Äô declared Fyne solemnly. ‚ÄòBreaking it once for all. And for what‚ÅÝ‚Äîfor what?‚Äô

‚ÄúHe glared at me. I could perhaps have given him an inkling for what, but I said nothing. He started again:

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòMy wife assures me that the girl does not love him a bit. She goes by that letter she received from her. There is a passage in it where she practically admits that she was quite unscrupulous in accepting this offer of marriage, but says to my wife that she supposes she, my wife, will not blame her‚ÅÝ‚Äîas it was in self-defence. My wife has her own ideas, but this is an outrageous misapprehension of her views. Outrageous.‚Äô

‚ÄúThe good little man paused and then added weightily:

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI didn‚Äôt tell that to my brother-in-law‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI mean, my wife‚Äôs views.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòNo,‚Äô I said. ‚ÄòWhat would have been the good?‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòIt‚Äôs positive infatuation,‚Äô agreed little Fyne, in the tone as though he had made an awful discovery. ‚ÄòI have never seen anything so hopeless and inexplicable in my life. I‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI felt quite frightened and sorry,‚Äô he added, while I looked at him curiously asking myself whether this excellent civil servant and notable pedestrian had felt the breath of a great and fatal love-spell passing him by in the room of that East-End hotel. He did look for a moment as though he had seen a ghost, an otherworld thing. But that look vanished instantaneously, and he nodded at me with mere exasperation at something quite of this world‚ÅÝ‚Äîwhatever it was. ‚ÄòIt‚Äôs a bad business. My brother-in-law knows nothing of women,‚Äô he cried with an air of profound, experienced wisdom.

‚ÄúWhat he imagined he knew of women himself I can‚Äôt tell. I did not know anything of the opportunities he might have had. But this is a subject which, if approached with undue solemnity, is apt to elude one‚Äôs grasp entirely. No doubt Fyne knew something of a woman who was Captain Anthony‚Äôs sister. But that, admittedly, had been a very solemn study. I smiled at him gently, and as if encouraged or provoked, he completed his thought rather explosively.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòAnd that girl understands nothing‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ It‚Äôs sheer lunacy.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI don‚Äôt know,‚Äô I said, ‚Äòwhether the circumstances of isolation at sea would be any alleviation to the danger. But it‚Äôs certain that they shall have the opportunity to learn everything about each other in a lonely t√™te-√Ý-t√™te.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòBut dash it all,‚Äô he cried in hollow accents which at the same time had the tone of bitter irony‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI had never before heard a sound so quaintly ugly and almost horrible‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚ÄòYou forget Mr.¬ÝSmith.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòWhat Mr.¬ÝSmith?‚Äô I asked innocently.

‚ÄúFyne made an extraordinary simiesque grimace. I believe it was quite involuntary, but you know that a grave, much-lined, shaven countenance when distorted in an unusual way is extremely apelike. It was a surprising sight, and rendered me not only speechless but stopped the progress of my thought completely. I must have presented a remarkably imbecile appearance.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòMy brother-in-law considered it amusing to chaff me about us introducing the girl as Miss Smith,‚Äô said Fyne, going surly in a moment. ‚ÄòHe said that perhaps if he had heard her real name from the first it might have restrained him. As it was, he made the discovery too late. Asked me to tell Zoe this together with a lot more nonsense.‚Äô

‚ÄúFyne gave me the impression of having escaped from a man inspired by a grimly playful ebullition of high spirits. It must have been most distasteful to him; and his solemnity got damaged somehow in the process, I perceived. There were holes in it through which I could see a new, an unknown Fyne.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòYou wouldn‚Äôt believe it,‚Äô he went on, ‚Äòbut she looks upon her father exclusively as a victim. I don‚Äôt know,‚Äô he burst out suddenly through an enormous rent in his solemnity, ‚Äòif she thinks him absolutely a saint, but she certainly imagines him to be a martyr.‚Äô

‚ÄúIt is one of the advantages of that magnificent invention, the prison, that you may forget people which are put there as though they were dead. One needn‚Äôt worry about them. Nothing can happen to them that you can help. They can do nothing which might possibly matter to anybody. They come out of it, though, but that seems hardly an advantage to themselves or anyone else. I had completely forgotten the financier de Barral. The girl for me was an orphan, but now I perceived suddenly the force of Fyne‚Äôs qualifying statement, ‚Äòto a certain extent.‚Äô It would have been infinitely more kind all round for the law to have shot, beheaded, strangled, or otherwise destroyed this absurd de Barral, who was a danger to a moral world inhabited by a credulous multitude not fit to take care of itself. But I observed to Fyne that, however insane was the view she held, one could not declare the girl mad on that account.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòSo she thinks of her father‚ÅÝ‚Äîdoes she? I suppose she would appear to us saner if she thought only of herself.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI am positive,‚Äô Fyne said earnestly, ‚Äòthat she went and made desperate eyes at Anthony‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòOh come!‚Äô I interrupted. ‚ÄòYou haven‚Äôt seen her make eyes. You don‚Äôt know the colour of her eyes.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòVery well! It don‚Äôt matter. But it could hardly have come to that if she hadn‚Äôt‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ It‚Äôs all one, though. I tell you she has led him on, or accepted him, if you like, simply because she was thinking of her father. She doesn‚Äôt care a bit about Anthony, I believe. She cares for no one. Never cared for anyone. Ask Zoe. For myself I don‚Äôt blame her,‚Äô added Fyne, giving me another view of unsuspected things through the rags and tatters of his damaged solemnity. ‚ÄòNo! by heavens, I don‚Äôt blame her‚ÅÝ‚Äîthe poor devil.‚Äô

‚ÄúI agreed with him silently. I suppose affections are, in a sense, to be learned. If there exists a native spark of love in all of us, it must be fanned while we are young. Hers, if she ever had it, had been drenched in as ugly a lot of corrosive liquid as could be imagined. But I was surprised at Fyne obscurely feeling this.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòShe loves no one except that preposterous advertising shark,‚Äô he pursued venomously, but in a more deliberate manner. ‚ÄòAnd Anthony knows it.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòDoes he?‚Äô I said doubtfully.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòShe‚Äôs quite capable of having told him herself,‚Äô affirmed Fyne, with amazing insight. ‚ÄòBut whether or no, I‚Äôve told him.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòYou did? From Mrs.¬ÝFyne, of course.‚Äô

‚ÄúFyne only blinked owlishly at this piece of my insight.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòAnd how did Captain Anthony receive this interesting information?‚Äô I asked further.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòMost improperly,‚Äô said Fyne, who really was in a state in which he didn‚Äôt mind what he blurted out. ‚ÄòHe isn‚Äôt himself. He begged me to tell his sister that he offered no remarks on her conduct. Very improper and inconsequent. He said‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ I was tired of this wrangling. I told him I made allowances for the state of excitement he was in.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòYou know, Fyne,‚Äô I said, ‚Äòa man in jail seems to me such an incredible, cruel, nightmarish sort of thing that I can hardly believe in his existence. Certainly not in relation to any other existences.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòBut dash it all,‚Äô cried Fyne, ‚Äòhe isn‚Äôt shut up for life. They are going to let him out. He‚Äôs coming out! That‚Äôs the whole trouble. What is he coming out to, I want to know? It seems a more cruel business than the shutting him up was. This has been the worry for weeks. Do you see now?‚Äô

‚ÄúI saw, all sorts of things! Immediately before me I saw the excitement of little Fyne‚ÅÝ‚Äîmere food for wonder. Further off, in a sort of gloom and beyond the light of day and the movement of the street, I saw the figure of a man, stiff like a ramrod, moving with small steps, a slight girlish figure by his side. And the gloom was like the gloom of villainous slums, of misery, of wretchedness, of a starved and degraded existence. It was a relief that I could see only their shabby hopeless backs. He was an awful ghost. But indeed to call him a ghost was only a refinement of polite speech, and a manner of concealing one‚Äôs terror of such things. Prisons are wonderful contrivances. Shut‚ÅÝ‚Äîopen. Very neat. Shut‚ÅÝ‚Äîopen. And out comes some sort of corpse, to wander awfully in a world in which it has no possible connections and carrying with it the appalling tainted atmosphere of its silent abode. Marvellous arrangement. It works automatically, and, when you look at it, the perfection makes you sick; which for a mere mechanism is no mean triumph. Sick and scared. It had nearly scared that poor girl to her death. Fancy having to take such a thing by the hand! Now I understood the remorseful strain I had detected in her speeches.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòBy Jove!‚Äô I said. ‚ÄòThey are about to let him out! I never thought of that.‚Äô

‚ÄúFyne was contemptuous either of me or of things at large.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòYou didn‚Äôt suppose he was to be kept in jail for life?‚Äô

‚ÄúAt that moment I caught sight of Flora de Barral at the junction of the two streets. Then some vehicles following each other in quick succession hid from my sight the black slight figure with just a touch of colour in her hat. She was walking slowly; and it might have been caution or reluctance. While listening to Fyne I stared hard past his shoulder trying to catch sight of her again. He was going on with positive heat, the rags of his solemnity dropping off him at every second sentence.

‚ÄúThat was just it. His wife and he had been perfectly aware of it. Of course the girl never talked of her father with Mrs.¬ÝFyne. I suppose with her theory of innocence she found it difficult. But she must have been thinking of it day and night. What to do with him? Where to go? How to keep body and soul together? He had never made any friends. The only relations were the atrocious East-End cousins. We know what they were. Nothing but wretchedness, whichever way she turned in an unjust and prejudiced world. And to look at him helplessly she felt would be too much for her.

‚ÄúI won‚Äôt say I was thinking these thoughts. It was not necessary. This complete knowledge was in my head while I stared hard across the wide road, so hard that I failed to hear little Fyne till he raised his deep voice indignantly.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI don‚Äôt blame the girl,‚Äô he was saying. ‚ÄòHe is infatuated with her. Anybody can see that. Why she should have got such a hold on him I can‚Äôt understand. She said ‚ÄòYes‚Äô to him only for the sake of that fatuous, swindling father of hers. It‚Äôs perfectly plain if one thinks it over a moment. One needn‚Äôt even think of it. We have it under her own hand. In that letter to my wife she says she has acted unscrupulously. She has owned up, then, for what else can it mean, I should like to know. And so they are to be married before that old idiot comes out‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ He will be surprised,‚Äô commented Fyne suddenly in a strangely malignant tone. ‚ÄòHe shall be met at the jail door by a Mrs.¬ÝAnthony, a Mrs.¬ÝCaptain Anthony. Very pleasant for Zoe. And for all I know, my brother-in-law means to turn up dutifully too. A little family event. It‚Äôs extremely pleasant to think of. Delightful. A charming family party. We three against the world‚ÅÝ‚Äîand all that sort of thing. And what for. For a girl that doesn‚Äôt care twopence for him.‚Äô

‚ÄúThe demon of bitterness had entered into little Fyne. He amazed me as though he had changed his skin from white to black. It was quite as wonderful. And he kept it up, too.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòLuckily there are some advantages in the‚ÅÝ‚Äîthe profession of a sailor. As long as they defy the world away at sea somewhere eighteen thousand miles from here, I don‚Äôt mind so much. I wonder what that interesting old party will say. He will have another surprise. They mean to drag him along with them on board the ship straight away. Rescue work. Just think of Roderick Anthony, the son of a gentleman, after all‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶‚Äô

‚ÄúHe gave me a little shock. I thought he was going to say the ‚Äòson of the poet‚Äô as usual; but his mind was not running on such vanities now. His unspoken thought must have gone on ‚Äòand uncle of my girls.‚Äô I suspect that he had been roughly handled by Captain Anthony up there, and the resentment gave a tremendous fillip to the slow play of his wits. Those men of sober fancy, when anything rouses their imaginative faculty, are very thorough. ‚ÄòJust think!‚Äô he cried. ‚ÄòThe three of them crowded into a four-wheeler, and Anthony sitting deferentially opposite that astonished old jailbird!‚Äô

‚ÄúThe good little man laughed. An improper sound it was to come from his manly chest; and what made it worse was the thought that for the least thing, by a mere hair‚Äôs breadth, he might have taken this affair sentimentally. But clearly Anthony was no diplomatist. His brother-in-law must have appeared to him, to use the language of shore people, a perfect philistine with a heart like a flint. What Fyne precisely meant by ‚Äòwrangling‚Äô I don‚Äôt know, but I had no doubt that these two had ‚Äòwrangled‚Äô to a profoundly disturbing extent. How much the other was affected I could not even imagine; but the man before me was quite amazingly upset.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòIn a four-wheeler! Take him on board!‚Äô I muttered, startled by the change in Fyne.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòThat‚Äôs the plan‚ÅÝ‚Äînothing less. If I am to believe what I have been told, his feet will scarcely touch the ground between the prison-gates and the deck of that ship.‚Äô

‚ÄúThe transformed Fyne spoke in a forcibly lowered tone which I heard without difficulty. The rumbling, composite noises of the street were hushed for a moment, during one of these sudden breaks in the traffic as if the stream of commerce had dried up at its source. Having an unobstructed view past Fyne‚Äôs shoulder, I was astonished to see that the girl was still there. I thought she had gone up long before. But there was her black slender figure, her white face under the roses of her hat. She stood on the edge of the pavement as people stand on the bank of a stream, very still, as if waiting‚ÅÝ‚Äîor as if unconscious of where she was. The three dismal, sodden loafers (I could see them too; they hadn‚Äôt budged an inch) seemed to me to be watching her. Which was horrible.

‚ÄúMeantime Fyne was telling me rather remarkable things‚ÅÝ‚Äîfor him. He declared first it was a mercy in a sense. Then he asked me if it were not real madness, to saddle one‚Äôs existence with such a perpetual reminder. The daily existence. The isolated sea-bound existence. To bring such an additional strain into the solitude already trying enough for two people was the craziest thing. Undesirable relations were bad enough on shore. One could cut them or at least forget their existence now and then. He himself was preparing to forget his brother-in-law‚Äôs existence as much as possible.

‚ÄúThat was the general sense of his remarks, not his exact words. I thought that his wife‚Äôs brother‚Äôs existence had never been very embarrassing to him but that now of course he would have to abstain from his allusions to the ‚Äòson of the poet‚ÅÝ‚Äîyou know.‚Äô I said ‚Äòyes, yes‚Äô in the pauses because I did not want him to turn round; and all the time I was watching the girl intently. I thought I knew now what she meant with her‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚ÄòHe was most generous.‚Äô Yes. Generosity of character may carry a man through any situation. But why didn‚Äôt she go then to her generous man? Why stand there as if clinging to this solid earth which she surely hated as one must hate the place where one has been tormented, hopeless, unhappy? Suddenly she stirred. Was she going to cross over? No. She turned and began to walk slowly close to the curbstone, reminding me of the time when I discovered her walking near the edge of a ninety-foot sheer drop. It was the same impression, the same carriage, straight, slim, with rigid head and the two hands hanging lightly clasped in front‚ÅÝ‚Äîonly now a small sunshade was dangling from them. I saw something fateful in that deliberate pacing towards the inconspicuous door with the words Hotel Entrance on the glass panels.

‚ÄúShe was abreast of it now and I thought that she would stop again; but no! She swerved rigidly‚ÅÝ‚Äîat the moment there was no one near her; she had that bit of pavement to herself‚ÅÝ‚Äîwith inanimate slowness as if moved by something outside herself.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòA confounded convict,‚Äô Fyne burst out.

‚ÄúWith the sound of that word offending my ears I saw the girl extend her arm, push the door open a little way and glide in. I saw plainly that movement, the hand put out in advance with the gesture of a sleepwalker.

‚ÄúShe had vanished, her black figure had melted in the darkness of the open door. For some time Fyne said nothing; and I thought of the girl going upstairs, appearing before the man. Were they looking at each other in silence and feeling they were alone in the world as lovers should at the moment of meeting? But that fine forgetfulness was surely impossible to Anthony the seaman directly after the wrangling interview with Fyne the emissary of an order of things which stops at the edge of the sea. How much he was disturbed I couldn‚Äôt tell because I did not know what that impetuous lover had had to listen to.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòGoing to take the old fellow to sea with them,‚Äô I said. ‚ÄòWell I really don‚Äôt see what else they could have done with him. You told your brother-in-law what you thought of it? I wonder how he took it.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòVery improperly,‚Äô repeated Fyne. ‚ÄòHis manner was offensive, derisive, from the first. I don‚Äôt mean he was actually rude in words. Hang it all, I am not a contemptible ass. But he was exulting at having got hold of a miserable girl.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòIt is pretty certain that she will be much less poor and miserable,‚Äô I murmured.

‚ÄúIt looked as if the exultation of Captain Anthony had got on Fyne‚Äôs nerves. ‚ÄòI told the fellow very plainly that he was abominably selfish in this,‚Äô he affirmed unexpectedly.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòYou did! Selfish!‚Äô I said rather taken aback. ‚ÄòBut what if the girl thought that, on the contrary, he was most generous.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòWhat do you know about it,‚Äô growled Fyne. The rents and slashes of his solemnity were closing up gradually but it was going to be a surly solemnity. ‚ÄòGenerosity! I am disposed to give it another name. No. Not folly,‚Äô he shot out at me as though I had meant to interrupt him. ‚ÄòStill another. Something worse. I need not tell you what it is,‚Äô he added with grim meaning.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòCertainly. You needn‚Äôt‚ÅÝ‚Äîunless you like,‚Äô I said blankly. Little Fyne had never interested me so much since the beginning of the de Barral-Anthony affair when I first perceived possibilities in him. The possibilities of dull men are exciting because when they happen they suggest legendary cases of ‚Äòpossession,‚Äô not exactly by the devil but, anyhow, by a strange spirit.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI told him it was a shame,‚Äô said Fyne. ‚ÄòEven if the girl did make eyes at him‚ÅÝ‚Äîbut I think with you that she did not. Yes! A shame to take advantage of a girl‚Äôs distress‚ÅÝ‚Äîa girl that does not love him in the least.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòYou think it‚Äôs so bad as that?‚Äô I said. ‚ÄòBecause you know I don‚Äôt.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòWhat can you think about it,‚Äô he retorted on me with a solemn stare. ‚ÄòI go by her letter to my wife.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòAh! that famous letter. But you haven‚Äôt actually read it,‚Äô I said.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòNo, but my wife told me. Of course it was a most improper sort of letter to write considering the circumstances. It pained Mrs.¬ÝFyne to discover how thoroughly she had been misunderstood. But what is written is not all. It‚Äôs what my wife could read between the lines. She says that the girl is really terrified at heart.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòShe had not much in life to give her any very special courage for it, or any great confidence in mankind. That‚Äôs very true. But this seems an exaggeration.‚Äô

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòI should like to know what reasons you have to say that,‚Äô asked Fyne with offended solemnity. ‚ÄòI really don‚Äôt see any. But I had sufficient authority to tell my brother-in-law that if he thought he was going to do something chivalrous and fine he was mistaken. I can see very well that he will do everything she asks him to do‚ÅÝ‚Äîbut, all the same, it is rather a pitiless transaction.‚Äô

‚ÄúFor a moment I felt it might be so. Fyne caught sight of an approaching tramcar and stepped out on the road to meet it. ‚ÄòHave you a more compassionate scheme ready?‚Äô I called after him. He made no answer, clambered on to the rear platform, and only then looked back. We exchanged a perfunctory wave of the hand. We also looked at each other, he rather angrily, I fancy, and I with wonder. I may also mention that it was for the last time. From that day I never set eyes on the Fynes. As usual the unexpected happened to me. It had nothing to do with Flora de Barral. The fact is that I went away. My call was not like her call. Mine was not urged on me with passionate vehemence or tender gentleness made all the finer and more compelling by the allurements of generosity which is a virtue as mysterious as any other but having a glamour of its own. No, it was just a prosaic offer of employment on rather good terms which, with a sudden sense of having wasted my time on shore long enough, I accepted without misgivings. And once started out of my indolence I went, as my habit was, very, very far away and for a long, long time. Which is another proof of my indolence. How far Flora went I can‚Äôt say. But I will tell you my idea: my idea is that she went as far as she was able‚ÅÝ‚Äîas far as she could bear it‚ÅÝ‚Äîas far as she had to‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶‚Äù